
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Automation Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/automation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 23:42:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Automation Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodeGen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Api documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[customer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&#160; The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1697 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/CustomrPoV3-02-1024x619.png" alt="SDKs and API documentation by APIMatic" width="744" height="450"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&nbsp; </span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum developer experience with the least onboarding problems.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automated SDK and API documentation generations are a sure way to boost API adoption while lifting the strain of repetitive tasks off developers. API provider companies from various industries like communication, fintech, and travel enjoy better team productivity and faster time to market as the time-consuming monotony of maintaining SDKs and API documentation is handled by APIMatic.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication APIs: Increased Developer Productivity for MessageMedia</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://messagemedia.com/us/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform that offers communication services between its customers’ workforce.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sending over a billion messages per year and servicing thousands of global customers required a streamlined developer experience to integrate their various messaging APIs, and manually updating SDKs on each update was not optimal.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the problems we had with our SDKs was if a new feature was added to the API, we would have to manually make the code changes to the SDKs itself. Given we have 6 SDKs for each of our APIs, it was a long and inefficient process to update.” — Ibrahim Tareq, Developer Evangelist</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine, MessageMedia was able to auto-generate SDKs in all of the required languages, and the SDKs could reflect changes in the API on the go, which had been a pain point for the team.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It has helped reduce the barrier of entry… you can hand out SDKs to your customers and make it easier and simpler for them to code their way to the first ‘hello world’.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/messagemedia-speaking-the-language-of-developers-with-apimatic-codegen-5a3a7ad17d8e"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with Autogenerated SDKs</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fintech APIs: Revenue Generator for Fortune 500 Fintech</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">This leading financial services giant provides access to the world’s largest independent payment network to almost any country in the world through API integrations.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hence, this company was quick to realize that in order to obtain partnerships and integrations with third parties, they needed to reach out to a larger developer community and ensure that their APIs were adopted faster. They began offering .NET and Java SDKs for their APIs, which were built in-house, but maintaining them took the time that could instead be spent on expanding their API landscape with the growing demand.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Writing SDKs for just two languages was a pretty time consuming and expensive </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">process, every time we had a release that affected those services, it would increase </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">our sprints and dev timelines” &#8211; Head of Innovation</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine streamlined their process in the form of automatically generated SDKs and API documentation for six languages instead of two, directly from their API definition files. This resulted in cost savings of hundreds of thousands of dollars compared to building SDKs and docs in-house while reducing their time to market the APIs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Fast go-to-market time for documentation, and then the ability to generate SDKs in </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">multiple languages; those were the things that attracted us to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/fintech/a-fortune-500-fintech-company/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How APIMatic Became a Revenue Generator for a Fortune 500 Fintech</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Operation Management APIs: From 1 Week to 18 Seconds with Dude Solutions</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.dudesolutions.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a leading software-as-a-service (SaaS) provider of operations management solutions for education, government, healthcare, and many industries.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">They have two front-facing REST APIs that drive their platform and are supported by a set of micro-services that specialize in different areas.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions realized early on that with SDKs, they would have sharable software that could be used across the entire platform. It would reduce the amount of code in each API stack and understand the security protocols. However, they started by creating the SDKs from scratch and soon enough found out that it was just as long a process as API development.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We learned that it takes almost as long to do the API implementation as it did the SDK development. In fact, it took one week to develop the SDK for a single language.” &#8211; Brian Hyder, Engineering Manager</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When they began designing their next micro-service, Dude Solutions started looking for alternate ways for SDK development and came across APIMatic. The autogeneration of SDKs in multiple languages helped drastically cut down SDK development and maintenance costs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Development time for SDKs for each language went from 1 week to 18 seconds thanks to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1695 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/dude-solutions.png" alt="" width="603" height="393"></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While they had initially planned to provide SDKs in 3 languages, the significant time and cost reduction enabled them to provide SDKs for 7 languages with APIMatic’s autogenerated SDKs.</span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/automate-all-the-things-how-dude-solutions-saved-20-000-in-development-costs-using-apimatic-f9c05118f041"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Dude Solutions Cut Down Time to Release from 1 Week to 18 Seconds</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel APIs: Client Onboarding Time Reduced by 20% for Didgigo</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.didgigo.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a digital media platform that assists travel agents in organizing and maintaining data, as well as creating detailed itinerary proposals that save time and boost sales opportunities for clients.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo offers APIs that allow travel experts to create travel documents for their clients automatically and publish both digital and print versions at the same time. However, for a firm that excels at offering automated tailor-made solutions to its clients, it became critical to find a solution that could shorten the API onboarding time for customers, without the engineering team having to context switch on each release.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our process was extremely manual and required a lot of back and forth” &#8211; Keanu Ashwell, Development Operations Engineer</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s autogenerated documentation in multiple languages, Didgigo is able to shift its focus on building robust APIs, without having to devote time and resources to maintain the documentation. The customer onboarding process has become more streamlined, with tickets raised during onboarding being <strong>reduced by 11-20%</strong>, and customer onboarding meetings going down by more than 7 meetings per quarter.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our experience with APIMatic and its provisions has been exceptional. We haven&#8217;t had </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">much time to maintain everything as we&#8217;re still strapped for resources due to COVID-19, </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">but we&#8217;ve still been able to rely on APIMatic to give our API users an understanding of </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">what functionality we expose via our APIs. The ability to test [the APIs] is also a feature I </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">love and something that drew me to the service when we migrated from our in-house Swagger solution.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/api-portal/didgigo/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Didgigo Reduces Client Onboarding Time with Autogenerated Documentation</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthcare/Senior Living APIs: Time to Release Down by 30% for Caremerge</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://caremerge.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">is an </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">all-in-one platform that empowers families, residents, and staff of senior citizens by </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">providing tools for modern elder care including family engagement, community engagement, chronic care management, and more.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge also uses various pre-existing services to make them more accessible for these senior citizens, for example with voice commands. However, managing all these services in a single platform requires multiple internal microservices and a public API.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Caremerge API powers communication between the services they offer and allows them to build integrations with various third-party vendors and services. Building those integrations requires the documentation for the API to be always updated, so developers spend less time figuring out how to integrate.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using APIMatic’s autogenerated API documentation with the API playground allows developers to test inputs and outputs within the docs, resulting in quicker integration of the API, and helps Caremerge cut down on time spent on maintenance.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">“APIMatic helps us save 20–30% of the time it took us to manage documentation for our API” &#8211; </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder, and CTO</span></em></span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api-734da95b2d9b"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge</span></a></p>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quicker synchronization of documentation and SDKs with APIs leads to shorter sprints and faster time to market. With a mission to make API consumption as simple as possible, APIMatic considers it a victory when our</span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> customers’ APIs are consumed</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more readily with our autogenerated SDKs and documentation.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Insight into APIMatic’s Autogenerated SDKs</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/02/an-insight-into-apimatics-autogenerated-sdks/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arooj Arshad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 11:44:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CLI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodeGen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Apimatic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Generation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1665</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How can you reduce client onboarding of your API so that the API user quickly gets to their first &#8220;Hello World&#8221;? One definitive way is to provide an SDK for a developer&#8217;s technology stack so that they can easily integrate your APIs onto their native platforms. By providing an SDK, it becomes much simpler for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/an-insight-into-apimatics-autogenerated-sdks/">An Insight into APIMatic’s Autogenerated SDKs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div class="">
<p class=""><img class=" wp-image-1675 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/updated-pic.png" alt="Generate SDK" width="572" height="404"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">How can you reduce client onboarding of your API so that the API user quickly gets to their first &#8220;Hello World&#8221;?</span> <span style="font-weight: 400">One definitive way is to provide an SDK for a developer&#8217;s technology stack so that they can easily integrate your APIs onto their native platforms.</span><span style="font-weight: 400"> By providing an SDK, it becomes much simpler for a developer to integrate your API in ways that are familiar and well-integrated with their existing toolchain</span><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">In simpler terms, it is no longer enough to expose your API endpoints with just HTTP documentation or API references. You need to attract developers to enable them to comfortably play around with your code, and this is what APIMatic SDKs help with.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic as a Code Generator</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://www.apimatic.io/"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400"> autogenerates SDKs </span><span style="font-weight: 400">f</span><span style="font-weight: 400">or APIs automatically in all major programming languages so that developers can consume APIs in their favorite development environment with less code, less effort, and more fun</span><span style="font-weight: 400">. </span><span style="font-weight: 400">These </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/overview-sdks/"><span style="font-weight: 400">comprehensive SDKs</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400"> help accelerate the API consumption process as they can be automatically generated and shipped along with your latest API update. They accurately map your API definition files into their respective classes and controllers while adhering to the best coding practices. APIMatic further provides flexibility to customize code generation through </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/configure-codegen/"><span style="font-weight: 400">Customizable CodeGen Settings</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">. APIMatic generates SDKs in the following languages:</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">PHP</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Ruby</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Python</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">C# (.NET)</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Java</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">TypeScript</span></li>
</ul>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Building and maintaining these feature-packed SDKs from scratch is not easy and requires extensive engineering time and effort. However, autogenerated SDKs can significantly cut down costs and time.</span> <span style="font-weight: 400">For more detailed pros and cons of manually generating SDKs against autogenerating them, read here on </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://www.apimatic.io/blog/2021/09/the-great-sdk-battle-build-vs-buy/"><span style="font-weight: 400">The Great SDK Battle: Build vs Buy</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">How does APIMatic Autogenerate SDKs?</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">SDK generation is a tricky challenge for API providers. On one side, you want to keep SDKs with minimal code and dependencies and on the other hand, you want to customize the generated code according to the needs of the developers. APIMatic gives you an easy solution by providing autogenerated SDKs for your APIs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic’s Code Generation Engine follows several steps internally to generate client libraries from API definition files. The code generation process starts with an input API definition file which can be in any of the multiple supported </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://www.apimatic.io/transformer/#supported-formats"><span style="font-weight: 400">API definition formats</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400"> like OpenAPI, RAML, API Blueprint, etc.</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li><b>API Transformation: </b><span style="font-weight: 400">This step transforms the input API definition file into APIMatic&#8217;s format which contains useful information for SDK generation that is not available in other API definition formats.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>API Validation:</b> <span style="font-weight: 400">After an input file is transformed into APIMatic’s format, it is validated. The validation process includes checking for syntactical and semantical discrepancies in the API definition and shows critical warnings and errors to be fixed before SDK generation can proceed.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>SDK Generation: </b><span style="font-weight: 400">Now, components of the API definition are looped over to generate code representations. While a basic SDK caters to settings, endpoints, and an abstraction layer, APIMatic goes an extra step by mapping your API completely into an SDK</span><span style="font-weight: 400">. </span><span style="font-weight: 400">Some important entity conversions from an API definition to an SDK are:</span>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Settings -&gt; Configuration files:</b><span style="font-weight: 400"> All API settings like environment configuration etc are consolidated in a configuration file.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Endpoints -&gt; Functions:</b><span style="font-weight: 400"> Each endpoint maps onto an independent function.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Groups -&gt; Controller class files:</b><span style="font-weight: 400"> Endpoints are automatically grouped into separate Controller classes.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Models -&gt; Model class files:</b><span style="font-weight: 400"> Data input is converted into models.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Errors -&gt; Exception class files:</b><span style="font-weight: 400"> Errors are handled as exceptions via a unified exception class.&nbsp;</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp; &nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp; &nbsp; Apart from these core files, the CodeGen engine also generates the following utility files:</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="list-style-type: none">
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400;text-align: left"><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp;HTTP abstraction layer</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;text-align: left"><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp;Helper class files</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;text-align: left"><span style="font-weight: 400">Client library interface</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;text-align: left"><span style="font-weight: 400">Language/platform-dependent files</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><b>Documentation Generation: </b><span style="font-weight: 400">Every generated SDK also includes a README.md file. The README contains complete class reference and code samples for the SDK and guides the user on setting up the environment (using tool-specific IDEs), initializing the client, creating the controller, calling the endpoints, and testing them.&nbsp;</span></li>
<li><b>Packaging:</b> <span style="font-weight: 400">After all the SDK files have been generated, there are multiple packaging options available to APIMatic users. You can either get the SDK packaged in a zip file, have it deployed to GitHub, or </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/publishing-a-package/"><span style="font-weight: 400">publish it as a package</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400"> on platforms like npm, NuGet, RubyGems, and PyPI.</span></li>
</ul>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">For more detail on the mapping from an API specification file to SDK, please refer to the </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/overview-sdks/"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic SDK O</span>verview</a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Features Supported in APIMatic&#8217;s Autogenerated SDKs&nbsp;</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic SDKs supports the latest versions and language dependencies, along with features that make them as robust and fault-tolerant as possible.</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>Immutable Clients for Multi-Threading</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">An</span><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/changelog/apimatic-code-generator-v3-titan#new-immutable-clients-in-sdks"> <span style="font-weight: 400">Immutable Client</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400"> does not allow the user of the client to mutate the client (i.e change its state) once it has been created.</span> <span style="font-weight: 400">Client classes of all the SDKs are designed using the immutable design pattern. This gives developers the assurity that no method call would mutate its state once the client is instantiated.</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>Timeout and Retries on API Call Errors</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic generated SDKs help you write fault-tolerant applications by helping deal with network fault errors. If an API call fails due to network problems, it is retried with an exponentially increasing wait time up to a maximum retry count specified by the user. This is particularly helpful during temporary network outages.</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>Support for XML in API Calls</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">The SDKs contain support for </span><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/changelog/apimatic-code-generator-v3-titan#support-for-xml"><span style="font-weight: 400">sending and receiving XML</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400"> in the API calls, alongside JSON. So if your API definition uses XML, it can be imported into APIMatic to generate SDKs without having to worry about serializing and deserializing the XML data.</span><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>oneOf and anyOf Support</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Java, Python, and PHP SDKs contain the support of <strong>oneOf</strong> and <strong>anyOf</strong> which gives the ability to create a complex schema or validate a value against multiple criteria.</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>Support for Nullable Properties in Models</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">J</span><span style="font-weight: 400">ava and C# SDKs contain nullable properties in models, so if a user does not assign any value to a property after model instance initialization, a null value will be sent in the HTTP request instead of being skipped altogether.</span></p>
<p class=""><strong>Access to HTTP Response Data</strong></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">The SDKs also allow access to the HTTP response information like response headers, status code, and body on API calls. </span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Other features in the SDKs include optimized error messages, handling cancellation of API calls, and more. For more information and details on all the features that APIMatic SDKs provide, have a look at our </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/sdk-features/"><span style="font-weight: 400">SDK Features List</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">How to Generate SDKs from API Definitions?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">Next, comes the part where you can generate your SDKs via various options according to your specified use case:</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/generating-sdks/#generate-sdks-via-web"><span style="font-weight: 400">Web</span></a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/generating-sdks/#generate-sdks-via-api"><span style="font-weight: 400">API</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp;</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/generating-sdks/#generate-sdks-via-apimatic-cli"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic CLI</span></a></span></li>
</ul>
<h3 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Generate SDKs through Web</span></h3>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">You can generate an SDK for any API definition file in your favorite language through our </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://www.apimatic.io/dashboard"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic dashboard</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">. Select any API or its version from the dashboard and generate the SDK via the ‘Generate’</span> <span style="font-weight: 400">button. After the validation process, you can choose to download the SDK as a zip file, deploy it to Github or publish it as a package.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_1668" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1668" style="width: 590px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-full wp-image-1668" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/generation-options.png" alt="" width="590" height="582"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1668" class="wp-caption-text">&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Generating SDK Options</figcaption></figure>
<h3 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Generate SDKs through API</span></h3>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">You can automate the process of SDK generation using</span> <span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://www.apimatic.io/apidocs/apimatic/"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic&#8217;s CodeGen API</span></a>,<span style="color: #000000"> by integrating it into your CI/CD pipelines</span></span><span style="font-weight: 400">. </span><span style="font-weight: 400">You can generate SDKs for APIs already imported into APIMatic, any external API, or by specifying a URL. The generated SDKs are downloaded as a zip file in your system.</span></p>
<pre class=""><code class="language-cs">{
    string apiEntityId = &quot;apiEntityId2&quot;; 
    Platforms template = Platforms.CSNETSTANDARDLIB; 

    try { &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
            APIEntityCodeGeneration result = await codeGenerationImportedApisController
                                                        .GenerateSDKAsync(apiEntityId, template); 
        } 
    catch (ApiException e) {};
}</code></pre>
<h3 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Generate SDKs through APIMatic CLI</span><span style="font-weight: 400">&nbsp;</span></h3>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">You can also integrate the </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/apimatic-cli/intro-and-install/"><span style="font-weight: 400">APIMatic CLI</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400"> into your CI/CD pipelines for a seamless and automated experience. APIMatic CLI supports all the basic features like validation, transformation, SDK, and documentation generation. You can generate an SDK for your API through the CLI via the <strong>apimatic SDK:generate</strong> command:&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1680 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cli-image.png" alt="apimatic-cli command to generate SDK" width="779" height="97"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">For more details, read our </span><span style="color: #3366ff"><a style="color: #3366ff" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/generating-sdks/"><span style="font-weight: 400">Generating SDKs via APIMatic Docs</span></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Wrapping it Up!</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400">Creating SDKs in multiple languages is quite resource-intensive and expensive. Good SDKs save both time and cognitive effort when integrating with a provider’s API. This is why APIMatic&#8217;s CodeGen engine gives you the maximum advantage in creating SDKs and takes care of all the SDK generation and maintenance work behind the scenes while your developers can focus on their applications and innovative solutions.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/an-insight-into-apimatics-autogenerated-sdks/">An Insight into APIMatic’s Autogenerated SDKs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Automating Developer Experience with APIMatic CLI</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/01/automate-dx-with-apimatic-cli/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 11:15:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Transformer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CLI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMatic CLI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1627</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>APIs act as a bridge to multiple tiers in distributed software systems. However, reflecting the changes of fast-evolving APIs among these connected tiers is a huge drain in productivity, and increases the time to market. This means that your software tiers must always remain in sync, and in an ideal world also minimize the redundancy [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/01/automate-dx-with-apimatic-cli/">Automating Developer Experience with APIMatic CLI</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class=" wp-image-9666 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Dev-Cycle-1024x690-1.png" alt="" width="549" height="370" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Dev-Cycle-1024x690-1.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Dev-Cycle-1024x690-1-300x202.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Dev-Cycle-1024x690-1-768x518.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 549px) 100vw, 549px" /></p>
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIs act as a bridge to multiple tiers in distributed software systems. However, reflecting the changes of fast-evolving APIs among these connected tiers is a huge drain in productivity, and increases the time to market. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">This means that your software tiers must always remain in sync, and in an ideal world also minimize the redundancy of generating documentation and SDKs on each update.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The <a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/apimatic-cli/intro-and-install/">APIMatic CLI</a> ensures that your developer experience checklist is in check at all times by automating the redundant, time and resource-consuming tasks of API validation, documentation, and SDK maintenance. The APIMatic CLI offers feature parity by providing automation in the form of:&nbsp;</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">API Validator</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">API Transformer&nbsp;</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDK Generator</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">API Portal Generator</span></li>
</ul>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can integrate the APIMatic CLI into your CI/CD pipelines for a seamless and automated experience. For example, every time your pipeline detects a change in the API, it can trigger </span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/continuous-code-generation/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">automatic code generation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for the API without any human intervention and you can ship updated SDKs as soon as the API is updated. </span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For a quick walkthrough of the newly introduced CLI, we’ll be using the Uber API specification.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Installing the APIMatic CLI</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Installing the CLI is quick and painless. You only need </span><b>Node.JS</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><b>npm </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">as a pre-requisite to execute the following command, and you’re good to go:</span></p>
<pre class=""><code class="language-bash">npm install -g @apimatic/cli</code></pre>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Validating the API for Unforeseen Errors</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Validating the API definition against robust internal checks ensures you have a smooth experience using APIMatic’s services. Fixing these validation issues before proceeding to generate portals or SDKs helps save debugging time. The </span><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/rulesets/overview/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">validation output</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is categorized into three categories defined below:</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b>Errors</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Any syntax/semantic issues found in the API definition.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b>Warnings</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Any unexpected behavior that may affect the output.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b>Info</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: Recommendations or suggestions that can help enhance your API definition and its completeness.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">To validate your API definition, run the </span><b>apimatic api:validate</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> command by providing the path to the file:</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1634 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/validation.png" alt="validate using CLI" width="637" height="91"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The API definition validated here does not seem to have any critical errors and warnings that need fixing, so we can move forward to either generate SDKs and API Portals or transform the API specification into another format.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Generating SDKs to Speak in the Language of Developers</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Once the API is validated, you can proceed to generate multi-language SDKs from the API definition, directly via the command line. The </span><b>apimatic sdk:generate</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> command generates an SDK in a specified language and downloads it to the specified destination folder.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, I generated a Python SDK from the Uber API using the APIMatic CLI:&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1631 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sdk.png" alt="" width="742" height="102"></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now check the destination folder, where the SDK has been downloaded in .zip form. Extracting the .zip file shows the complete SDK files, including a comprehensive README to use the SDK:</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1632 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sdk-downloaded.png" alt="sdk generation using cli" width="661" height="323"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can use your favorite IDE to start building applications using the Uber API SDK straightaway. To read more about APIMatic SDKs, please refer to the </span><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/generate-sdks/overview-sdks/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic SDK documentation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Generating API Portal for Higher Adoption</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic embraces the ‘documentation as code’ philosophy, allowing you to specify all aspects of the API documentation as code. The </span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">API Portal</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> bundles API documentation, SDKs, and code samples into a static website. Just like with all products of APIMatic, the API Portal can be generated right from the terminal as well, letting the entire process be made part of the release pipeline.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In order to generate an API Portal, the CLI expects inputs to be provided in a specific format:</span></p>
<ul class="">
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">content </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">directory containing Markdown guides.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">spec </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">directory containing API specifications.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">static </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">directory containing images or any other static content referenced in the documentation.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A configuration file called </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMATIC-BUILD.json</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></li>
</ul>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Place all the artifacts in a directory, including the Uber API under the </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">spec </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">directory:</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1629" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/portal-directory.png" alt="" width="281" height="194"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The </span><b>apimatic portal:generate</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> command takes the contents of this directory to convert it into a static portal’s components.</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1630 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/portal-generated.png" alt="portal generation using cli" width="624" height="80"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The static website can now be hosted on a hosting service of your choice, let’s say by creating a website on Netlify, and the Uber API portal is live:</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1628 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/cli-portal.gif" alt="APIMatic CLI Portal" width="1346" height="634"></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Transforming the API into Multiple API Formats</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can also automatically transform your API into more than </span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/transformer/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">10 popular API specification formats</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> including OpenAPI, RAML, API Blueprint, WSDL, Postman, and more. Many APIMatic users integrate automated transformations into their CI/CD pipelines via the Transformer API, which helps them take away the pain of having to manually rewrite the APIs. The same process can be replicated with a script that executes the CLI command for Transformer as well.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The following example shows how the </span><b>apimatic api:transform</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> command converts the Uber API (in OpenAPI 3.0 format) to RAML, and saves it to a specific directory:&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1633 size-full" src="https://devapi.dream.press/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/transformed.png" alt="transform using cli" width="682" height="130"></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Conclusion</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automation lets developers concentrate on business objectives and innovative solutions instead of diverting their time and efforts towards redundant tasks like maintaining documentation and building SDKs for each API update. Hence, the APIMatic CLI has been introduced as yet another automation option </span><a href="http://apimatic.io/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">among our growing toolset</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> so you only need to focus on your API, while we take care of the rest.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/01/automate-dx-with-apimatic-cli/">Automating Developer Experience with APIMatic CLI</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
