
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Case Studies Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/case-studies/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 14:47:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Case Studies Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodeGen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Api documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[customer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&#160; The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1697 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/CustomrPoV3-02-1024x619.png" alt="SDKs and API documentation by APIMatic" width="744" height="450"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&nbsp; </span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum developer experience with the least onboarding problems.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automated SDK and API documentation generations are a sure way to boost API adoption while lifting the strain of repetitive tasks off developers. API provider companies from various industries like communication, fintech, and travel enjoy better team productivity and faster time to market as the time-consuming monotony of maintaining SDKs and API documentation is handled by APIMatic.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication APIs: Increased Developer Productivity for MessageMedia</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://messagemedia.com/us/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform that offers communication services between its customers’ workforce.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sending over a billion messages per year and servicing thousands of global customers required a streamlined developer experience to integrate their various messaging APIs, and manually updating SDKs on each update was not optimal.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the problems we had with our SDKs was if a new feature was added to the API, we would have to manually make the code changes to the SDKs itself. Given we have 6 SDKs for each of our APIs, it was a long and inefficient process to update.” — Ibrahim Tareq, Developer Evangelist</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine, MessageMedia was able to auto-generate SDKs in all of the required languages, and the SDKs could reflect changes in the API on the go, which had been a pain point for the team.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It has helped reduce the barrier of entry… you can hand out SDKs to your customers and make it easier and simpler for them to code their way to the first ‘hello world’.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/messagemedia-speaking-the-language-of-developers-with-apimatic-codegen-5a3a7ad17d8e"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with Autogenerated SDKs</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fintech APIs: Revenue Generator for Fortune 500 Fintech</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">This leading financial services giant provides access to the world’s largest independent payment network to almost any country in the world through API integrations.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hence, this company was quick to realize that in order to obtain partnerships and integrations with third parties, they needed to reach out to a larger developer community and ensure that their APIs were adopted faster. They began offering .NET and Java SDKs for their APIs, which were built in-house, but maintaining them took the time that could instead be spent on expanding their API landscape with the growing demand.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Writing SDKs for just two languages was a pretty time consuming and expensive </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">process, every time we had a release that affected those services, it would increase </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">our sprints and dev timelines” &#8211; Head of Innovation</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine streamlined their process in the form of automatically generated SDKs and API documentation for six languages instead of two, directly from their API definition files. This resulted in cost savings of hundreds of thousands of dollars compared to building SDKs and docs in-house while reducing their time to market the APIs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Fast go-to-market time for documentation, and then the ability to generate SDKs in </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">multiple languages; those were the things that attracted us to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/fintech/a-fortune-500-fintech-company/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How APIMatic Became a Revenue Generator for a Fortune 500 Fintech</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Operation Management APIs: From 1 Week to 18 Seconds with Dude Solutions</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.dudesolutions.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a leading software-as-a-service (SaaS) provider of operations management solutions for education, government, healthcare, and many industries.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">They have two front-facing REST APIs that drive their platform and are supported by a set of micro-services that specialize in different areas.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions realized early on that with SDKs, they would have sharable software that could be used across the entire platform. It would reduce the amount of code in each API stack and understand the security protocols. However, they started by creating the SDKs from scratch and soon enough found out that it was just as long a process as API development.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We learned that it takes almost as long to do the API implementation as it did the SDK development. In fact, it took one week to develop the SDK for a single language.” &#8211; Brian Hyder, Engineering Manager</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When they began designing their next micro-service, Dude Solutions started looking for alternate ways for SDK development and came across APIMatic. The autogeneration of SDKs in multiple languages helped drastically cut down SDK development and maintenance costs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Development time for SDKs for each language went from 1 week to 18 seconds thanks to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1695 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/dude-solutions.png" alt="" width="603" height="393"></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While they had initially planned to provide SDKs in 3 languages, the significant time and cost reduction enabled them to provide SDKs for 7 languages with APIMatic’s autogenerated SDKs.</span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/automate-all-the-things-how-dude-solutions-saved-20-000-in-development-costs-using-apimatic-f9c05118f041"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Dude Solutions Cut Down Time to Release from 1 Week to 18 Seconds</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel APIs: Client Onboarding Time Reduced by 20% for Didgigo</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.didgigo.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a digital media platform that assists travel agents in organizing and maintaining data, as well as creating detailed itinerary proposals that save time and boost sales opportunities for clients.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo offers APIs that allow travel experts to create travel documents for their clients automatically and publish both digital and print versions at the same time. However, for a firm that excels at offering automated tailor-made solutions to its clients, it became critical to find a solution that could shorten the API onboarding time for customers, without the engineering team having to context switch on each release.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our process was extremely manual and required a lot of back and forth” &#8211; Keanu Ashwell, Development Operations Engineer</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s autogenerated documentation in multiple languages, Didgigo is able to shift its focus on building robust APIs, without having to devote time and resources to maintain the documentation. The customer onboarding process has become more streamlined, with tickets raised during onboarding being <strong>reduced by 11-20%</strong>, and customer onboarding meetings going down by more than 7 meetings per quarter.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our experience with APIMatic and its provisions has been exceptional. We haven&#8217;t had </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">much time to maintain everything as we&#8217;re still strapped for resources due to COVID-19, </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">but we&#8217;ve still been able to rely on APIMatic to give our API users an understanding of </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">what functionality we expose via our APIs. The ability to test [the APIs] is also a feature I </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">love and something that drew me to the service when we migrated from our in-house Swagger solution.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/api-portal/didgigo/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Didgigo Reduces Client Onboarding Time with Autogenerated Documentation</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthcare/Senior Living APIs: Time to Release Down by 30% for Caremerge</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://caremerge.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">is an </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">all-in-one platform that empowers families, residents, and staff of senior citizens by </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">providing tools for modern elder care including family engagement, community engagement, chronic care management, and more.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge also uses various pre-existing services to make them more accessible for these senior citizens, for example with voice commands. However, managing all these services in a single platform requires multiple internal microservices and a public API.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Caremerge API powers communication between the services they offer and allows them to build integrations with various third-party vendors and services. Building those integrations requires the documentation for the API to be always updated, so developers spend less time figuring out how to integrate.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using APIMatic’s autogenerated API documentation with the API playground allows developers to test inputs and outputs within the docs, resulting in quicker integration of the API, and helps Caremerge cut down on time spent on maintenance.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">“APIMatic helps us save 20–30% of the time it took us to manage documentation for our API” &#8211; </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder, and CTO</span></em></span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api-734da95b2d9b"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge</span></a></p>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quicker synchronization of documentation and SDKs with APIs leads to shorter sprints and faster time to market. With a mission to make API consumption as simple as possible, APIMatic considers it a victory when our</span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> customers’ APIs are consumed</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more readily with our autogenerated SDKs and documentation.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge API</title>
		<link>/blog/2020/04/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>According to the United States Department of Health and Human Services, there are over 39.6 million elderly people in the US, out of which 1 Million are being actively served an elderly care facility. Today’s seniors want to better leverage technology to enhance their quality of life. The industry, estimated at $740 billion, is full [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/04/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api/">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge API</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="398" class="elementor elementor-398">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-144a492c elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="144a492c" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-72f7b65c" data-id="72f7b65c" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-6bc5822 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="6bc5822" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
			<style>/*! elementor - v3.6.4 - 13-04-2022 */
.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-stacked .elementor-drop-cap{background-color:#818a91;color:#fff}.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-framed .elementor-drop-cap{color:#818a91;border:3px solid;background-color:transparent}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap{margin-top:8px}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap-letter{width:1em;height:1em}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap{float:left;text-align:center;line-height:1;font-size:50px}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap-letter{display:inline-block}</style>				<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="alignnone wp-image-399" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_aYem2QZt6J4QK6bCUJh3OA-1024x519.png" alt="Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge API - APIMatic Success story" width="1024" height="519"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="c78a" class="">According to the United States Department of Health and Human Services, there are over 39.6 million elderly people in the US, out of which 1 Million are being actively served an elderly care facility. Today’s seniors want to better leverage technology to enhance their quality of life. The industry, estimated at $740 billion, is full of challenges and is ready for disruption.</p>
<p id="c45a" class=""><a href="https://caremerge.com/">Caremerge</a>&nbsp;is one of the companies providing tools for modern elder care, including an API platform to drive apps and integrations. Partnering with APIMatic saved the Caremerge team lots of time and made it easy for others to build with their API.</p>
<p id="5757" class="">The company aims to provide an all in one platform to address all problems that challenge the demographic including Family Engagement, Community Engagement, Calendar Central, and Chronic Care Management. Additionally, they bring in various pre-existing services from the market and make them more accessible for these senior citizens, for instance with voice commands. Something which they manage using multiple internal microservices and a public API.</p>
<p id="9806" class="">Caremerge API powers much of the communication between the facilities and services they offer, and allows them to build integrations with various third-party vendors and services. Building those integrations requires the documentation for the API to be always upto the mark, meeting all modern standards, so developers spend less time figuring out how to integrate.</p>
<p id="364b" class="">But maintaining and producing documentation is a challenge of its own, something which took them valuable resource and time. Since the product is very technical, they had a senior engineer working on documentation. To save time for that resource they decided to automate documentation and started looking for an out of the box documentation solution. Trying multiple open source and paid solutions including Swagger UI, they found a lot of them hard to maintain. Until they came across APIMatic, which not only did the job for them by producing better than ever documentation, but did it in record saving time, while completely minimising the effort at their end.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“APIMatic helps us save 20–30% of the time it took us to manage documentation for our API”</p>
<cite>Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder and CTO, Caremerge</cite></blockquote>
<p id="d696" class="">Often documentation can get too wordy and hard to navigate, but according to Caremerge, their customers and partners loved the way information was laid out for them.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“ APIMatic has made integrating so easy for us. Whenever our partners go through the documentation, they know just what to do.”</p>
<cite>Muneeb Khawaja, VP Engineering, Caremerge</cite></blockquote>
<p id="f915" class="">What added wow factor to the documentation, was the interactive console, which allowed developers to test inputs and outputs, within the docs, allowing developers to back and forth with the API. Today CareMerge is working on more integrations that ever, helping seniors through out America live reasonably enhanced lives.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default">
<p>“Integrations built with APIMatic Documentation are benefitting over 30 thousand senior citizens ”</p>
<cite>Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder and CTO, Caremerge</cite></blockquote>
<p id="4050" class="">For us at APIMatic, it has always been a motto to make lives of developers easy, to make things comfortable for them, and those developers in turn contributing to enhance the quality of lives of our s<em>enior citizens,&nbsp;</em>is something which makes us really happy. Just like the medicare and healthcare industry, we are excited to see the senior living industry go through such a shift, and are delighted to be a part of it.</p>
<p class="">Thanks to&nbsp;Adam DuVander.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/04/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api/">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge API</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with APIMatic</title>
		<link>/blog/2018/10/how-messagemedia-increases-developer-productivity-with-apimatic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 07:07:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MessageMedia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=1201</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>MessageMedia &#160;is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform with over 40,000 customers sending over 1.6 billion messages per year. With a focus on helping businesses boost ROIs more than 100x, MessageMedia offers services for appointment and payment reminders, marketing messages, authentication and verification and for communicating with their customers’ workforce. The Challenge: Creating and Maintaining [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/10/how-messagemedia-increases-developer-productivity-with-apimatic/">How MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with APIMatic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1201" class="elementor elementor-1201">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-4b03c2c0 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="4b03c2c0" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-3d605a20" data-id="3d605a20" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-143516bf elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="143516bf" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1gxI0N-DWeSMVRazK4Z8wEA.png" alt="" width="1400" height="700"></p>
<p id="c4e7" class="hd he ds hf b hg hh hi hj hk hl hm hn ho hp hq hr hs ht hu hv hw hx hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph=""><a class="cj ib" href="https://www.messagemedia.com/" rel="noopener">MessageMedia </a>&nbsp;is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform with over 40,000 customers sending over 1.6 billion messages per year.</p>
<p id="2867" class="hd he ds hf b hg hh hi hj hk hl hm hn ho hp hq hr hs ht hu hv hw hx hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">With a focus on helping businesses boost ROIs more than 100x, MessageMedia offers services for appointment and payment reminders, marketing messages, authentication and verification and for communicating with their customers’ workforce.</p>

<h2 id="e56d" class="ic id ds cd ie if ig hi ih ii ij hm ik il im in io ip iq ir is it iu iv iw ix ep">The Challenge: Creating and Maintaining SDKs</h2>
<p id="dccc" class="hd he ds hf b hg iy hi hj hk iz hm hn ho ja hq hr hs jb hu hv hw jc hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">With communications going digital exponentially, MessageMedia successfully managed to overcome the challenge of providing 99.99% gateway uptime with its robust and high-performance networking infrastructure. However, this also meant MessageMedia’s developer relations team had to focus on increasing adoption and ensuring that developers had all the resources required to easily integrate their APIs. Sending over a billion messages per year and servicing thousands of global customers required a streamlined developer experience to integrate their various messaging APIs.</p>
<p id="7bda" class="hd he ds hf b hg hh hi hj hk hl hm hn ho hp hq hr hs ht hu hv hw hx hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">The team at MessageMedia understood that for ensuring seamless integration of their APIs, offering SDKs and code samples was an utmost necessity. But they also soon came to realize that manually producing and maintaining SDKs in 6 languages for each API update was not cutting it.</p>

<blockquote class="jd">
<p id="440a" class="je jf ds dt b jg jh ji jj jk jl ia cg" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="jm">“One of the problems we had with our SDKs was if a new feature was added to the API, we would have to manually make the code changes to the SDKs itself. Given we have 6 SDKs for each of our APIs, it was a long and inefficient process to update.”&nbsp;</em>— Ibrahim Tareq, Developer Evangelist at MessageMedia.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="0502" class="ic id ds cd ie if ig hi ih ii ij hm ik il jn in io ip jo ir is it jp iv iw ix ep">The Solution: APIMatic’s Auto-generated SDKs</h2>
<p id="16c2" class="hd he ds hf b hg iy hi hj hk iz hm hn ho ja hq hr hs jb hu hv hw jc hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">This is where APIMatic was able to meet MessageMedia’s requirements to increase API adoption and leverage their position across multiple platforms. With APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine, MessageMedia was able to <a href="https://apimatic.io/blog/2018/11/how-to-create-sdks-for-your-api-in-less-than-a-minute">auto-generate SDKs</a> in all of the required languages, and the SDKs could reflect changes in the API on the go, which had been a pain point for the team before.</p>

<blockquote class="jd">
<p id="5ba1" class="je jf ds dt b jg jh ji jj jk jl ia cg" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="jm">“APIMatic has helped eliminate the manual effort that was required to set up and get the SDKs running. There is quite a lot of work involved in writing all of that code”, says Ibrahim.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p id="87d3" class="hd he ds hf b hg jq hi hj hk jr hm hn ho js hq hr hs jt hu hv hw ju hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">MessageMedia certainly gained an edge with APIMatic’s auto-generated SDKs. Now they can ship SDKs to customers in a number of languages within minutes, while keeping the SDKs up-to-date at all times. The time to market has been significantly reduced, as the CodeGen Engine can generate an SDK as soon as an update to API is made, and even automate this process in CI/CD pipelines.</p>
<p id="7c19" class="hd he ds hf b hg hh hi hj hk hl hm hn ho hp hq hr hs ht hu hv hw hx hy hz ia dk ep" data-selectable-paragraph="">MessageMedia’s developer customer base has found it much easier to adopt MessageMedia APIs through the auto-generated SDKs and comprehensive documentation that comes with them for each language and IDE.</p>

<blockquote class="jd">
<p id="078e" class="je jf ds dt b jg jh ji jj jk jl ia cg" data-selectable-paragraph=""><em class="jm">“It has helped reduce the barrier of entry… you can hand out SDKs to your customers and make it easier and simpler for them to code their way to the first ‘hello world’.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/10/how-messagemedia-increases-developer-productivity-with-apimatic/">How MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with APIMatic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
