
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Code Samples Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/code-samples/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 09:16:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Code Samples Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>[Webinar Recap] Low API Adoption: Have You Blamed Your API Portal Yet?</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/04/webinar-recap-low-api-adoption-have-you-blamed-your-api-portal-yet/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 13:02:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Webinar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=24543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You create a great API and invest resources, time, and energy into it, but it turns out it’s not being adopted as much as you had anticipated. While your first instinct might be to investigate the API, there could be other factors at play here. For starters, is your API documentation in-sync with the API? [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/04/webinar-recap-low-api-adoption-have-you-blamed-your-api-portal-yet/">[Webinar Recap] Low API Adoption: Have You Blamed Your API Portal Yet?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>You create a great API and invest resources, time, and energy into it, but it turns out it’s not being adopted as much as you had anticipated. While your first instinct might be to investigate the API, there could be other factors at play here.<br><br>For starters, is your API documentation in-sync with the API? Do you provide only HTTP references or language-specific documentation? Are there any code samples that your API users can copy-paste directly onto their IDEs? Are there any SDKs that your users can integrate easily into their applications?<br><br>This might become a little overwhelming until you shift your perspective to how your API users are interacting with your API. Understanding your API user’s journey can help you identify where your API Portal may need more focus, so we break that journey into three phases:<br></p>



<ul><li>Discovery</li><li>Exploration</li><li>Integration</li></ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Dty2T3dFow2x0t13mbRYRuMv9b3rBDv_-7m2MK_L0CJ8zeYOwTbTPGVIg8pQkzbOVIsMr89EW0pETGJjDFS38Gae4FzK6S5K60z383z82bGlke35NmQEUoSXeFuM8wTcWwxn9fU" alt=""/></figure>



<p>In <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pRl2JNwgu3g&amp;ab_channel=APIMaticOfficial" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this webinar</a>, APIMatic’s Chief Product Architect, Mehdi Raza, and API Problem Solver, Keith Casey, present this perspective in detail and how mapping your API Portal’s features against each phase make it much easier to create a streamlined developer experience for your users. This eventually results in more adoption of your API as you provide them an experience for their use case specifically.</p>



<p>Mehdi goes through examples of existing API portals from the API consumer’s point of view and discusses the landing page, language-specific documentation styles, good and bad code samples, SDKs, and more. The interactive presentation is followed by an informative and conversational Q&amp;A session, one question being:&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><em>Q: If you could make one improvement to any API portal, what would be the one thing that people would benefit most from?</em></strong></p>



<p>A: <em>The one thing that people can benefit most in the explore phase especially is getting the use-cases of your API users laid properly, and figuring out which ones are the most important. So that you can make them the front piece of your API portal, and it helps out your API users straight away.</em></p>



<h2>Webinar Notes</h2>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=19">0:17</a>] Introduction and premise</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=177">2:58</a>] Low adoption after your API launch, what went wrong?</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=348">5:48</a>] Understanding the API consumer journey</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=646">10:48</a>] Optimizing the API Portal for the Discovery phase</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=668">11:10</a>] Experiments for webinar viewers (good and bad API Portal)</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=1004">16:48</a>] Optimizing the API Portal for the Exploration phase</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=1420">23:47</a>] Optimizing the API Portal for the Integration phase</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=1583">26:28</a>] Code samples: best and worst practices</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=1994">33:10</a>] SDKs: why are they important, and how are Stripe and other big names using them?</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=2265">37:52</a>] Last trick: the secret behind API adoption revealed</p>



<p>[<a href="https://youtu.be/pRl2JNwgu3g?t=2434">40:35</a>] Q&amp;A session</p>



<h2>Watch The Webinar</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="[Webinar] Low API Adoption: Have You Blamed Your API Portal Yet?" width="653" height="367" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRl2JNwgu3g?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2>Additional Resources</h2>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">APIMatic Developer Experience Portal</a></li><li><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/continuous-code-generation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Code Generation-as-a-Service</a></li><li><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/blog/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How are SDKs and Docs Helping API Businesses?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/blog/the-great-sdk-battle-build-vs-buy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Great SDK Battle: Build vs Buy</a></li></ul>



<p>For any questions, comments, or feedback, please visit <a href="http://apimatic.io/">our website</a> or <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/request-demo/">request a demo</a> with our experts.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/04/webinar-recap-low-api-adoption-have-you-blamed-your-api-portal-yet/">[Webinar Recap] Low API Adoption: Have You Blamed Your API Portal Yet?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</title>
		<link>/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DuVander]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 10:32:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Calls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Direct API Calls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What&#8217;s it like to call your API? Developers want to use your API to accomplish something, and you want to make it as easy as possible for them to incorporate your service. To allow developers to call your API directly from any technology, your docs provide DIY instructions. To go a step further and give [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/">DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1519" class="elementor elementor-1519">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-7825289e elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="7825289e" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-5ad04015" data-id="5ad04015" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-687f92af elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="687f92af" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
			<style>/*! elementor - v3.6.4 - 13-04-2022 */
.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-stacked .elementor-drop-cap{background-color:#818a91;color:#fff}.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-framed .elementor-drop-cap{color:#818a91;border:3px solid;background-color:transparent}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap{margin-top:8px}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap-letter{width:1em;height:1em}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap{float:left;text-align:center;line-height:1;font-size:50px}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap-letter{display:inline-block}</style>				<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1552 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/dx-of-sdks-vs-api-calls-1024x459.png" alt="" width="771" height="346"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">What&#8217;s it like to call your API? Developers want to use your API to accomplish something, and you want to make it as easy as possible for them to incorporate your service. To allow developers to call your API directly from any technology, your docs provide DIY instructions. To go a step further and give developers additional conveniences and tooling, you can provide Software Development Kits (SDKs). SDKs include code to call your API so that developers don&#8217;t have to write it themselves from scratch.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While calling an API directly vs. using an SDK does not change the ultimate functionality of the API, it can dramatically affect the developer experience. In most cases, one method will be preferred over the other, varying according to each developer’s needs, preferences, and skills. An SDK offers simplicity and speedier development but applies only to a particular development framework. SDKs require resources to develop and maintain. Direct calls offer platform flexibility and are available to all developers, but are harder to use without expertise.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In this article, we&#8217;ll be looking at why your developer experience may focus on direct API calls, SDKs, or both.</span></p>

<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Direct API Calls: The Basics</span></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">For communicating with a service, sending API calls directly to URL endpoints is the simplest way. Of course, when we say </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">simplest</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, we mean in terms of program complexity, not ease of use.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When using an API without an SDK, you make calls to its URL endpoints directly using standard internet protocol commands for transferring packets of information over the network. There&#8217;s no abstraction between you and the service, so every parameter must be written into the call. It must also conform to a standard format.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">An example of how to construct a direct API call using Python is shown in the code snippet below. Notice the URL for the API endpoint is specified explicitly, alongside required header parameters that describe the request. This information is bundled and transmitted using the <code>requests</code> library, which then receives any response data returned by the API and stores it in the <code>resp</code> variable. Note that the cost of deserialization is added here for the API call.</span></p>

<pre class=""><code class="language-python">import requests
from requests.structures import CaseInsensitiveDict

url = &quot;https://connect.squareup.com/v2/payments&quot;

headers = CaseInsensitiveDict()
headers[&quot;Square-Version&quot;] = &quot;2021-06-16&quot;
headers[&quot;Authorization&quot;] = &quot;Bearer ACCESS TOKEN&quot;
headers[&quot;Content-Type&quot;] = &quot;application/json&quot;

resp = requests.get(url, headers=headers)
print(resp.status_code)

decoded = jsonpickle.decode(resp.text)
</code></pre>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another example of a non-trivial API call can be seen here, pulled from the User Authentication documentation for the</span> <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/developers/documentation"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dropbox API</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1520" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1520" style="width: 790px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1520 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/dropbox-1024x677.png" alt="dropbox user authentication" width="790" height="523"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1520" class="wp-caption-text">Dropbox User Authentication Docs</figcaption></figure>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">For many developers, the need to specify every parameter is exactly what they want: the full power of the service at their fingertips.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Low-level control can be unnecessary and overwhelming, though, especially for new developers. With just the basic building blocks, it can become a challenge for developers to perform more complicated tasks.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not only can direct API calls be complicated to do correctly, but they can also be frustrating to try to troubleshoot. API response codes aren&#8217;t particularly specific when providing error messages; Many developers may give up after countless generic 404 errors.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ultimately, many developers will wish they could have something a little more prepared for them. For those developers, you can please them by offering SDKs in their language.</span></p>

<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs: What Are They?</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs are a compilation of environment-specific developer tools designed to access your API. SDKs make it more straightforward for developers to use your API using a programming language framework they prefer. For the developer who wants a little more guidance, SDKs will be the most appealing way for them to access your service.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs abstract away the minutiae of the API that often bog down implementation for developers. They can be thought of as an API wrapper that makes accessing that API more friendly to a particular type of developer. A developer has to download and install an SDK that matches the language of their development environment, where it will then provide a host of streamlined functionalities for interacting with your API. If the developer is using Python, for instance, they’ll most likely download an SDK through pip, such as this example from </span><a href="https://www.algolia.com/doc/guides/getting-started/quick-start/tutorials/quick-start-with-the-api-client/python/?client=python"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Algolia’s documentation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1521" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1521" style="width: 721px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1521 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/algolia-1024x350.png" alt="Algolia Documentation" width="721" height="247"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1521" class="wp-caption-text">Algolia SDK download through pip</figcaption></figure>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The example call to Dropbox&#8217;s API, shown earlier, constructed with their Python SDK is shown below. In contrast to a direct API call, it does not require the developer to hard code a URL and headers. Instead, the API token is passed to a provided client object that handles those details.</span></p>

<pre class=""><code class="language-python">import dropbox
token = &#039;My-API-Token&#039;
dbx = dropbox.Dropbox(token)

My_Field = dropbox.file_properties.PropertyField(&#039;Security Policy&#039;,&#039;Confidential&#039;)
My_Template_ID = &#039;ptid:1...&#039;
My_Property_Group = dropbox.file_properties.PropertyGroup(template_id=My_Template_ID, fields=[My_Field])

dbx.file_properties_properties_add(&quot;/my_awesome/word.docx&quot;, My_Property_Group)
</code></pre>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">While APIs aren&#8217;t language-specific, SDKs are. A developer will download the SDK for the specific language they want to work with. API providers that intend to offer SDKs have to research what languages most appeal to their core user base. Developers who have the use of an SDK will be incredibly satisfied by the bevy of tools made available for them, including, but not limited to:</span>
<ul class="">
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Autocomplete SDK commands inline</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Code samples for commands</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Example applications</span></li>
</ul>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">A beneficial everyday use case where SDKs are much easier to use than direct API calls is when developers need to perform complicated authentication procedures. Doing this correctly and securely with only direct API calls can be tricky, but most SDKs take these steps and make them easily implementable with just a few commands. The low-level API call parameters and structure are abstracted away from the developer and handled by the SDK.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">In many ways, SDKs are the epitome of one of the main purposes of APIs: to give the developer the ability to build off existing technology as easily and quickly as possible.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For many developers, SDKs are the preferred method of interacting with APIs. For others, there are cases for making direct API calls without an SDK. Now that we&#8217;ve looked at both options let&#8217;s see why developers would lean towards one or the other.</span></p>

<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Choosing Between SDKs and Direct API Calls</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In an ideal world, there will be an SDK available to meet the developer’s exact needs. SDKs cost resources to produce and maintain, however. And even when SDKs are available, there are quite a few situations where the available SDKs might not work for what a developer wants to do. Just to list a few:</span></p>

<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">An SDK may not be available in their desired language</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The SDK may not be updated to incorporate new API features yet</span></li>
</ul>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In both of these situations, directly using the API might be the only option. After all, it takes time and effort for an API provider to build SDKs. If there&#8217;s only one Julia developer using your API who wants a Julia SDK, it might not justify the use of resources.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even for the SDKs of languages you deem popular enough to support, it takes time and effort to update those SDKs. Functionality added to an API yesterday may not be supported in the SDK by today.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For the vast majority of use cases, developers will appreciate having SDKs available and will eagerly use them. This is especially true for those who are making use of multiple APIs in their applications. For that reason, SDKs are worth the time and effort to develop for your primary user groups. The effort it takes to provide up-to-date SDKs will save them effort as they can seamlessly incorporate API calls into their app code.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">And for those edge case developers, those who code in esoteric languages, those who need maximum security control over what the API is doing, and those who want to be on the cutting edge no matter what, direct API calls are most useful.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">A great example of a company showing both direct API and SDK calls in their documentation is </span><a href="https://stripe.com/docs/api/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stripe</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1522" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1522" style="width: 576px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1522 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/stripe.gif" alt="Stripe API documentation showing both SDKs and API calls" width="576" height="296"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1522" class="wp-caption-text">Stripe API documentation showing both SDKs and API calls</figcaption></figure>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">Both direct API calls and SDKs are tools that you should make available in your developers&#8217; toolboxes. And the more tools at their disposal, the more effective your developers will be.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">At the end of the day, the goal of your developer experience should be improving the accessibility of your product to developers of all backgrounds. Providing SDKs is the best way to make your API a little more manageable for them to implement.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">
</span>Have a look at how <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal">APIMatic enhances the developer experience</a> of your API with robust SDKs auto-generated in all popular languages from a single API definition file.</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/">DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Anatomy of API Code Samples</title>
		<link>/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Sample]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hence it comes as no surprise why code samples make an important part of the developer experience checklist list for several APIs programs, including the likes of Amazon, Facebook, Twilio, and Stripe. All of them have code samples included one way or the other and have found massive success. And for a very good reason. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/">The Anatomy of API Code Samples</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="359" class="elementor elementor-359">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-2c773500 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="2c773500" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-41f291e6" data-id="41f291e6" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-7abbf594 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="7abbf594" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"></figure>
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9c8b" class="">While APIs form an important part of modern software development, it’s crucial to ensure that the utility offered by an API does not come at the cost of hindered productivity. Often it takes developers multiple hours to get familiar with an API before they can start building and integrating with it, however, a great developer experience can ensure developers get started with the least of steps and minimal time. In this blog, we will discuss how code samples help contribute towards an outstanding developer experience. We will discuss in detail what makes good samples, the different styles of samples, and how samples gel in with documentation and other elements to form a formidable developer experience.</p>
<h2 id="74b0" class="">Part I: Code Samples — Why Should We Care?</h2>
<p id="6565" class="">Learning new technologies is a complex task, even for the savviest of developers. Often it requires them to go through in-depth documentation, guides, and tutorials, something which they are very keen to skip on. What code samples do instead, is provide them with a task-based learning activity, which requires concrete action.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Developers love learning by experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="60f5" class="">Developers are hands-on learners and code is another language they speak. When they see code, they want to try it, break it apart, put it into action. It’s their favorite call-to-action, often when figuring out if an API is the right fit for them, developers would have already tested out the code samples on developer portals to make their choice.</p>
<p id="d54b" class="">This was proved by a&nbsp;<a href="https://eventil.com/talks/PPSznP-jarod-reyes-how-twilio-writes-documentation">user study</a>&nbsp;conducted by Twilio, where they found that pages with lesser words before code, did better than pages with more sentences before code.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_dlX9uwiw3sdqOg9VFMaDKg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="a6b5">Hence it comes as no surprise why code samples make an important part of the developer experience checklist list for several APIs programs, including the likes of Amazon, Facebook, Twilio, and Stripe. All of them have code samples included one way or the other and have found massive success. And for a very good reason.</p>
<h3 id="c41c">API Calls are Complex Structures</h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_th9O3N-5hKaf_z2EAFepQQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0a22">Before we further talk about code samples, it’s important to understand the need for them in the first place. Why can’t developers do without them?</p>
<p id="3347">And it all starts with putting an API call together. A lot goes into an API call, all these protocols, and conventions, and developers get all caught up in it, instead of focusing on their actual projects. It can take developers multiple hours to figure out what to put into a call, taking a toll on their productivity and creativity and all adding up to integration time.</p>
<p id="e3da" class="">What code samples do is put there calls together for them, in languages of their choice, so they don’t have to do it. Nicely done samples can get developers to&nbsp;<strong>the first Hello World</strong>&nbsp;with an API without writing a single line of code. Samples that go beyond that can be put straight into production. Which now leads to our next question.</p>
<h3 id="0d90">How many code samples can you write?</h3>
<p id="cae9">Not enough! Especially if you are looking for coverage of every endpoint. APIs tend to change and evolve and to update the samples manually with every iteration, even you somehow managed to produce them is not feasible.</p>
<p id="226a" class="">A viable approach here is to auto-generate these samples using an out of the box documentation solution. Different tools have different ideas on how to package deliver these samples. While some do the bare minimum, others go the extra mile to see developers have to put in as little work to get them running. It’s important for API owners to select the right tool to provide the best samples to their consumers, it should be a top priority choosing a documentation solution.</p>
<h2 id="db1d">Part II : Code Samples — Several Different Styles</h2>
<p id="3b6d" class="">To help API owners make well-informed choices, we ran a study to compare this different style of samples, which we analyzed keeping in mind the following qualities:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>Learning Objective</strong>&nbsp;— They demonstrate actual (non-theoretical) use of API</li>
<li><strong>Runnable</strong>&nbsp;— Are runnable out of the box on a console and IDEs</li>
<li><strong>Interactive</strong>&nbsp;— Come with a playground to tweak them around</li>
<li><strong>Language Idiomatic —&nbsp;</strong>Proper language Structure to gel in with production-ready applications</li>
</ul>
<p id="d76f" class="">We categorized our learning into 5 different styles, the summary of which is categorized in the table below:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ciLtfA5TKB_gpe_Io6eBGg@2x.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 id="178f"><strong>Style 1: Static, Non- Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_utlmN5MUbvMqVh3hRBnOTw.png" alt="The Anatomy of API Code Samples" width="700" height="294"></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Postman</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p>The first style is made of static samples, which are not runnable out of the box and required some tweaking done on them. The samples while easily navigable alongside the reference docs, come with no code playground and cannot be tried or tested on the portal.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_wNmdSk-xDCaLpftrbDJG8A.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="13bd" class="">We call the samples,&nbsp;<strong>HTTP snippets</strong>, because they essentially look like an HTTP call, without any proper language structure around them. Samples for some languages were copy-paste ready, while others took a bit of tweaking to run. In the case of Java, we had to configure maven dependencies for the build, and the generator could not pick some values such as the example body and the auth header, which have to be manually added.</p>
<p id="580c" class="">These samples were built upon the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mashape.com/">Mashape</a>&nbsp;<code>httpsnippet</code> library, which has been made open source by Kong to be included within your documentation products. This specific sample was generated on the Postman platform. While there was no on-portal console, on the Postman app you can run a call using Postman collections.</p>
<h3 id="fc1d"><strong>Style 2: Dynamic, Non- Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_6UNsCWYCQM1Anwrbz6lLMQ.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Stoplight.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">The second style of samples made of dynamic HTTP snippets. While the sample came along with a console, they were incomplete and had to be tweaked to be made runnable on the console and IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-385 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_WMUhQmNcXNDGLrkPLEfkYg.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="ec4f">After a few simple fixes, including the missing headers and entering a body, we got the samples running.</p>
<p id="1b16">The console, while getting the job done, made it a difficult task to add in these fields, offering no help on what goes inside the call. For somebody completely unaware of the API and starting new, making use of the console could prove to be a challenge.</p>
<p id="6bfc" class="">These samples, too, were built on the Mashape’s HTTP Snippet library and resembled barebone curl command lacking language structure.</p>
<p id="85db" class="">Samples in this style are available in Shell, Javascript, Node, C, Java, PHP, Objective-C, Swift, Python, Ruby, C#, GO and OCaml, covering pretty much all major platforms. We found this style on&nbsp;Stoplight.io.</p>
<h3 id="5646"><strong>Style 3: Dynamic, Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_4e7PmSXiQ1aKqaXKMbLluw.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Readme.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="319f">The third style of samples made of dynamic snippets that were runnable out of the box. We had to add nothing to the samples to make them work, they came with all the required constructs.</p>
<p id="bed3">The samples come with an intuitive playground which lets you know what kind of field goes where with what data types. This makes it very easy to construct a sample.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_FcRjxPahKOa71Z_fbu5vSw.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9218">Although the samples did a good job explaining what goes in and out of an API call, they were still not idiomatic and required work to be done on them. For instance, there is no body-serialization going on, all these different fields that have to go as arguments, go as one single string and there is no mechanism to put those values together in the form of one single string. These samples were found on Readme.io.</p>
<p id="7964" class="">What we also found missing in all three of these styles was lack of getting started guides, for instance, the HTTP client requires to be included as a dependency and then included as imports within the sample, something which has been left to the discretion of the user to figure out. For novice developers, setting up development environments may also prove to be a challenge, something which the samples or the documentation does not help with at all.</p>
<h3 id="384d"><strong>Style 4: Dynamic, Runnable HTTP snippets, with Proper Guides</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Nys41hEwySBdPhLYQxYJGw-1.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p>The fourth style of samples, while also dynamic and runnable, came with an extra advantage. We found configuration instructions for them, which made it easier to work with them.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_0cK-QcLXleJ_VoBfOeTkXg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">The sample can be tried and tested on the in-product interactive console. Although the console was not as intuitive as the one found in Style 3, particularly making it tough to add arguments, you have to make sure to not mess up a single space of bracket when making up the JSON string, or the request won’t go.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_oelI4U_0KTc12oayvGuZHQ.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 id="d3c5">Style 5: Dynamic, Runnable &amp; Language Idiomatic snippets</h3>
<p id="86cf">These samples are different than the ones we saw above, you see no specifics of making an API call here, no URLs passed or methods declared or headers going in. Instead, you see some object-oriented code here, using proper crud mechanisms.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_DspO9rFjpbnhtLZjxYFZ0Q.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample generated on APIMatic.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8cb9" class="">This is because these samples were generated alongside an SDK, an SDK abstracts out all the details about making an API call and generates additional language structure around these samples, so developers have to write as little communication code as possible. This includes body serialization and response deserializations, which makes it very easy to work with data points.</p>
<p id="266d" class="">The samples can be tried and tested out and tweaked using an interactive explorer, which comes with intuitive, form-based ways to input. The console validates every field, so no incorrect data goes in and helps you construct samples without touching code at all. With the console you can construct API calls with your sample arguments and authentication keys, and copy-paste the resulting samples in your production-ready applications.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_wcQclzK732E-djl-Ws-SlQ.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="279e">And all of that comes with proper documentation, the platform gives API providers the facility to document every parameter in each of the endpoints and data models. Providers can also auto-generate &#8220;getting started guides&#8221; for different IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_bvvGJZTDaI0E2-k57HCWHg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="has-text-align-center" style="text-align: left;">Once set, the developers navigate to their desired use case, copy-paste the code, and start working on the business logic — letting the SDK and the sample take care of logistics.</p>
<h2 id="21f7">Part III: Making Code Samples Work in Production</h2>
<p id="77cf" class="">Looking at the different styles of samples, the question that now arises is how practical are these samples to use? Do they completely replace the need to code, or are they just a push towards the right direction? Do they fully demonstrate the use case for the endpoint? Or do they just explain the logistics of making an API call?</p>
<h3 id="d87e">Language Coded HTTP Snippets or More?</h3>
<p id="6704">If you closely look at many of the auto-generated samples, especially the styles 1 to 4, what they essentially do is eliminate the redundant work of configuring environments, and help consumers figure out what kind of syntax to use. However, when making real-world use of API, you need a lot more. Do these samples, which essentially lack language structure and look like language translated HTTP requests, cut it? The answer is<strong>&nbsp;NO&nbsp;</strong>and for the following reasons:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>No Data Types:</strong>&nbsp;The samples takes input and output in the form of a string, leaving it to the consuming developers to write an efficient i/o mechanism to complete these requests. Often the fields inside the body are not documented.</li>
<li><strong>No Data Models:</strong>&nbsp;Modelling the JSON/XML as classes make it easier to deal with the data, both input, and output. These “models” add a whole different layer on top of the API, with your application having to interact with the model, instead of queried response in JSON or XML.</li>
<li><strong>No Validation and Error Handling:</strong>&nbsp;Since there is no proper I/O mechanism, and both inputs are taken and output returns in form of JSON strings, it’s impossible to validate the sent data and handle error cases to determine what went wrong with the request.</li>
</ul>
<p id="d900">To further demonstrate our point, we will write a&nbsp;<strong>Sample App&nbsp;</strong>to make a new&nbsp;<strong>pet&nbsp;</strong>entry to a store. The app will utilize Code Samples generated by&nbsp;<strong>Postman&nbsp;</strong>for the endpoint<strong>&nbsp;Add Pet.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_utlmN5MUbvMqVh3hRBnOTw-1.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e759" class="">Copy-pasting the code straight away did not work. To configure the HTTP client, we had to include the maven dependency to the build. Following which we found the authentication header missing. We passed in the credentials:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><strong><code>.addHeader(&quot;api_key&quot;, &quot;special-key&quot;)</code></strong></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b89b" class="">And then had to build a JSON String to pass in the input, since the argument body is passed as a String. Constructing an argument body of the two required fields, this is how the sample looked like:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><code>package TestApp.Testapp123;
import java.io.*;
import okhttp3.*;

 class main {
  public static void main(String []args) throws IOException{
     
	 OkHttpClient client = new OkHttpClient().newBuilder()
	 .build();
	  MediaType mediaType = MediaType.parse(&quot;application/json&quot;);
	  RequestBody body = RequestBody.create(mediaType, &quot;{\&quot;name\&quot;:\&quot;doggie\&quot;,\&quot;photoUrls\&quot;:[\&quot;photoUrls1\&quot;]}&quot;);
	  Request request = new Request.Builder()
	 .url(&quot;https://petstore.swagger.io/v2/pet&quot;)
	 .method(&quot;POST&quot;, body)
	 .addHeader(&quot;Accept&quot;, &quot;application/json, application/xml&quot;)
	 .addHeader(&quot;Content-Type&quot;, &quot;application/json&quot;)
	 .addHeader(&quot;api_key&quot;, &quot;special-key&quot;)
	 .build();	  
	  Response response = client.newCall(request).execute();
	  System.out.println(response.body().string()); 	
	    }
	  }</code></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">We ran the code after this tweaking, and it worked like a charm. So how do this sample further translates to real-world usage? If we were to take inputs for the Pet entry from a user, how do we send that as arguments? And before that how do we ensure the data taken from the user is the of the correct type? To tackle that we wrote a model class for the Pet Object, with all the underlying attributes including getters and setters.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><code>package TestApp.SimpleConsoleAppFix;

import java.util.List;

import io.swagger.petstore.models.Category;
import io.swagger.petstore.models.StatusEnum;
import io.swagger.petstore.models.Tag;

public class PetModel {
	
	    public Long getId() {
		return id;
	}
	public void setId(Long id) {
		this.id = id;
	}
	public Category getCategory() {
		return category;
	}
	public void setCategory(Category category) {
		this.category = category;
	}
	public String getName() {
		return name;
	}
	public void setName(String name) {
		this.name = name;
	}
	public List&lt;String&gt; getPhotoUrls() {
		return photoUrls;
	}
	public void setPhotoUrls(List&lt;String&gt; photoUrls) {
		this.photoUrls = photoUrls;
	}
	public List&lt;Tag&gt; getTags() {
		return tags;
	}
	public void setTags(List&lt;Tag&gt; tags) {
		this.tags = tags;
	}
	public StatusEnum getStatus() {
		return status;
	}
	public void setStatus(StatusEnum status) {
		this.status = status;
	}
	    Long id;
	    Category category;
	    String name;
	    List&lt;String&gt; photoUrls;
	    List&lt;Tag&gt; tags;
	    StatusEnum status;

}</code></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e551" class="">Following which we wrote the code to take in input values for these attributes. Now that we ensured we took in these values, with their correct data types, how do we pass these in the request, since the request passes the arguments in the form of a string. Manually doing this was, of course, unfeasible and out of the question, so we had to write in an object to string mapper to do the job for us. This took in these various attribute fields and put them together in the form of a JSON string.</p>
<p id="b586" class="">It was at this point that we were able to achieve a business use case out of the sample. We could pass in the input parameters, with their correct types, concatenated as a JSON string and passed along with the argument. The model allowed us to keep local records of the sent values as well.https://blog.devapi.dream.press/media/a6a1ace16d322eaaf541f83acf4905f9</p>
<p id="4294" class="">Working with multiple endpoints and multiple models would have taken us even more time, depending on the use case and business logic. For instance, for the GET endpoints, we would have to write a string to object mapper to parse values from the response string back to our model. While the sample does a great job pushing developers in the right direction, it is clear that it is not a plug and play situation. Developers have to put in a lot of code to get the calls running, and have to figure out on their own what goes before or comes after the API call.</p>
<p><em>Now imagine if there were samples that could take care of all these logistics, you had to write no communication code at all, and could just plug and play a sample into action. The good news is, you no longer have to imagine. The language idiomatic samples generated alongside an SDK already do that for you.</em></p>
<h2 id="21e8">Language Idiomatic Code Samples — The Way To Go</h2>
<p id="b15b">SDKs have often been labeled as the cornerstone of the API developer experience. What SDKs essentially do is that they abstract out all underlying details of making an API call, making your API look like a library. They provide developers a complete framework to model their applications, including all the necessary dependencies, referenced libraries, system libraries, i/o mechanisms, and class models.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ncYb-AnKZ5JZxOytMwp1PA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="4ce3" class="">Furthermore SDKs automatically format API responses to match the data types used in the programming language. They add an interface on top of the API, so your app interacts with the modeled data from SDK, instead of raw API arguments and responses. By providing SDKs, you can help developers focus on the business logic while taking care of API communication code.</p>
<p id="933e">Code samples generated with SDKs have a lot more work done on them. Since the SDK abstracts out request construction, none of the construction bit makes part of the sample, making the sample look very lean. Such samples can easily fit in with your applications in a very scalable manner, you only have to add minimal communication code, since there exist mechanisms to access, manipulate and work around with all the data fields, that go in and come out of an API call.</p>
<h2 class="has-text-align-center">. . .</h2>
<p id="308d" class="">Concluding this all, we strongly recommend that developers make use of code samples to consume APIs. No matter what style, design, or approach. Code samples will help you get started easily and save you tons of time. While for most people, the simple HTTP snippets may do the job, it is samples with more language structure that help with real-world use and can fit in straight with your applications.</p>
<p id="8467" class="">Again we emphasize the fact that the developer experience is a key driver for an API adoption. APIs are meant to execute integrations, and the easier to integrate, the better the API. Luckily for you, we at APIMatic hold all sorts of expertise to help improve the experience you deliver to developers. Reach out to us today at&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/contact">https://apimatic.io/contact</a>&nbsp;and let’s discuss what can be done to enhance your offerings today.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/">The Anatomy of API Code Samples</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>We&#8217;ve Rewritten Our Developer Experience Portal and You’re Gonna Love It</title>
		<link>/blog/2018/08/weve-rewritten-our-developer-experience-portal-and-youre-gonna-love-it/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mehdi Raza Jaffery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 12:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience Portal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=1109</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Greetings! Our Developer Experience Portal is already into its next version! We did not pack our bags after launching the first version last month and are proud to present Developer Experience Portal Version 1.1. This time even more optimized, more beautiful, and more developer-friendly. The new version is packed with a number of improvements and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/08/weve-rewritten-our-developer-experience-portal-and-youre-gonna-love-it/">We&#8217;ve Rewritten Our Developer Experience Portal and You’re Gonna Love It</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1109" class="elementor elementor-1109">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-394a2653 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="394a2653" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-352d1735" data-id="352d1735" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-6cbdcbb5 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="6cbdcbb5" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1nEt7Q1uNLSW3nMaX8t9LIQ.png" data-image-id="1*nEt7Q1uNLSW3nMaX8t9LIQ.png" data-width="1200" data-height="700" data-is-featured="true"></p>
</figure>
<p class="graf graf--p">Greetings! Our Developer Experience Portal is already into its next version! We did not pack our bags after <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://www.producthunt.com/posts/developer-experience-portal">launching the first version</a> last month and are proud to present Developer Experience Portal Version 1.1. This time even more optimized, more beautiful, and more developer-friendly. The new version is packed with a number of improvements and some new features.</p>

<blockquote class="graf graf--blockquote">Read what makes APIMatic&#8217;s <a class="markup--anchor markup--blockquote-anchor" href="https://apimatic.io/blog/2018/01//developer-experience-beyond-api-docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://blog.devapi.dream.press/introducing-portals-that-speak-your-devs-language-bac82a8c573f">Developer Experience portal different</a> from other available solutions.</blockquote>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? Built from Ground Up to be&nbsp;Awesome</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">The new portal is written from scratch, based on our new internal <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Documentation Format </strong>that powers much of the interactive parts of docs such as the console and reactive code snippets.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">This will enable us to implement more <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">complex features </strong>in the future without being limited by markup languages such as Markdown.</p>

<h2 class="graf graf--h3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/270d.png" alt="✍" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> <strong class="markup--strong markup--h3-strong">Overhaul of Typography</strong></h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">The design of typography (textual elements such as headings, paragraphs, lists, etc) has been overhauled. The new portal brings <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">massive improvements to the look of the content</strong>.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1Fy_P4QCUmMfw90eXCYndQQ.png" data-image-id="1*Fy_P4QCUmMfw90eXCYndQQ.png" data-width="1106" data-height="729"></p>
</figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">?&#x200d;? Redesigned API Reference</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">Endpoint reference has been redesigned and now looks much <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">cleaner</strong>.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1USLklSloeoR3JIleDnQtow.png" data-image-id="1*USLklSloeoR3JIleDnQtow.png" data-width="1464" data-height="786"></p>
</figure>
<p class="graf graf--p">Also, types are now <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">linked </strong>to their definitions for easier navigation.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">

<figure style="width: 1145px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="graf-image" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1akJ1bDIT9LGupWxCxkEfsQ.png" alt="Now linking properly to models and enumerations in parameters table." width="1145" height="581" data-image-id="1*akJ1bDIT9LGupWxCxkEfsQ.png" data-width="1145" data-height="581"><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Now linking properly to models and enumerations in the parameters table.</figcaption></figure>

<figcaption class="imageCaption"></figcaption></figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? <strong class="markup--strong markup--h3-strong">Switching between Languages</strong></h2>
<p class="graf graf--p"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Switching </strong>between languages maintains the endpoint or model or whatever section is open. Config in the console is also persisted between languages.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1POtnjKzJYhCAvQrF6W3dyg.gif" data-image-id="1*POtnjKzJYhCAvQrF6W3dyg.gif" data-width="1138" data-height="634"></p>
</figure>
<p class="graf graf--p">We’ve added <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">icons </strong>in the language drop-down.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1T42G2_USrBQ9R0X4uc0gnA.png" data-image-id="1*T42G2_USrBQ9R0X4uc0gnA.png" data-width="189" data-height="403"></p>
</figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? <strong class="markup--strong markup--h3-strong">Improved Embedded&nbsp;Mode</strong></h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">The menu looks better in the <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">embedded </strong>(two-column) mode. Large menus will scroll now.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1yDV9JwbhyDktH3lab9d2dA.png" data-image-id="1*yDV9JwbhyDktH3lab9d2dA.png" data-width="1079" data-height="703"></p>
</figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? Quick&nbsp;Jump</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">We’ve added a <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">fuzzy search </strong>that helps quickly jumping to endpoints and models. It can also be triggered from the <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">keyboard </strong>using <code class="markup--code markup--p-code">Ctrl+K</code>&nbsp;.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure graf--layoutOutsetCenter">

<figure style="width: 1013px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="graf-image" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1vGz-syA7CtCfHug8mJ8AOA.gif" alt="Using the keyboard to quickly navigate documentation." width="1013" height="580" data-image-id="1*vGz-syA7CtCfHug8mJ8AOA.gif" data-width="1013" data-height="580"><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Using the keyboard to quickly navigate documentation.</figcaption></figure>

<figcaption class="imageCaption"></figcaption></figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? Gentler Error&nbsp;Messages</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">We’ve improved the <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">messaging </strong>in case an API call fails in the API console.</p>

<figure class="graf graf--figure">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="graf-image aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1FXNrUiM2lguTvIT10JtZUQ.png" data-image-id="1*FXNrUiM2lguTvIT10JtZUQ.png" data-width="578" data-height="596"></p>
</figure>
<h2 class="graf graf--h3">? Faster,&nbsp;Lighter</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">The new portal is written to be fast and light. Despite adding new features, we’ve actually shed weight <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">resulting in about a 33% reduction in size</strong>.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">The new portal optimizes for a perception of fast loading speed by delaying loading of non-critical components until they are needed. This results in <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">a 71% reduction in size on the first load</strong>. Technical implementation details can be read <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://medium.com/@thehappybug/using-react-context-in-a-typescript-app-c4ef7504c858" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://medium.com/@thehappybug/using-react-context-in-a-typescript-app-c4ef7504c858">here</a>.</p>

<h2 class="graf graf--h3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/2b50.png" alt="⭐" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> How do I get&nbsp;this?</h2>
<ul class="postList">
 	<li class="graf graf--li">Read how to <a class="markup--anchor markup--li-anchor" href="https://docs.apimatic.io/changelog/developer-experience-portal-major-release/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://docs.devapi.dream.press/changelog/developer-experience-portal-major-release/">upgrade your existing portal</a> to the newest version.</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--li">Or create one from scratch using our <a class="markup--anchor markup--li-anchor" href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://devapi.dream.press/developer-experience-portal">portal generator</a>.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/08/weve-rewritten-our-developer-experience-portal-and-youre-gonna-love-it/">We&#8217;ve Rewritten Our Developer Experience Portal and You’re Gonna Love It</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
