
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Developer Experience Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/developer-experience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 01:59:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Developer Experience Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</title>
		<link>/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam DuVander]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 10:32:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Calls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Direct API Calls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What&#8217;s it like to call your API? Developers want to use your API to accomplish something, and you want to make it as easy as possible for them to incorporate your service. To allow developers to call your API directly from any technology, your docs provide DIY instructions. To go a step further and give [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/">DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1519" class="elementor elementor-1519">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-7825289e elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="7825289e" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-5ad04015" data-id="5ad04015" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-687f92af elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="687f92af" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
			<style>/*! elementor - v3.6.4 - 13-04-2022 */
.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-stacked .elementor-drop-cap{background-color:#818a91;color:#fff}.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-framed .elementor-drop-cap{color:#818a91;border:3px solid;background-color:transparent}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap{margin-top:8px}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap-letter{width:1em;height:1em}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap{float:left;text-align:center;line-height:1;font-size:50px}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap-letter{display:inline-block}</style>				<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1552 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/dx-of-sdks-vs-api-calls-1024x459.png" alt="" width="771" height="346"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">What&#8217;s it like to call your API? Developers want to use your API to accomplish something, and you want to make it as easy as possible for them to incorporate your service. To allow developers to call your API directly from any technology, your docs provide DIY instructions. To go a step further and give developers additional conveniences and tooling, you can provide Software Development Kits (SDKs). SDKs include code to call your API so that developers don&#8217;t have to write it themselves from scratch.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While calling an API directly vs. using an SDK does not change the ultimate functionality of the API, it can dramatically affect the developer experience. In most cases, one method will be preferred over the other, varying according to each developer’s needs, preferences, and skills. An SDK offers simplicity and speedier development but applies only to a particular development framework. SDKs require resources to develop and maintain. Direct calls offer platform flexibility and are available to all developers, but are harder to use without expertise.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In this article, we&#8217;ll be looking at why your developer experience may focus on direct API calls, SDKs, or both.</span></p>

<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Direct API Calls: The Basics</span></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">For communicating with a service, sending API calls directly to URL endpoints is the simplest way. Of course, when we say </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">simplest</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, we mean in terms of program complexity, not ease of use.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When using an API without an SDK, you make calls to its URL endpoints directly using standard internet protocol commands for transferring packets of information over the network. There&#8217;s no abstraction between you and the service, so every parameter must be written into the call. It must also conform to a standard format.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">An example of how to construct a direct API call using Python is shown in the code snippet below. Notice the URL for the API endpoint is specified explicitly, alongside required header parameters that describe the request. This information is bundled and transmitted using the <code>requests</code> library, which then receives any response data returned by the API and stores it in the <code>resp</code> variable. Note that the cost of deserialization is added here for the API call.</span></p>

<pre class=""><code class="language-python">import requests
from requests.structures import CaseInsensitiveDict

url = &quot;https://connect.squareup.com/v2/payments&quot;

headers = CaseInsensitiveDict()
headers[&quot;Square-Version&quot;] = &quot;2021-06-16&quot;
headers[&quot;Authorization&quot;] = &quot;Bearer ACCESS TOKEN&quot;
headers[&quot;Content-Type&quot;] = &quot;application/json&quot;

resp = requests.get(url, headers=headers)
print(resp.status_code)

decoded = jsonpickle.decode(resp.text)
</code></pre>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another example of a non-trivial API call can be seen here, pulled from the User Authentication documentation for the</span> <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/developers/documentation"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dropbox API</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1520" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1520" style="width: 790px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1520 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/dropbox-1024x677.png" alt="dropbox user authentication" width="790" height="523"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1520" class="wp-caption-text">Dropbox User Authentication Docs</figcaption></figure>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">For many developers, the need to specify every parameter is exactly what they want: the full power of the service at their fingertips.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Low-level control can be unnecessary and overwhelming, though, especially for new developers. With just the basic building blocks, it can become a challenge for developers to perform more complicated tasks.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not only can direct API calls be complicated to do correctly, but they can also be frustrating to try to troubleshoot. API response codes aren&#8217;t particularly specific when providing error messages; Many developers may give up after countless generic 404 errors.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ultimately, many developers will wish they could have something a little more prepared for them. For those developers, you can please them by offering SDKs in their language.</span></p>

<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs: What Are They?</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs are a compilation of environment-specific developer tools designed to access your API. SDKs make it more straightforward for developers to use your API using a programming language framework they prefer. For the developer who wants a little more guidance, SDKs will be the most appealing way for them to access your service.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">SDKs abstract away the minutiae of the API that often bog down implementation for developers. They can be thought of as an API wrapper that makes accessing that API more friendly to a particular type of developer. A developer has to download and install an SDK that matches the language of their development environment, where it will then provide a host of streamlined functionalities for interacting with your API. If the developer is using Python, for instance, they’ll most likely download an SDK through pip, such as this example from </span><a href="https://www.algolia.com/doc/guides/getting-started/quick-start/tutorials/quick-start-with-the-api-client/python/?client=python"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Algolia’s documentation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1521" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1521" style="width: 721px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1521 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/algolia-1024x350.png" alt="Algolia Documentation" width="721" height="247"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1521" class="wp-caption-text">Algolia SDK download through pip</figcaption></figure>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The example call to Dropbox&#8217;s API, shown earlier, constructed with their Python SDK is shown below. In contrast to a direct API call, it does not require the developer to hard code a URL and headers. Instead, the API token is passed to a provided client object that handles those details.</span></p>

<pre class=""><code class="language-python">import dropbox
token = &#039;My-API-Token&#039;
dbx = dropbox.Dropbox(token)

My_Field = dropbox.file_properties.PropertyField(&#039;Security Policy&#039;,&#039;Confidential&#039;)
My_Template_ID = &#039;ptid:1...&#039;
My_Property_Group = dropbox.file_properties.PropertyGroup(template_id=My_Template_ID, fields=[My_Field])

dbx.file_properties_properties_add(&quot;/my_awesome/word.docx&quot;, My_Property_Group)
</code></pre>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">While APIs aren&#8217;t language-specific, SDKs are. A developer will download the SDK for the specific language they want to work with. API providers that intend to offer SDKs have to research what languages most appeal to their core user base. Developers who have the use of an SDK will be incredibly satisfied by the bevy of tools made available for them, including, but not limited to:</span>
<ul class="">
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Autocomplete SDK commands inline</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Code samples for commands</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Example applications</span></li>
</ul>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">A beneficial everyday use case where SDKs are much easier to use than direct API calls is when developers need to perform complicated authentication procedures. Doing this correctly and securely with only direct API calls can be tricky, but most SDKs take these steps and make them easily implementable with just a few commands. The low-level API call parameters and structure are abstracted away from the developer and handled by the SDK.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">In many ways, SDKs are the epitome of one of the main purposes of APIs: to give the developer the ability to build off existing technology as easily and quickly as possible.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For many developers, SDKs are the preferred method of interacting with APIs. For others, there are cases for making direct API calls without an SDK. Now that we&#8217;ve looked at both options let&#8217;s see why developers would lean towards one or the other.</span></p>

<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Choosing Between SDKs and Direct API Calls</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In an ideal world, there will be an SDK available to meet the developer’s exact needs. SDKs cost resources to produce and maintain, however. And even when SDKs are available, there are quite a few situations where the available SDKs might not work for what a developer wants to do. Just to list a few:</span></p>

<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">An SDK may not be available in their desired language</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The SDK may not be updated to incorporate new API features yet</span></li>
</ul>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In both of these situations, directly using the API might be the only option. After all, it takes time and effort for an API provider to build SDKs. If there&#8217;s only one Julia developer using your API who wants a Julia SDK, it might not justify the use of resources.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even for the SDKs of languages you deem popular enough to support, it takes time and effort to update those SDKs. Functionality added to an API yesterday may not be supported in the SDK by today.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For the vast majority of use cases, developers will appreciate having SDKs available and will eagerly use them. This is especially true for those who are making use of multiple APIs in their applications. For that reason, SDKs are worth the time and effort to develop for your primary user groups. The effort it takes to provide up-to-date SDKs will save them effort as they can seamlessly incorporate API calls into their app code.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">And for those edge case developers, those who code in esoteric languages, those who need maximum security control over what the API is doing, and those who want to be on the cutting edge no matter what, direct API calls are most useful.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">A great example of a company showing both direct API and SDK calls in their documentation is </span><a href="https://stripe.com/docs/api/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stripe</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>


<figure id="attachment_1522" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1522" style="width: 576px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-1522 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/stripe.gif" alt="Stripe API documentation showing both SDKs and API calls" width="576" height="296"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1522" class="wp-caption-text">Stripe API documentation showing both SDKs and API calls</figcaption></figure>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">Both direct API calls and SDKs are tools that you should make available in your developers&#8217; toolboxes. And the more tools at their disposal, the more effective your developers will be.</span>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">At the end of the day, the goal of your developer experience should be improving the accessibility of your product to developers of all backgrounds. Providing SDKs is the best way to make your API a little more manageable for them to implement.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">
</span>Have a look at how <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal">APIMatic enhances the developer experience</a> of your API with robust SDKs auto-generated in all popular languages from a single API definition file.</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/dx-of-sdks-vs-direct-api-calls/">DX of SDKs vs Direct API Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>APIMatic v3: Your Biggest DX Game Changer [Webinar Follow-up]</title>
		<link>/blog/2021/10/apimatic-v3-your-biggest-dx-game-changer-webinar-follow-up/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Qurat-ul-Ain Ghazali]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 11:16:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Webinar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMatic Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1501</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In APIMatic v3 (codenamed Titan), our largest release to date, we have made some major improvements to the Code Generator and the API Portal to make your API’s developer experience seamless and further feature-rich. Developer experience is critical for smooth and rapid onboarding of your API which, in turn, leads to quicker API adoption and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/apimatic-v3-your-biggest-dx-game-changer-webinar-follow-up/">APIMatic v3: Your Biggest DX Game Changer [Webinar Follow-up]</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1501" class="elementor elementor-1501">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-68f6a399 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="68f6a399" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-7eac4c7a" data-id="7eac4c7a" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-4a4cef6 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="4a4cef6" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">In APIMatic v3 (codenamed Titan), our largest release to date, we have made some major improvements to the Code Generator and the <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal">API Portal</a> to make your API’s developer experience seamless and further feature-rich. Developer experience is critical for smooth and rapid onboarding of your API which, in turn, leads to quicker API adoption and higher ROI.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The webinar &#8220;APIMatic v3: Your Biggest DX Game Changer&#8221; gave an overview of the new features and major improvements made in this release to help streamline your API&#8217;s developer experience. Mehdi, our Chief Product Architect, discussed updates to the Code Generator such as introducing immutable clients as SDKs for multi-threading, timeouts, and retries on API call errors, the support for latest dependencies, and language versions, and more. He also gave a walkthrough of the revamped API Portal that is more developer-friendly and intuitive and offers the updated WYSIWYG Markdown docs editor.</span></p>

<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">

<hr>

</div>
</div>
<h3 class="">Notes:</h3>
<ul class="">
 	<li><strong>Introduction to APIMatic</strong>: D<span style="font-weight: 300;">eveloper experience platform that enables faster integrations of your API </span> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=87">1.27</a>]</li>
</ul>
<ol class="">
 	<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ol>
 	<li>SDK Generation: <span style="font-weight: 300;">&nbsp;PHP, Ruby, Python, C#, Java and TS/JS</span> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=103">1.43</a>]</li>
 	<li><span style="font-weight: 300;">HTTP and Language-Specific Documentation</span>&nbsp;[<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=130">2.10</a>]</li>
 	<li>API Portal and Code Playground [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=143">2.23</a>]</li>
 	<li>Dynamic Code Samples [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=168">2.48</a>]</li>
 	<li>Assisted Authentication [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=190">3.10</a>]</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<ul class="">
 	<li><strong>APIMatic v3</strong> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=218">3.38</a>]</li>
 	<li><strong>Code Generator</strong>: U<span style="font-weight: 400;">pdated target language and runtime versions in all generated SDKs, the addition of TS</span>&nbsp;[<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=316">5.16</a>]</li>
 	<li><strong>Immutable Clients</strong>: For <span style="font-weight: 400;">all languages [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=481">8.01</a>]</span></li>
 	<li><strong>API </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Timeouts and Retries, Support for XML, and other enhancements</strong> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=566">9.26</a>]</span></li>
 	<li><strong>API Portal</strong>: Improved aesthetics and UX, new API Code Playground, pop-out code samples, and customizable table-of-contents ​[<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=771">12.51</a>]</li>
 	<li><strong>Migrate to APIMatic v3</strong> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=1134">18.54</a>]</li>
 	<li><strong>Q&amp;A</strong> [<a href="https://youtu.be/dj9LIdjFBIU?t=1261">21.01</a>]</li>
</ul>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">

<hr>

</div>
</div>
<h3 class="">Watch the Webinar</h3>
<iframe title="Webinar - APIMatic v3: Your Biggest DX Game Changer" width="653" height="367" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dj9LIdjFBIU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">

<hr>

</div>
</div>
<h3 class="">Helpful APIMatic v3 Resources:&nbsp;</h3>
<ul class="">
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/blog/2021/06/whats-new-in-apimatic-v3/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">What’s New in APIMatic v3?</span></a></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/account-management/migrate-to-v3/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic v3 Migration Guide&nbsp;</span></a></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/changelog/apimatic-code-generator-v3-titan/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Code Generator Changelog</span></a></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://docs.apimatic.io/changelog/releasing-apimatic-v3-revamped-api-portal/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">API Portal Changelog</span></a></li>
</ul>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<div>

<hr>

</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">For any questions, comments, or feedback, please visit <a href="http://apimatic.io/">our website</a> or send an email to <a href="mailto:marketing@apimatic.io">marketing@apimatic.io</a>.</span></p>

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/10/apimatic-v3-your-biggest-dx-game-changer-webinar-follow-up/">APIMatic v3: Your Biggest DX Game Changer [Webinar Follow-up]</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cryptocurrency APIs: State of Developer Experience 2021</title>
		<link>/blog/2021/04/cryptocurrency-apis-state-of-developer-experience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sohaib Tariq]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 09:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blockchain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[crypto apis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[crypto rest api]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[crypto websocket api]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cryptocurrency]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic-blog.000webhostapp.com/?p=121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Bitcoin was first introduced to the world in 2009 at a price of approximately $0 per Bitcoin. In early April 2021, it reached an all time high of $64,800. The success of bitcoin has given rise to an entire Crypto ecosystem that comprises thousands of Cryptocurrencies and other digital-native assets. Much has been written about [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/04/cryptocurrency-apis-state-of-developer-experience/">Cryptocurrency APIs: State of Developer Experience 2021</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="121" class="elementor elementor-121">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-4c9f5e49 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="4c9f5e49" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-3cb8f70f" data-id="3cb8f70f" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-60826a88 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="60826a88" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"></figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="mod-reset"><br><img class="wp-image-122 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_qJsf3NngGgkGNokNzjGHrA-e1622209755991.png" alt="Cryptocurrency APIs - State of Developer Experience" width="640" height="320"></p>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">Bitcoin was first introduced to the world in 2009 at a price of approximately $0 per Bitcoin. In early April 2021, it reached an all time high of $64,800.</p>
<p class="">The success of bitcoin has given rise to an entire Crypto ecosystem that comprises thousands of Cryptocurrencies and other digital-native assets.</p>
<p class=""><strong>Much has been written about APIs in the Fintech ecosystem, but Cryptocurrencies have largely been absent from the conversation. This is in part because Crypto is not formally classified as Fintech, despite it being “Financial Technology”.</strong></p>
<p class="">Fintech or not, Crypto deserves a mention in any discussion around technology in the financial sector owing to the amount of interest it is garnering from institutional investors, publicly listed companies and even government institutions.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1JigSXmFSw2emxuJ73oep6A.png" alt="Bitcoin holdings of prominent public companies"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 class="">Cryptocurrency Adoption</h2>
<p class="">While institutional investors are adopting Cryptocurrencies as investment instruments, payment providers are laying the groundwork to begin using Cryptocurrencies for financial transactions.</p>
<p class=""><strong>Anchorage Digital Bank</strong> has become the first federally chartered digital asset bank in history. This is a major milestone for the Crypto industry, as it places Anchorage on the same regulatory footing as other national banks in the USA.</p>
<p class="">Mobile payment services are rushing to tap the growing Crypto market as well. <strong>CashApp</strong>, <strong>Square’s</strong> peer-to-peer payments app has been allowing its users to buy and sell Bitcoin for the last couple of years. Now <strong>Paypal</strong> has also jumped into the fray. Not only can Paypal users buy Bitcoin and other popular Cryptocurrencies within the app, but with the newly launched “Checkout with Crypto” feature, customers can also use their Cryptocurrency holdings as a funding source to pay at PayPal’s 29 million merchants around the globe.</p>
<p class="">Electronic Payments giants <strong>Visa</strong> and <strong>MasterCard </strong>also seem eager to join the party.</p>
<p class=""><strong>Visa</strong> has already partnered up with major Cryptocurrency exchanges like Binance, Crypto.com and Coinbase to launch debit cards to allow users to pay with Cryptocurrency at over 70 million merchants globally.</p>
<p class="">Visa is also launching Crypto APIs to allow users to participate in the digital economy. Although these APIs are still in the initial pilot phase, interested users can sign up to join the <a href="https://globalclient.visa.com/crypto" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">waitlist</a> to access the APIs.</p>
<p class=""><strong>Mastercard</strong> has revealed that it is planning to start offering support for some Cryptocurrencies later this year. However, details regarding the exact Cryptocurrencies that will be supported have not yet been disclosed.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 class="">Crypto Exchanges</h2>
<p class="">As traditional financial institutions gear up to enter the Crypto space, Cryptocurrency exchanges remain the largest stakeholders in this space. Crypto exchange data collected by <a href="https://www.theblockcrypto.com/linked/96472/monthly-crypto-exchange-volumes-broke-1-trillion-for-the-first-time-in-february" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Block Research</a> shows that monthly traded volumes on exchanges surpassed <strong>$1 trillion </strong>in February, a new record.</p>
<p class=""><strong>Cryptocurrency exchanges remain the first point of contact for most new entrants into the Crypto market, allowing users to buy, sell, hold and stake Cryptocurrencies.</strong></p>
<p class="">Contrary to traditional financial institutions who have had to undergo extensive Digital Transformation initiatives to cater to the digital economy, Crypto exchanges have the advantage of being digital-native. This is why almost all major exchanges already provide public APIs to allow programmatic access to their services.</p>
<h2 class="">Crypto Exchange APIs — Features</h2>
<p class="">Most Crypto exchanges provide 2 types of APIs; <strong>REST APIs</strong> and <strong>Websocket APIs. </strong>REST APIs provide transactional services that make up the core of the exchange’s offerings. Websocket APIs, on the other hand, are generally used to provide real time updates.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1cU2y5394L-8fST4hMUrpRw.png" alt="Essential Features - Crypto Exchange APIs"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">Virtually all of a Cryptocurrency exchange’s service offerings are accessible through its API.&nbsp;Since this holds true for all notable exchanges, therefore, merely <strong>having</strong> an API can not be a differentiator in an industry where every major player has one. What <strong>can </strong>set an API apart is <strong>API</strong> <strong>Developer Experience</strong>.</p>
<h2>Crypto Exchange APIs — Developer Experience (DX)</h2>
<p class="">Developer Experience will play a major role in ascertaining which API gains mass adoption in a fiercely competitive industry that is rapidly going mainstream. The most prominent element in an APIs DX is its <strong>Developer Portal</strong>.</p>
<p class="">How do the Developer Portals of some major Cryptocurrency exchanges measure up against our Developer Experience Checklist? Let’s find out!</p>
<h3>Developer Experience Checklist</h3>
<p>We look for the following elements when evaluating a Developer Portal:</p>
<ol class="">
<li><strong>Landing Page</strong>: What is this API and what can it do?</li>
<li><strong>Getting started guides/tutorials</strong>: Step by step guides for some of the most common use cases.</li>
<li><strong>API Documentation</strong>: Endpoints, Schemas, Authentication methods and any other conceptual information that could be useful while working with this API.</li>
<li><strong>Try it out/ Interactive API explorer</strong>: Make API calls from within the Developer Portal.</li>
<li><strong>SDKs</strong>: Client Libraries to cater to a number of Languages and Platforms.</li>
<li><strong>Code samples</strong>: Code samples for each endpoint, preferably in multiple languages.</li>
<li><strong>FAQs</strong></li>
<li><strong>Change Logs</strong></li>
</ol>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12"><hr></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 class="">Developer Experience Analysis</h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/18z1i6Pk5p8TAoxtxxxWadw.jpg" alt="Developer Experience - Cryptocurrency APIs 2021"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 class="">Bitfinex</h3>
<p class="">Bitfinex seems to be ahead of the pack in terms of Developer Experience. The API documentation seems to be well written and well organized and ticks most of the boxes on our Developer Experience Checklist. Open source SDKs are provided for Go, Node.js, Ruby and Python and are being actively maintained. There are also a number of community built SDKs for other languages and platforms. The documentation is interactive, allowing developers to make API calls from within the API Docs.</p>
<p class="">However, code samples are where we found the Bitfinex portal slightly lacking, with many endpoints restricted to code samples in only javascript; it would be great to see code samples in multiple languages to facilitate developers from diverse backgrounds.</p>
<h3>Coinbase</h3>
<p>The Coinbase Developer Portal seems to tick many of the boxes on our Developer Experience Checklist, however, on closer inspection, we noticed some issues, particularly around SDKs.</p>
<p class="">SDKs for Python, Ruby, PHP and Node.js are listed in the documentation, however, a quick look at their GitHub repositories will tell you that they have all been deprecated. There are a number of community built SDKs featured on the Coinbase Developer Portal as well, however, sadly, most of these seem to have been abandoned by the maintainers.</p>
<p class="">Code samples are provided for Node.js, Ruby and Python which is definitely where Coinbase has an edge over Bitfinex, however the Coinbase portal concedes some ground by not having interactive documentation.</p>
<p>Coinbase is also going the extra mile by maintaining a presence on Stackoverflow as well as a dedicated Twitter account for developers. This certainly earns them brownie points.</p>
<p>We did note, however, that the Coinbase Pro API documentation seems to have a couple of important DX elements missing, including code samples and SDKs, which is specially surprising since this platform caters to high value clients.</p>
<h3>Bittrex</h3>
<p>Bittrex has a well designed portal that seems to be doing the basics right. The documentation is well structured and well written. Moreover, developers can communicate with the Bittrex team by creating issues on GitHub.</p>
<p class="">Adding interactive documentation, code samples and SDKs would definitely elevate the Developer Experience for the Bittrex API to another level.</p>
<h3>Kraken</h3>
<p class="">Kraken has two separate portals for their REST and Websockets APIs with completely different design and aesthetics which had us double checking the URL to ensure we were on the correct website. Moving past the visual elements, the Websockets documentation seems to be quite well structured, with the REST API documentation lagging slightly behind.</p>
<p>An official PHP SDK is provided for the REST API but it does not seem to have been updated in a while. There are a number of unofficial SDKs featured on the website, however, they are accompanied by a disclaimer that the company is not liable for any losses incurred due to the usage of these libraries, so we are not sure of the usefulness of these community maintained SDKs.</p>
<h3>Binance</h3>
<p class="">The last exchange on our list also happens to be the largest of the lot, Binance. The <strong>Binance </strong>API docs do the basics quite well and additionally, provide a Postman collection to lower the barrier for entry. There is also a developer forum where developers can discuss issues with the Binance support team.</p>
<p class="">However, as with the other exchanges on our list, Binance also seems to be complacent in terms of SDKs and code samples. These would be great additions to the Binance Developer Portal.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><strong>To sum up, it seems that most Crypto exchange Developer Portals are lagging in terms of SDKs and code samples, which we rank among the most important elements of a great Developer Experience.</strong></p>
<p class="">Most exchanges seem to be relying on community built libraries. While we love open source software at APIMatic, we also acknowledge the fact that community projects tend to be neglected over time. API owners must also either audit these libraries periodically to ensure their stability or provide disclaimers for developers to use these libraries at their own risk, neither of which is ideal.</p>
<p class=""><strong>APIMatic solves this problem with its proprietary code generation engine, which is able to instantly auto-generate SDKs and code samples for any API.</strong></p>
<p class="">To learn more about how we can help automate your APIs developer experience, check out our <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/developer-experience-portal" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Developer Experience Portal offering</a>, complete with API documentation, auto-generated SDKs and code samples.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2021/04/cryptocurrency-apis-state-of-developer-experience/">Cryptocurrency APIs: State of Developer Experience 2021</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Anatomy of API Code Samples</title>
		<link>/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Samples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Code Sample]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hence it comes as no surprise why code samples make an important part of the developer experience checklist list for several APIs programs, including the likes of Amazon, Facebook, Twilio, and Stripe. All of them have code samples included one way or the other and have found massive success. And for a very good reason. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/">The Anatomy of API Code Samples</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="359" class="elementor elementor-359">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-2c773500 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="2c773500" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-41f291e6" data-id="41f291e6" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-7abbf594 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="7abbf594" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"></figure>
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9c8b" class="">While APIs form an important part of modern software development, it’s crucial to ensure that the utility offered by an API does not come at the cost of hindered productivity. Often it takes developers multiple hours to get familiar with an API before they can start building and integrating with it, however, a great developer experience can ensure developers get started with the least of steps and minimal time. In this blog, we will discuss how code samples help contribute towards an outstanding developer experience. We will discuss in detail what makes good samples, the different styles of samples, and how samples gel in with documentation and other elements to form a formidable developer experience.</p>
<h2 id="74b0" class="">Part I: Code Samples — Why Should We Care?</h2>
<p id="6565" class="">Learning new technologies is a complex task, even for the savviest of developers. Often it requires them to go through in-depth documentation, guides, and tutorials, something which they are very keen to skip on. What code samples do instead, is provide them with a task-based learning activity, which requires concrete action.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Developers love learning by experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="60f5" class="">Developers are hands-on learners and code is another language they speak. When they see code, they want to try it, break it apart, put it into action. It’s their favorite call-to-action, often when figuring out if an API is the right fit for them, developers would have already tested out the code samples on developer portals to make their choice.</p>
<p id="d54b" class="">This was proved by a&nbsp;<a href="https://eventil.com/talks/PPSznP-jarod-reyes-how-twilio-writes-documentation">user study</a>&nbsp;conducted by Twilio, where they found that pages with lesser words before code, did better than pages with more sentences before code.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_dlX9uwiw3sdqOg9VFMaDKg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="a6b5">Hence it comes as no surprise why code samples make an important part of the developer experience checklist list for several APIs programs, including the likes of Amazon, Facebook, Twilio, and Stripe. All of them have code samples included one way or the other and have found massive success. And for a very good reason.</p>
<h3 id="c41c">API Calls are Complex Structures</h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_th9O3N-5hKaf_z2EAFepQQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0a22">Before we further talk about code samples, it’s important to understand the need for them in the first place. Why can’t developers do without them?</p>
<p id="3347">And it all starts with putting an API call together. A lot goes into an API call, all these protocols, and conventions, and developers get all caught up in it, instead of focusing on their actual projects. It can take developers multiple hours to figure out what to put into a call, taking a toll on their productivity and creativity and all adding up to integration time.</p>
<p id="e3da" class="">What code samples do is put there calls together for them, in languages of their choice, so they don’t have to do it. Nicely done samples can get developers to&nbsp;<strong>the first Hello World</strong>&nbsp;with an API without writing a single line of code. Samples that go beyond that can be put straight into production. Which now leads to our next question.</p>
<h3 id="0d90">How many code samples can you write?</h3>
<p id="cae9">Not enough! Especially if you are looking for coverage of every endpoint. APIs tend to change and evolve and to update the samples manually with every iteration, even you somehow managed to produce them is not feasible.</p>
<p id="226a" class="">A viable approach here is to auto-generate these samples using an out of the box documentation solution. Different tools have different ideas on how to package deliver these samples. While some do the bare minimum, others go the extra mile to see developers have to put in as little work to get them running. It’s important for API owners to select the right tool to provide the best samples to their consumers, it should be a top priority choosing a documentation solution.</p>
<h2 id="db1d">Part II : Code Samples — Several Different Styles</h2>
<p id="3b6d" class="">To help API owners make well-informed choices, we ran a study to compare this different style of samples, which we analyzed keeping in mind the following qualities:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>Learning Objective</strong>&nbsp;— They demonstrate actual (non-theoretical) use of API</li>
<li><strong>Runnable</strong>&nbsp;— Are runnable out of the box on a console and IDEs</li>
<li><strong>Interactive</strong>&nbsp;— Come with a playground to tweak them around</li>
<li><strong>Language Idiomatic —&nbsp;</strong>Proper language Structure to gel in with production-ready applications</li>
</ul>
<p id="d76f" class="">We categorized our learning into 5 different styles, the summary of which is categorized in the table below:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ciLtfA5TKB_gpe_Io6eBGg@2x.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 id="178f"><strong>Style 1: Static, Non- Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_utlmN5MUbvMqVh3hRBnOTw.png" alt="The Anatomy of API Code Samples" width="700" height="294"></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Postman</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p>The first style is made of static samples, which are not runnable out of the box and required some tweaking done on them. The samples while easily navigable alongside the reference docs, come with no code playground and cannot be tried or tested on the portal.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_wNmdSk-xDCaLpftrbDJG8A.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="13bd" class="">We call the samples,&nbsp;<strong>HTTP snippets</strong>, because they essentially look like an HTTP call, without any proper language structure around them. Samples for some languages were copy-paste ready, while others took a bit of tweaking to run. In the case of Java, we had to configure maven dependencies for the build, and the generator could not pick some values such as the example body and the auth header, which have to be manually added.</p>
<p id="580c" class="">These samples were built upon the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mashape.com/">Mashape</a>&nbsp;<code>httpsnippet</code> library, which has been made open source by Kong to be included within your documentation products. This specific sample was generated on the Postman platform. While there was no on-portal console, on the Postman app you can run a call using Postman collections.</p>
<h3 id="fc1d"><strong>Style 2: Dynamic, Non- Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_6UNsCWYCQM1Anwrbz6lLMQ.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Stoplight.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">The second style of samples made of dynamic HTTP snippets. While the sample came along with a console, they were incomplete and had to be tweaked to be made runnable on the console and IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-385 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_WMUhQmNcXNDGLrkPLEfkYg.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="ec4f">After a few simple fixes, including the missing headers and entering a body, we got the samples running.</p>
<p id="1b16">The console, while getting the job done, made it a difficult task to add in these fields, offering no help on what goes inside the call. For somebody completely unaware of the API and starting new, making use of the console could prove to be a challenge.</p>
<p id="6bfc" class="">These samples, too, were built on the Mashape’s HTTP Snippet library and resembled barebone curl command lacking language structure.</p>
<p id="85db" class="">Samples in this style are available in Shell, Javascript, Node, C, Java, PHP, Objective-C, Swift, Python, Ruby, C#, GO and OCaml, covering pretty much all major platforms. We found this style on&nbsp;Stoplight.io.</p>
<h3 id="5646"><strong>Style 3: Dynamic, Runnable HTTP Snippets</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_4e7PmSXiQ1aKqaXKMbLluw.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample on Readme.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="319f">The third style of samples made of dynamic snippets that were runnable out of the box. We had to add nothing to the samples to make them work, they came with all the required constructs.</p>
<p id="bed3">The samples come with an intuitive playground which lets you know what kind of field goes where with what data types. This makes it very easy to construct a sample.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_FcRjxPahKOa71Z_fbu5vSw.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9218">Although the samples did a good job explaining what goes in and out of an API call, they were still not idiomatic and required work to be done on them. For instance, there is no body-serialization going on, all these different fields that have to go as arguments, go as one single string and there is no mechanism to put those values together in the form of one single string. These samples were found on Readme.io.</p>
<p id="7964" class="">What we also found missing in all three of these styles was lack of getting started guides, for instance, the HTTP client requires to be included as a dependency and then included as imports within the sample, something which has been left to the discretion of the user to figure out. For novice developers, setting up development environments may also prove to be a challenge, something which the samples or the documentation does not help with at all.</p>
<h3 id="384d"><strong>Style 4: Dynamic, Runnable HTTP snippets, with Proper Guides</strong></h3>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Nys41hEwySBdPhLYQxYJGw-1.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p>The fourth style of samples, while also dynamic and runnable, came with an extra advantage. We found configuration instructions for them, which made it easier to work with them.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_0cK-QcLXleJ_VoBfOeTkXg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">The sample can be tried and tested on the in-product interactive console. Although the console was not as intuitive as the one found in Style 3, particularly making it tough to add arguments, you have to make sure to not mess up a single space of bracket when making up the JSON string, or the request won’t go.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_oelI4U_0KTc12oayvGuZHQ.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h3 id="d3c5">Style 5: Dynamic, Runnable &amp; Language Idiomatic snippets</h3>
<p id="86cf">These samples are different than the ones we saw above, you see no specifics of making an API call here, no URLs passed or methods declared or headers going in. Instead, you see some object-oriented code here, using proper crud mechanisms.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_DspO9rFjpbnhtLZjxYFZ0Q.png" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>Code Sample generated on APIMatic.io</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8cb9" class="">This is because these samples were generated alongside an SDK, an SDK abstracts out all the details about making an API call and generates additional language structure around these samples, so developers have to write as little communication code as possible. This includes body serialization and response deserializations, which makes it very easy to work with data points.</p>
<p id="266d" class="">The samples can be tried and tested out and tweaked using an interactive explorer, which comes with intuitive, form-based ways to input. The console validates every field, so no incorrect data goes in and helps you construct samples without touching code at all. With the console you can construct API calls with your sample arguments and authentication keys, and copy-paste the resulting samples in your production-ready applications.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_wcQclzK732E-djl-Ws-SlQ.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="279e">And all of that comes with proper documentation, the platform gives API providers the facility to document every parameter in each of the endpoints and data models. Providers can also auto-generate &#8220;getting started guides&#8221; for different IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_bvvGJZTDaI0E2-k57HCWHg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="has-text-align-center" style="text-align: left;">Once set, the developers navigate to their desired use case, copy-paste the code, and start working on the business logic — letting the SDK and the sample take care of logistics.</p>
<h2 id="21f7">Part III: Making Code Samples Work in Production</h2>
<p id="77cf" class="">Looking at the different styles of samples, the question that now arises is how practical are these samples to use? Do they completely replace the need to code, or are they just a push towards the right direction? Do they fully demonstrate the use case for the endpoint? Or do they just explain the logistics of making an API call?</p>
<h3 id="d87e">Language Coded HTTP Snippets or More?</h3>
<p id="6704">If you closely look at many of the auto-generated samples, especially the styles 1 to 4, what they essentially do is eliminate the redundant work of configuring environments, and help consumers figure out what kind of syntax to use. However, when making real-world use of API, you need a lot more. Do these samples, which essentially lack language structure and look like language translated HTTP requests, cut it? The answer is<strong>&nbsp;NO&nbsp;</strong>and for the following reasons:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>No Data Types:</strong>&nbsp;The samples takes input and output in the form of a string, leaving it to the consuming developers to write an efficient i/o mechanism to complete these requests. Often the fields inside the body are not documented.</li>
<li><strong>No Data Models:</strong>&nbsp;Modelling the JSON/XML as classes make it easier to deal with the data, both input, and output. These “models” add a whole different layer on top of the API, with your application having to interact with the model, instead of queried response in JSON or XML.</li>
<li><strong>No Validation and Error Handling:</strong>&nbsp;Since there is no proper I/O mechanism, and both inputs are taken and output returns in form of JSON strings, it’s impossible to validate the sent data and handle error cases to determine what went wrong with the request.</li>
</ul>
<p id="d900">To further demonstrate our point, we will write a&nbsp;<strong>Sample App&nbsp;</strong>to make a new&nbsp;<strong>pet&nbsp;</strong>entry to a store. The app will utilize Code Samples generated by&nbsp;<strong>Postman&nbsp;</strong>for the endpoint<strong>&nbsp;Add Pet.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_utlmN5MUbvMqVh3hRBnOTw-1.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e759" class="">Copy-pasting the code straight away did not work. To configure the HTTP client, we had to include the maven dependency to the build. Following which we found the authentication header missing. We passed in the credentials:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><strong><code>.addHeader(&quot;api_key&quot;, &quot;special-key&quot;)</code></strong></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b89b" class="">And then had to build a JSON String to pass in the input, since the argument body is passed as a String. Constructing an argument body of the two required fields, this is how the sample looked like:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><code>package TestApp.Testapp123;
import java.io.*;
import okhttp3.*;

 class main {
  public static void main(String []args) throws IOException{
     
	 OkHttpClient client = new OkHttpClient().newBuilder()
	 .build();
	  MediaType mediaType = MediaType.parse(&quot;application/json&quot;);
	  RequestBody body = RequestBody.create(mediaType, &quot;{\&quot;name\&quot;:\&quot;doggie\&quot;,\&quot;photoUrls\&quot;:[\&quot;photoUrls1\&quot;]}&quot;);
	  Request request = new Request.Builder()
	 .url(&quot;https://petstore.swagger.io/v2/pet&quot;)
	 .method(&quot;POST&quot;, body)
	 .addHeader(&quot;Accept&quot;, &quot;application/json, application/xml&quot;)
	 .addHeader(&quot;Content-Type&quot;, &quot;application/json&quot;)
	 .addHeader(&quot;api_key&quot;, &quot;special-key&quot;)
	 .build();	  
	  Response response = client.newCall(request).execute();
	  System.out.println(response.body().string()); 	
	    }
	  }</code></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">We ran the code after this tweaking, and it worked like a charm. So how do this sample further translates to real-world usage? If we were to take inputs for the Pet entry from a user, how do we send that as arguments? And before that how do we ensure the data taken from the user is the of the correct type? To tackle that we wrote a model class for the Pet Object, with all the underlying attributes including getters and setters.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted"><code>package TestApp.SimpleConsoleAppFix;

import java.util.List;

import io.swagger.petstore.models.Category;
import io.swagger.petstore.models.StatusEnum;
import io.swagger.petstore.models.Tag;

public class PetModel {
	
	    public Long getId() {
		return id;
	}
	public void setId(Long id) {
		this.id = id;
	}
	public Category getCategory() {
		return category;
	}
	public void setCategory(Category category) {
		this.category = category;
	}
	public String getName() {
		return name;
	}
	public void setName(String name) {
		this.name = name;
	}
	public List&lt;String&gt; getPhotoUrls() {
		return photoUrls;
	}
	public void setPhotoUrls(List&lt;String&gt; photoUrls) {
		this.photoUrls = photoUrls;
	}
	public List&lt;Tag&gt; getTags() {
		return tags;
	}
	public void setTags(List&lt;Tag&gt; tags) {
		this.tags = tags;
	}
	public StatusEnum getStatus() {
		return status;
	}
	public void setStatus(StatusEnum status) {
		this.status = status;
	}
	    Long id;
	    Category category;
	    String name;
	    List&lt;String&gt; photoUrls;
	    List&lt;Tag&gt; tags;
	    StatusEnum status;

}</code></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e551" class="">Following which we wrote the code to take in input values for these attributes. Now that we ensured we took in these values, with their correct data types, how do we pass these in the request, since the request passes the arguments in the form of a string. Manually doing this was, of course, unfeasible and out of the question, so we had to write in an object to string mapper to do the job for us. This took in these various attribute fields and put them together in the form of a JSON string.</p>
<p id="b586" class="">It was at this point that we were able to achieve a business use case out of the sample. We could pass in the input parameters, with their correct types, concatenated as a JSON string and passed along with the argument. The model allowed us to keep local records of the sent values as well.https://blog.devapi.dream.press/media/a6a1ace16d322eaaf541f83acf4905f9</p>
<p id="4294" class="">Working with multiple endpoints and multiple models would have taken us even more time, depending on the use case and business logic. For instance, for the GET endpoints, we would have to write a string to object mapper to parse values from the response string back to our model. While the sample does a great job pushing developers in the right direction, it is clear that it is not a plug and play situation. Developers have to put in a lot of code to get the calls running, and have to figure out on their own what goes before or comes after the API call.</p>
<p><em>Now imagine if there were samples that could take care of all these logistics, you had to write no communication code at all, and could just plug and play a sample into action. The good news is, you no longer have to imagine. The language idiomatic samples generated alongside an SDK already do that for you.</em></p>
<h2 id="21e8">Language Idiomatic Code Samples — The Way To Go</h2>
<p id="b15b">SDKs have often been labeled as the cornerstone of the API developer experience. What SDKs essentially do is that they abstract out all underlying details of making an API call, making your API look like a library. They provide developers a complete framework to model their applications, including all the necessary dependencies, referenced libraries, system libraries, i/o mechanisms, and class models.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ncYb-AnKZ5JZxOytMwp1PA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="4ce3" class="">Furthermore SDKs automatically format API responses to match the data types used in the programming language. They add an interface on top of the API, so your app interacts with the modeled data from SDK, instead of raw API arguments and responses. By providing SDKs, you can help developers focus on the business logic while taking care of API communication code.</p>
<p id="933e">Code samples generated with SDKs have a lot more work done on them. Since the SDK abstracts out request construction, none of the construction bit makes part of the sample, making the sample look very lean. Such samples can easily fit in with your applications in a very scalable manner, you only have to add minimal communication code, since there exist mechanisms to access, manipulate and work around with all the data fields, that go in and come out of an API call.</p>
<h2 class="has-text-align-center">. . .</h2>
<p id="308d" class="">Concluding this all, we strongly recommend that developers make use of code samples to consume APIs. No matter what style, design, or approach. Code samples will help you get started easily and save you tons of time. While for most people, the simple HTTP snippets may do the job, it is samples with more language structure that help with real-world use and can fit in straight with your applications.</p>
<p id="8467" class="">Again we emphasize the fact that the developer experience is a key driver for an API adoption. APIs are meant to execute integrations, and the easier to integrate, the better the API. Luckily for you, we at APIMatic hold all sorts of expertise to help improve the experience you deliver to developers. Reach out to us today at&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/contact">https://apimatic.io/contact</a>&nbsp;and let’s discuss what can be done to enhance your offerings today.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2020/06/the-anatomy-of-api-code-samples/">The Anatomy of API Code Samples</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sms Marketing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=436</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Every day, 23 billion SMS messages are sent worldwide, which is equivalent to 16 million messages per minute, exchanged between 7 billion mobile subscribers across the world — (CTIA) The SMS industry is huge, and the bulk SMS industry huger. Wide adoption and availability of the technology has made it the number one choice of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/">State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="436" class="elementor elementor-436">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-21c95151 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="21c95151" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-33c470a0" data-id="33c470a0" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-188ddceb elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="188ddceb" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-437 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_9S0vdIiVL9SvUXrR4vLH8w-1024x512.jpg" alt="State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020" width="1024" height="512"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<blockquote class="">
<p id="16fa" class="">Every day, 23 billion SMS messages are sent worldwide, which is equivalent to 16 million messages per minute, exchanged between 7 billion mobile subscribers across the world — (CTIA)</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="4cab" class="">The SMS industry is huge, and the bulk SMS industry huger. Wide adoption and availability of the technology has made it the number one choice of communication for businesses, who can now reach out to millions of people across the globe with the minimum of effort. Businesses today are making use of SMS messages to send alerts of all kinds, and for a very good reason.</p>
<blockquote class="">
<p id="d3ad" class="">SMS messages are more likely to be opened than Emails, a typical message is read within 3 minutes with a CTR of 19% versus 2% for email.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="b46e" class="">A lot of that is being done over (A2P), Application-to-Person, where an application is programmed to trigger messages at particular intervals or events. There are a number of tools available to run these campaigns, but none as customizable and powerful as SMS APIs which give direct control to businesses to build messaging facilities straight into their systems.</p>
<p id="9dc1" class="">As of now, they are more than&nbsp;<strong>750 Messaging APIs</strong>&nbsp;currently listed on Programmable Web, with more and more services being listed daily. Using SMS APIs, companies can send complex 2-Way SMS messages, marketing messages, verification messages, notifications, alerts and warnings of all kinds.</p>
<p id="0f97" class="">To see what makes some of these APIs so popular, we shortlisted a pool of them, analyzed what they had to offer, and what really makes them so popular in this age and time. The APIs that we analyzed include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li>Twilio</li>
<li>Nexmo</li>
<li>Plivo</li>
<li>Telstra</li>
<li>AT&amp;T</li>
<li>Bandwidth</li>
<li>ClickSend</li>
<li>MessageMedia</li>
</ul>
<p id="db07" class="">For the analysis, we started off by looking at the features these APIs have to offer, followed by the compliances they meet, and then their Developer Experience programs. By the end of the blog, you would know what does it take to stand out in the industry and compete with the giants we know today.</p>
<h2 id="9de9"><strong>Essential Features — SMS APIs 2019</strong></h2>
<p id="53af" class="">Analyzing these APIs in terms of the functionality they provide, we recognized that there are a set of features that are common to most of them. These features are the bare essentials if you want to make it in the SMS APIs space. They include:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-438 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_OVg9CFI3FVS4MJiJUYoohA.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8d87" class="">Many of the APIs included in this study go beyond that and have added more value, building on these features. For instance Twilio allows sending of MMS messages, allowing senders to attached pictures or other forms of media. Furthermore, they have a mechanism to recognize the optimum routes to send out messages, ensuring guaranteed delivery in record time. Nexmo features a persistent sending ID, using the same number to send messages to one person. Plivo features number pooling, to distribute campaign loads and ensure quicker delivery.</p>
<h2 id="3099"><strong>Compliance Requirements — SMS APIs 2019</strong></h2>
<p id="8c9e" class="">For the telecommunication industry, one of the biggest challenges faced is being compliant with local and international regulations. Often continents, countries, states and even specific carrier networks, have a set of rules they abide with, and unless an SMS API caters to these rules, messages may never be delivered as intended and campaigns may go in vain.</p>
<p id="6064" class="">For most top SMS APIs, all these regulations are met and precautions are implemented, some important regulations and guides include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><a href="https://www.fdic.gov/regulations/compliance/manual/8/viii-5.1.pdf">The TCPA (<em>Telephone Consumer Protection Act)</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://api.ctia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/190719-CTIA-Messaging-Principles-and-Best-Practices-FINAL.pdf">CTIA Messaging Principles and Best Practices</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.wixstatic.com/ugd/9456a5_72a6056a11f5401c95d29181e850625b.pdf">CTIA Short Code Monitoring Handbook</a></li>
</ul>
<p id="9a39">Some common practices to be globally compliant by most regulations include:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-439 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_X_kTbzcew9iAPJo5qvqq4A.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="57e4" class=""><strong>What Really Makes Great SMS APIs?</strong></h2>
<p id="6b08" class="">So by now, if you are trying to rate one SMS API over the other, you probably would run into too many of them offering the same set of features, with different implementations, all offering them one way or the other, leaving you guessing that which of them is really worth it?</p>
<p id="ecc8" class="">And for that, we take you to the question,&nbsp;<strong>what makes a great API?</strong></p>
<p id="5e94" class="">And the unanimous answer to that is great&nbsp;<strong>Developer Experience.</strong>&nbsp;All the best APIs are easy to consume and require shorter development time to integrate. At the end of the day, each API is supposed to facilitate interoperability, and the easier is it to integrate, the better the API.</p>
<p id="a149" class="">To see how these SMS APIs stood out, we analyzed their publicly available Docs and Developer Portals and came up with the matrix below, which summarizes our findings.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-440 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_q_AESiXsFaY4P0uKPSMWHg-1024x640.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="4f3d">Where each of these API providers fills in quite a number of checks on the Developer Experience Checklist, each of them stood out in some respective fields.</p>
<p id="481b" class="">Twilio, Nexmo and ClickSend do a wonderful job with their Landing Pages, which do a great job onboarding users with what facilities they offer, what features does the API come with and how can they help them solve problems with tons of uses cases, tutorials, and Sample Apps. Almost all API Providers have made use of visuals and diagrams to explain the inner workings of an API.</p>
<p id="ef3a" class="">Bandwidth offers a Sandbox environment where users could play around with the API, similarly, MessageMedia offers an API console where Code Samples can be tried around with. Telstra has a run in postman button, where you can try out sample calls, the click of a button takes you to the postman tool.</p>
<p id="ec68">Both Twilio and Nexmo offer a dedicated API Service Status page, with intuitive layout structures that help consumers get to their desired bit of information faster.</p>
<p id="d7b9" class="">SDKs and Code Samples are also something that all these popular APIs have to offer, popular languages being: Ruby, PHP, Python, JavaScript, C# and Node.</p>
<h2 id="1752" class=""><strong>Great Developer Experience: A Challenge</strong></h2>
<p id="d64f" class="">If you are out at this making an SMS API, it’s essential that you miss out on none of these offerings, or you will stand no chance against the competition. Often smaller teams come up with brilliant technology but lack the numbers to focus on anything else except the core offering. It is just as essential to focus on material revolving around the API, the marketing pages, documentation, client libraries and much more, all of which take a lot of time, effort and energy, but without none of which your API will see success or adoption.</p>
<p id="54e5" class="">While companies like Twilio, Nexmo, and AT&amp;T can afford to heavily invest in programs like that, for startups and smaller companies it becomes impossible to spare time or money. With the cost and time it takes to produce all of this material, it’s not scalable with evolution, often Docs and SDKs lag far behind when APIs are multiple versions ahead, and this is the reason.</p>
<p id="4f0d" class="">So the challenge here is how do you take your brilliant API out to developers when you don’t have the means to keep it developer-friendly for long?</p>
<p id="050f" class="">And the answer lies in automation, while a human developer may take several days to produce and maintain all of these components, Code-Gen Engines can take an API Spec as input to automatically generate all of these components and all of it within a few minutes. Want to make updates to your API? Don’t worry, build the engine into your CI/CD pipeline and generate new components with every new push, release or update.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-441 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/0_UFKse1UtCEOQwgJr.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="691f" class="">All you now have to do is, add more and more features to your API, make it compliant to the point you can rollover your competition, while a Code-Gen Engine takes care of the material you need to put it out in front of Developers.</p>
<p id="7373" class="">Need to talk more about automating Developer Experience?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.apimatic.io/contact">Speak to us</a>&nbsp;today and we’ll help you get started.</p>
<p class="">Thanks to&nbsp;Adam DuVander.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/">State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Psd2]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=627</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>FinTech Startups have leveraged upon the utility of Web APIs to dominate the financial services industry, and traditional financial institutes are following suit, executing strategies like the&#160; Open Banking&#160; initiative, to expose their services. When so many options are available, putting out an API is never enough, it’s essential to make sure developers can actually [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/">Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="627" class="elementor elementor-627">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-68285476 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="68285476" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-31224221" data-id="31224221" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-44df238c elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="44df238c" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="alignnone wp-image-628" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_sBXfWZNYodHGMEjtg17YKQ-1024x512.jpg" alt="Popular Developer Experience Practices in FinTech and Banking APIs" width="1024" height="512"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="743e" class="">FinTech Startups have leveraged upon the utility of Web APIs to dominate the financial services industry, and traditional financial institutes are following suit, executing strategies like the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/o/open-banking.asp"> Open Banking&nbsp; </a>initiative, to expose their services.</p>
<p id="a8fb" class="">When so many options are available, putting out an API is never enough, it’s essential to make sure developers can actually make use of the API in an effective and efficient manner. And for this, we have analyzed some popular APIs from both the Open Banking and FinTech Space. We evaluated these APIs using our Developer Experience checklist as a reference, which has been endorsed by industry experts like Kin Lane, Adam Duvander and more</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-630" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Sd1gAl5zc8GjfcY3Mi4MCw-1.jpg" alt="" width="567" height="441"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b918">The list of APIs derived from multiple resources, including RapidAPI, GoMedic, etc. include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><em>Barclays APIs</em></li>
<li><em>Nordea Bank</em></li>
<li><em>Citi APIs</em></li>
<li><em>Deutsche Bank</em></li>
<li><em>Stripe</em></li>
<li><em>Square</em></li>
<li><em>Visa</em></li>
<li><em>CoinAPI</em></li>
</ul>
<p id="afad">For the study, we analyzed, their publicly available resources, including their developer portals, product pages, and all underlying documentation and components.</p>
<p id="49a0">We have summarized our research in the form of a table to give you a quick overview of both Banking and FinTech APIs in terms of what they are offering.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-631 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_buxsZK1nfOKAtciwSwysOg.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="6743">And then further discuss in depth and detail, how each of these vendors has gone about with individual components.</p>
<h2 id="1a0c" class="">1. Citibank</h2>
<p id="e44a" class=""><a href="https://sandbox.developerhub.citi.com/us/home">Citibank’s</a>&nbsp;API program comprises of 11 APIs in total, the documentation for all of which they have available on a single developer portal. Their developer portal which they call the “Developer Hub” comes with a beautiful Landing Page, which features their API Catalog, Getting Started Guides, Use Cases and Success Stories.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-632 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Z1wTN5ipavKTJKGh8kSbBw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="46c1">This is followed by a brief preview of some sample API Calls and Responses, which they do rather intuitively.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-633 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_JxdaUGEX-QsGevwEbgSxpA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b6a0">Landing pages are where consumers usually make their choice and it’s important you help them make it by selling a value proposition, and Citibank builds on that beautifully.</p>
<p id="5ecd">Signing Up is pretty easy, straightforward, and requires just a username and passwords, upon activation, you are allowed to generate your own API keys. Most of the portal is accessible without logging in, which is essential for a portal of any nature in this age.</p>
<p id="cc95" class="">The API Catalog page displays all their APIs in a very organized manner, classified according to function and location, they are easy to search and browse. Each API has an in detailed Overview Page, which explains what an API does and how does it do it. Since Citi Banks serves different markets, their pages and documentation is specifically curated for each region.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-634 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_oNnGMYt60NKEZc09o5h4hw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="5871" class="">Citi Bank’s API Playground lets you play around with their APIs in a really intuitive manner. It takes in your Client ID and Secret to generate an access token, following which you chose an app to make a sample call, with parameters you want to experiment with.</p>
<p id="72ee">The Documentation pages start with a short summary of what the API does, followed by authorization instructions. The endpoints are grouped according to function and can be accessed via sidebar navigation.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-635 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_VAqtcC1IU74RrJ-vX7xmJw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="bcbc">The endpoints for each group are first listed, and then explained in detail. The descriptions are accompanied by Code Samples in 8 languages. CitiBank adds a really interesting touch to how these samples are displayed by offering a light and dark mode and making them copy-paste ready. For each API call, they also list and explain the possible responses and error messages in cases applicable. They also give out a swagger specification for each API.</p>
<p id="41a9" class="">The FAQs section covers all topics from registration to security in detail and tries to answer as many questions as possible. The Sales and Support pages provide an email interface to request help from their teams.</p>
<p id="8de5">Their portal overall looks really neat and clean is simple to use and looks like it does belong from the CitiBank line of products.</p>
<h2 id="89c6">2. Deutsche Bank</h2>
<p id="8015" class=""><a href="https://developer.db.com/">Deutsche Bank&nbsp; </a>offers around 9 APIs, grouped by function and all cataloged on their Developer Portal, which in their navy blue and grey colors, looks beautiful. On the landing page of the portal, they communicate important announcements, updates, and features straight at the top, which is followed by a listing of their API Products.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-636 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_U844WNNZStZlgZYom7PPoA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="05c5" class="">Deutsche then builds on trust by highlighting their advanced security protocols, since that’s a big concern for developers before working with any kind of financial gateway. Addressing potential interests as such, early on, can help you hook visitors even before they explore your code. Deutsche understands that and builds on it by exhibiting their beautiful API Explorer next.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-637 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_8tGFG4yeRr7DwuoCuDuF5Q.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8840">Following that they present a customer story to explain a common use case, and then display the ideal user journey with the help of visuals. Deutsche makes use of visuals to explain workflows and inner workings of their APIs at various places.</p>
<p id="d679" class="">Their portal also features news and events channels, where they highlight latest releases, new features, publish their events and talk about new ideas. This sort of engagement plays a crucial role in connecting with the community, which they successfully do.</p>
<p id="ce02">Each API has a pretty rich Overview page, which talks about the features of an API, explains what it does, pricing plans, and then links to the API Explorer so developers can get to experiment with it straight away.</p>
<p id="af18">Getting started guides are really thorough and explain how to register an account and apply for authorization keys. Reference Docs are beautiful, with endpoints for each API grouped together and each endpoint with every parameter is explained in detail.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-638 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_eW6RhLBKzYUHyWWTu_fJ-A.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="2553">The interactive API explorer allows to make sample calls straight away and displays potential responses according to the type of call made.</p>
<p id="7730">Deutsche goes an extra mile with support and allows users to request features, contact them for general inquiries, seek troubleshooting support, or report bugs all from the same page. The FAQs page pretty much explain everything and serve as an excellent self-servicing support option.</p>
<p id="aaec">We love the slick UI, and the use of visuals that Deutsche makes, everything is pretty easy to understand, although they lack a few basic components, that could have elevated their developer experience even further.</p>
<h2 id="7821">3.&nbsp; Nordea Open Banking</h2>
<p id="3238" class=""><a href="https://developer.nordeaopenbanking.com/app/">Nordea Bank</a>&nbsp;offers one of the best onboarding techniques we have seen in any portal across any industry, they take users across the entire journey from registering, setting up an app, to generating API keys and everything, with beautiful visuals and step by step content.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-639 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_fvgKszBdWB74IMHiel2mfA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0e2d" class="">With that, they also offer training videos for multiple scenarios, Swagger and Postman collections for all APIs and sample code, which can be accessed on their GitHub.</p>
<p id="1477">The Landing Page is beautiful and builds upon the value the bank delivers via their APIs, we loved how they have testimonials as social proof and then evangelize the open banking industry as a whole with articles and blogs straight on the Landing Page.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-640 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_04n0Xe9uX_aBFB65UHvxgQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="1d3d">Nordea also deals with multiple APIs, each with an Overview Page, that helps customers understand what they can achieve with it, Nordea uses visuals to explain how their APIs work. To build up trust further, they have their API roadmaps up, so evaluating developers can foresee what the future would look like, helping them make a solid well-informed decision.</p>
<p id="381f" class="">Documentation for APIs starts with Change Logs and Version release notes. We believe that is a really important practice, early on educating users, what preliminary actions they have to take before going on with implementation are really important. We love how they set out the context, and answer any sort of considerations such as security concerns, terminology, rate limiting and all other queries a user may have before they actually get to documentation.</p>
<p id="7c35">The Reference docs are beautiful, come with a detailed description of parameters, sample call request, and responses and an API Console where those calls can be tried out and tested.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-641 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_UUS5QtbansjtDK7MWt-nTw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9fa3" class="">The endpoints are listed on the sidebar, from where they are easily navigable. Nordea gives out OpenAPI spec for each API and recommend to generate client libraries on Swagger CodeGen but do not have that listed as an offering anywhere on their portal, and have a few languages agnostic code samples listed on their GitHub.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-642 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_mVoY-OQjtIvfZCVWBb5yRQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="5f7c">The support section once again does a great job, covers up pretty much everything with FAQs and provides an option to seek help by raising tickets or discussing issues with the community.</p>
<h2 id="eff2" class="">4. Barclays’s API</h2>
<p id="ed81" class=""><a href="https://developer.barclays.com/">Barclay’s API&nbsp; </a>program is one of the largest in the industry, with over 12 well-maintained APIs and more in experimental phases, they have made sure they deliver a great developer experience.</p>
<p id="c59d" class="">Their developer portal is the face of their API program and they have managed the entire project beautifully.</p>
<p id="57ac" class="">On the Landing Page, they send out a very bold message about their mission, and with that list their APIs, customer stories, use cases and talk about open banking overall. Building upon the value of their offering is something that all API providers have done in this space and we cannot stress how important that is considering the competition in this fast-paced industry.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-643 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_rVKQVWYGDJVClxHLGuyOBw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="65e8" class="">The next most important thing on a portal is an API Overview Page and Barclay’s does a wonderful job, making use of video content to explain the offering. They highlight all key features and benefits and explain what customers would need to get started.</p>
<p id="ad0f">Registering an account is standard practice and takes no longer than a minute, getting started guides are in fair detail and depth as well, covering everything from key features, version history, to prerequisites.</p>
<p id="35f8">The Reference Docs do a fair job in explaining what an endpoint does and comes with code samples in some cases. Barclay’s also gives out an API Specification in RAML format for their APIs, so that you can make use of complementary tooling and take maximum advantage out of it.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-644 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_hAKD7gXoFC516OVW1bLg4Q.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="470f" class="">The FAQs section which they call their knowledge Base does a decent job explaining the ins and outs of the program on top of which they have to get in touch option, so consumers can approach them at any given time.</p>
<h2 id="4fc7">5.&nbsp; Square</h2>
<p id="c05e"><a href="https://squareup.com/us/en/developers">Square</a>&nbsp;is one of the leading payment processing companies in the US, and they made that possible, with easy to integrate services and great developer experience. With an API first model, they have enabled both hardware and software to seamlessly integrate and provide a butter smooth experience.</p>
<p id="9192" class="">To make their APIs easy to consume, they tick almost all major things on the developer checklist. Their developer portal looks great, is easy to navigate, and makes use of visuals for explanations where necessary.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-645 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_jp1Bs05rOfDwpyyX7p96jA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e657" class="">The Landing Page highlights all major features, benefits, pricing plans, customer stories, sample apps and support channels that a visitor may require to begin with.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-646 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZRb7WbHCLFasEkBavOAI9w.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="2a40">The Documentation Page begins with a step by step guide on how to get started on their platform, registering an account, generating authorization keys and handling errors, etc. Square strongly believes that developers get help implementing their APIs in languages they are comfortable with and hence give out multiple SDKs in multiple platforms, which they proudly present on their portal before everything. This is followed by a few sample applications where developers can take inspiration from. They then list out their APIs, each API has an Overview Page, where they talk about how to use it, work with it, prerequisites and pricing.</p>
<p id="829c">The Reference Docs which they call, Technical References, are put out in a three — column architecture, the in-app postman button allows testing out Sample Requests and views their responses.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-647 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_jLci1f78TTheTq3QgqXbbA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="ca97">The docs are really well done and coupled together with SDKs, make it very easy to integrate their services into any system, no matter what the platform. A reason that many modern companies chose to go with services as such, saving implementation time and cost at their end.</p>
<p id="d7e9">Square has a developer blog, newsletter, a dedicated slack channel and an email widget built into their portal, so any developer can reach out to them anytime.</p>
<h2 id="4ffd" class="">6.&nbsp; Stripe</h2>
<p id="1332"><a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a>&nbsp;offers one of the best if not the absolute best developer experience, not only in the FinTech space but in the entire API industry. They offer everything that makes API consumption easy and hence comes as no surprise that they are one of the most popular payment processing platforms today.</p>
<p id="5bd6" class="">Stripe deal in several APIs, and on their landing page catalog them in a way which makes it really easy for developers to figure out what they need. Developers can check out these APIs straight away on their try it out section which comes straight after. This is followed by development guides and other tips which may help developers jump-start their platforms.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-648 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_qNBkJK3isl3rHINeDli3gQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="af6e" class="">Where Stripe wins is that they on-board non-developer decision makers as well, and have a comprehensive guide explaining their offering in a non-technical way and not only that, they have pre-built plug-ins and extensions which can be configured to trigger their APIs, allowing non-developer users take advantage of what they have to offer.</p>
<p id="bc42">Each API has an Overview Page which thoroughly explains what consumers can achieve from that API. Stripe goes an extra mile and helps users implement APIs in a number of ways, including pre-built UI components for both Web and Mobile, along with SDKs in multiple platforms. The guides section is full of code samples and instructions for each kind of implementation, including the necessary CSS or styling files that go with it.</p>
<p id="69be">The Getting Started Guides are platform specific, so users have no trouble setting up their environments or IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-649 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_xUDhmY2weHITfL_Ti1-XIQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="30d5">They make use of visuals where they can to explain workflows and journeys, which they present in a very engaging manner.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-650 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZMPqddEakPYNg8l2urEsDA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="97ed">The Reference Docs give a really clean look and very easy to go through, there’ s no clutter or confusion, each endpoint in explained in detail, and come with Code samples in multiple languages including Ruby, Python, PHP, Java, Node, .NET and GO.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-651 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_meK6rJlTjqgS2VbtsfHHSA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="f2c0">They have forums and discussion boards where developers can engage with the community anytime to solve their queries, on top of which representatives from Stripe are always on the look around to guide anyone in need. Alternatively, their team can also be reached out via email, chat or phone. With their Developer digest, they effectively communicate any changes and updates to their users, which is an opt-in service, with the widget available on the landing page.</p>
<p id="0f93" class="">We love how they have made their platform accessible to global communities and render all of their documentation it in around 7 languages, earning them bonus accessibility points.</p>
<p id="9e64">Stripe completes everything that is on our Developer Experience checklist and it should come as no surprise that it is the number 1 choice for so many businesses when it comes to payment processing.</p>
<h2 id="e101">7. Visa</h2>
<p id="baf5"><a href="https://developer.visa.com/">Visa</a>&nbsp;is one of the largest payment networks across the world, that facilitates millions of electronic transactions per minute. The service is made available to vendors and businesses through a number of APIs and plug-ins.</p>
<p id="7286">Visa’s Developer Center is one of the most beautiful Developer Experience platforms we have seen, it encompasses all their values, branding and visuals to deliver a delightful experience. On the Landing Page, straight on the top, they have a scroll where they advertise their devrel events, ask for feedback and present their tutorials.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-652 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_-afTH4rlFSJLIFTLeoQBsQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="fa88" class="">After that, they list their API catalog, which can be further browsed in detail, along with that they mention multiple use cases over various verticals and industries. We love how they present their Customer Stories, which they do in the form of videos, which are engaging and beautiful captivate the attention of landing visitors.</p>
<p id="08c1">On the catalog page, the APIs are grouped together according to function and can be browsed using filters on the left. Each API has an in detail Overview Page, which explains what the API is for, who can use it, how are they supposed to priced and their regional availability.</p>
<p id="3183">They make use of visuals were required to explain key features, workflows and supporting APIs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-653 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_3vqm1iafbyh-I10K_AjCjA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8c7e">The Getting Started Guides are really through and explains step by step how to make use of APIs, the reference docs are presented in a three column architecture, with sample calls and responses, that can be tried out on their interactive API Explorer.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-654 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_qtfBVr8xMyG9LcKRT1a-Gg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="cea7" class="">Where we found Visa to be leading, is how they communicate with users, all types of messaging are really rich, vibrant and deliver their point across in a beautiful manner.</p>
<p id="2b21">They have separate pages for Release Notes, Glossary, Support where they have FAQs, a whole About Us page where they explain why to use any of Visa APIs at all and a Contact Us page which directs you to an email widget.</p>
<p id="8fac">On top of that, they have a Developer blog, where they keep posting the latest news, updates and tips about their services, and a community page where users can come discuss and solve each other’s problems.</p>
<p id="4b10" class="">Developer Experience is more than just Docs and Visa treating their APIs like products truly proves that, no wonder they are where they stand today.</p>
<h2 id="1678"><strong>8. CoinAPI</strong></h2>
<p id="2b30" class="">CoinAPI is a unique cryptocurrency API that combines data from all virtual currency exchanges and makes it available through a single platform. The API provides incredible utility to cryptocurrency traders and has become a huge hit in the space. What has made the API so successful is the ease when it comes to consuming it. Through their documentation practices, they have made it really easy to work with the many endpoints and terabytes of data they have to offer.</p>
<p id="987e">When you land on their site, you are taken straight away to the product pages which are beautifully done.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-655 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_n-cQwQ7AAzORIaWaZAy7ew.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="19c4">The pages cover everything, from the exceptional value the API provides, to the social proof, uses cases and how client libraries are available in multiple languages.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-656 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_gXfChIGczKqlDoaWQUSi2g.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="893d" class="">The documentation site is done in the same branding and looks striking in their navy blue. The landing page for the documentation site gives a thorough explanation of their API programs, which is divided into three distinct protocols, REST, WebSocket and FIX. This ensures they keep developers across all boards happy since REST is a popular API format overall and other two popular in the finance space.</p>
<p id="278d">After that, they talk about the SDKs which the offer in 15 languages. For them the SDKs are an integral part of their offerings, hence are well tested and well maintained and they encourage the use of it, while also accepting suggestions to their main repository from the community.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-657 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_52_Xw6Ldw9JIRTNiPhBB1w.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b77f">This is followed by security protocols, and the standards and conventions the APIs follow.</p>
<p id="bda5">CoinAPI does a wonderful job educating users, on how and where to get started with their APIs, before they nosedive into development and we give them full points for that. All three APIs have a short overview which explains how to work with that particular format, along with necessary details such as authorization, request limits, etc.</p>
<p id="a921">The Reference Docs are presented in a really neat manner, have nicely done descriptions, and come with code samples in 9 languages. We love the way they do their warnings, disclaimers, and tips, making them extremely legible.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-658 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_EUHWgbjJSOmdgnoGLKdevA-1024x343.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0e8b">They have a dedicated page for support, where they have separate tabs for FAQs, Security &amp; Privacy, Announcements, Billing and Subscriptions, answering every potential query a user might run across. CoinAPI gets full marks for communication as well, the support page is easy to navigate, has a search function and serves as an effective communication channel between them and consuming developers.</p>
<p id="a8dd">Coming from an industry that is still emerging, it’s impressive how they check most of the things from the Developer Experience checklist. And their wide adoption should come as no surprise.</p>
<p id="c17a">Summarizing the research we found out, although most of these APIs offer a number of components from the Developer Experience checklist, it’s FinTech APIs that has taken the lead by offering SDKs and investing more in thier documentation practises. A developer coming in for a payment solution is more likely going to choose an API, which has an implementation available in a language they are comfortable with and is more convenient to use, hence no wonder Stripe and Square are global leaders today.</p>
<p id="889f" class="">If you are in the Finance industry, you too can offer an amazing developer experience for your API, and without putting in the hard work, time or dedicating resources. We can help you get started with your developer experience program from the Landing Pages, to Docs, Code Samples, SDKs, and everything.&nbsp;</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/">Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=660</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Banking and Finance industry is one of the most heavily regulated sectors of the world. The regulations, although important to protect the integrity of the system and customer interest, come at the cost of hindered advancement and such had been the case for the industry. This was until the rise of FinTech companies, who [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/">State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="660" class="elementor elementor-660">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-34f857ff elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="34f857ff" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-4aea8260" data-id="4aea8260" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-4a141574 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="4a141574" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-661 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_AwRHHaXNeo1O2pu7hQz8ag-1024x512.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="d6ac" class="">The Banking and Finance industry is one of the most heavily regulated sectors of the world. The regulations, although important to protect the integrity of the system and customer interest, come at the cost of hindered advancement and such had been the case for the industry.</p>
<p id="db59" class="">This was until the rise of FinTech companies, who leveraged APIs as gateways to expose traditional financial services so that third-party developers could build custom solutions on top of them. There’s a lot you can achieve with FinTech APIs, without having to go through the labor of manually implementing any functionality.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>A simple query on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.programmableweb.com/search/financial"> ProgrammableWeb</a>shows there are&nbsp;<em>1956</em>&nbsp;APIs listed under the tag of Financial APIs, with around&nbsp;<em>290</em>&nbsp;listed this very year.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="e432" class="">FinTech APIs are putting immense pressure on Traditional Banking and Financial Organisations, who are actively trying to catch up. Customers today expect advanced, frictionless experiences and banks with traditional business models are failing to provide them.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-662 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_o6g31nFwrWSkx9twG7rzOw.jpg" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>A stat from EY’s FinTech Adoption Index shows that globally, 64% of “Digitally active consumers” are using FinTech applications in favor of traditional banking ones.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="d65f" class="">When <a href="https://assets.ey.com/content/dam/ey-sites/ey-com/en_gl/topics/banking-and-capital-markets/ey-global-fintech-adoption-index.pdf">Ernst and Young&nbsp; </a>conducted their first study on FinTech adoption in 2015, they found adoption rates for FinTech as low as 10% amongst the consumers they surveyed. The number rose to 33% in 2017 and now stands at 64%. More and more individuals especially millennials, are shying away from traditional banking and instead are inclined more towards digital solutions put out by these FinTech companies.</p>
<p id="4c55" class="">It’s clearly time for banks to explore newer business models and to expose data and functionality in a similar fashion, acting as the infrastructure or platform on which financial services of the future are built. Else tech giants or startups in the space will ultimately wipe them over.</p>
<h2 id="d558" class="">Open Banking and Europe’s PSD2</h2>
<p id="9911" class="">In 2015 the European Parliament adopted new legislation, Payment Services Directive 2 better known as <a href="https://www.ecb.europa.eu/paym/intro/mip-online/2018/html/1803_revisedpsd.en.html">PSD2</a>, to streamline the digitalisation of banks and financial services. The directive obligates banks across Europe to make banking data and services available to third-party developers, so they can build value-added services on top of them.</p>
<p id="dca9">The concept of Open Banking, on the other hand, has been around for much longer and it suggests that banks provide access to user data via Open APIs, so that they can partner with external entities to improve customer experience.</p>
<p id="0b6b" class="">The Open Banking Initiative is powering PSD2 today, for which deadlines are running out and banks are putting out APIs on a daily basis. The directive has provided Banks with an excellent opportunity to make their mark, tight deadlines have forced banks to work faster on API preparation, resulting in 529 Banking APIs publicly listed as of today.</p>
<p id="4a24">Banks, because of the initiative, and the legislation are on their way to make a comeback, but is just putting out an API enough?</p>
<h2 id="33c8" class="">Developer Experience Makes APIs Useable</h2>
<p id="5ca8" class="">Developers today have a wide array of choices. A number of Banking and Finance APIs today provide the same utility and services, some implementing them in a different manner, some adopting different technology stacks, but what truly sets these APIs apart is the ease when it comes to consumption.</p>
<p id="07ff" class="">Developers want to get started as soon as possible, spend as little time getting acquainted with the API, and focus more on building creative solutions on top of them. In order for an API to be widely adopted, it must have a great developer experience.</p>
<p id="0ba7" class="">Since Developer Experience is a huge deciding factor when it comes to adopting an API, we sat down and shortlisted 8 popular Banking and Finance APIs and analysed what they have to offer in terms of Developer Experience, and what makes them popular choices amongst developers.</p>
<p id="6fa9" class="">Using the famous Developer Experience checklist as criteria and point of reference, we noticed some common trends and practices, which are objectively summarised in the table below:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Read in detail what forms the Developer Experience Checklist for APIs: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/what-exactly-is-developer-experience-1646b813df14">What exactly is Developer Experience?</a></p>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-663" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_buxsZK1nfOKAtciwSwysOg-1.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="19ca" class="">Quickly skimming through the table you would notice that most of these APIs offer a number of components from the Developer Experience checklist, and hence comes as no surprise why they are doing so well. One area we saw FinTech APIs lead, was with offering API implementations in multiple languages, in the form of SDKs, so developers can instantly start making use of these APIs in languages they are comfortable with.</p>
<p id="91fc" class="">We further ran a detailed analysis to find out how these APIs have gone about with their Developer Experience and what sets them apart from each other and remaining of the competition, which you can go through here:&nbsp;<a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis-a5474fe535e4"> Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs.</a></p>
<h3 id="8e19"><strong>PSD2 is an Opportunity for Digital Transformation</strong></h3>
<p id="2287" class="">FinTech APIs have built popularity, cashing on the exemplary experiences they provide, both to developers and customers, and Banking APIs that have followed suit have done well. But this is not the case for every bank out there. PSD2, although very explicitly requires banks to open up data and banking functionalities, it does not specify how banks are supposed to meet these requirements, with many just checking them off with bare minimum implementations.</p>
<p id="8b13" class="">Banks that are looking to just adhere to regulatory requirements and not do more, may miss out on big opportunities to expand and grow new business models, and may not be able to put themselves on the map with FinTech APIs.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>According to a survey, only 59% of Europe’s 442 banks met PSD2’s 14th March deadline, to have a publicly available testing facility or a sandbox environment .</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="a963">Of course, it is easier said than done and many banks are still struggling to prepare their APIs, with most of them slacking behind. In order to fulfill legal requirements, the API experience gets second fiddle. While understandable, it leads to a missed opportunity nonetheless</p>
<p id="adf4" class="">With the final 29th September deadline looming ahead, a number of Banking APIs are going to hit the markets, and only the ones that come with a developer experience will catch all the buzz, leaving the rest trailing on traction.</p>
<h2 id="32b5" class="">Automation is the Key to Scaling Developer Experience</h2>
<p id="0227" class="">So where does this leave API teams today who are still working on their API and have no time or resources to work on the consumption part of it?</p>
<p id="8a9a" class="">And the answer lies in&nbsp;<strong>Automation</strong>.</p>
<p id="833d" class="">With all hands busy on deck working on the core functionality of APIs, there is no reason that resources have to be dedicated to just work on producing the artifacts that make APIs easier to consume. Instead, let the machines do the working for you!</p>
<p id="3749">A lot can be done with an API Specification today. The document, when passed through CodeGen engines, can drive entire Developer Experience(DX) for APIs with automatic generation of DX components. And not just Documentation or Portals, but also complex components like SDKs, Code Samples, API Explorers and can even CI/CD pipelines so none of this has to be updated manually.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<figure id="attachment_664" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-664" style="width: 800px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-664" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZE_9hIZFJCH8to2mVeNeig.gif" alt="Generate DX Components with just an API Specification" width="800" height="450"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-664" class="wp-caption-text">Generate DX Components with just an API Specification</figcaption></figure>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="0f4d" class="">Get Started ASAP</h2>
<p id="5df6" class="">Where are you with Developer Experience for your APIs? Pushing for that 29th September Deadline and have no idea where to get started? Don’t worry about it.</p>
<p id="a7bb">Luckily for you, here at APIMatic, this is our specialty. We hold the necessary skills and expertise to help you set up an automated Developer Experience solution, and with our in-house technology, can get you running within weeks!</p>
<p id="f9ff" class="">You can always&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/contact">reach out to our team</a>&nbsp;to discuss Developer Experience and we’ll help you find an easy way out that fits your need. There’s no reason you have to stay behind and not compete with the top Banking and FinTech APIs of today.&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/account/register"> Get started&nbsp; </a>as soon as you can!</p>
<p class="">Thanks to&nbsp;Adam DuVander.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/">State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Create SDKs for your API in less than a Minute ⏰</title>
		<link>/blog/2018/11/how-to-create-sdks-for-your-api-in-less-than-a-minute/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 11:27:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=553</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Having a quality Developer Experience does not stop at having great API docs. You need to provide client or helper libraries in the form of SDKs (Software Development Kits) to help accelerate the API consumption process. Many API experts and gurus over the years have advocated the importance of shipping out SDKs with APIs, including: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/11/how-to-create-sdks-for-your-api-in-less-than-a-minute/">How to Create SDKs for your API in less than a Minute ⏰</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="553" class="elementor elementor-553">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-16a5e6e1 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="16a5e6e1" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-5cc2933e" data-id="5cc2933e" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-1ca8595 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="1ca8595" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-554 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_NgUaKbvONyap68fNeb11OQ.jpg" alt="How to Create SDKs for your API in less than a Minute using APIMatic" width="800" height="350"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="74c5" class="">Having a quality Developer Experience does not stop at having great API docs. You need to provide client or helper libraries in the form of SDKs (Software Development Kits) to help accelerate the API consumption process. Many API experts and gurus over the years have advocated the importance of shipping out SDKs with APIs, including:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kinlane/">Kin Lane</a>the&nbsp;<a href="https://apievangelist.com/">API Evangelist</a>, for whom SDKs form an important part of the&nbsp;<a href="https://apievangelist.com/2018/07/12/my-api-lifecycle-checklist-and-scorecard/"> Developer Experience checklist.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kvantomme/">Kristof Van Tomme </a>who lists SDKs as one of the&nbsp;<a href="https://nordicapis.com/how-bad-developer-portals-kill-apis/">eight important key features</a>&nbsp;of every successful developer portal.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/duvander/">Adam Duvander</a><strong>,&nbsp;</strong>whose&nbsp;<a href="https://everydeveloper.com/developer-experience/">DX Index</a>&nbsp;comprises 13 separate criteria, each weighted according to importance. At top of the list, lies libraries available in popular languages.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="e648" class="">It is no longer enough to expose your API endpoints with just the HTTP Docs or API references. You need to attract developers with platforms that are native to them, you need to enable them to comfortably play around with your code, and this is what SDKs help with.</p>
<p id="1305" class=""><mark>In simpler terms, SDKs are like a cockpit for your API, they put your consumers into the driving seat and ensure that they feel powerful and in total control!</mark></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-555 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_VupZPPjtjhb2QeaWFQr0jQ.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="c145" class="">Many API Providers after accepting the need of giving out SDKs, ponder over what languages should they offer them in? The golden answer for this is as many as you can. Developers today are working with a number of languages and platforms, the diversity when it comes to adoption of new technology is all time high. According to a survey on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.programmableweb.com/news/what-programming-language-most-popular-apis/2013/06/03"> Programmable web</a>, these are the languages programmers are using the most to consume APIs:</p>
<ol class="">
<li>PHP</li>
<li>Python</li>
<li>Ruby</li>
<li>.NET / C#</li>
<li>Java</li>
<li>Perl</li>
<li>ColdFusion</li>
<li>Node.js</li>
<li>ActionScript</li>
</ol>
<p id="aa4d" class="">Some of these languages may be losing popularity, and new languages are being adopted day by day but the fact still remains that APIs are being consumed in multiple languages and you need to cater the need.</p>
<p id="54ab" class="">Which again gives birth to the question:</p>
<h2 id="97f0" class="">How are you going to create SDKs in all these languages?</h2>
<p id="2d24" class="">While it may seem easy, writing client libraries for an API that you wrote yourself, it’s not so simple. It does not only require hours of redundant labour work but also a number of resources, loads of time and a lot of testing, making SDKs more of a chore. Companies who have the $$$ and resources to build in-house SDKs with language experts are at an advantage, leaving the rest dreaming.</p>
<p id="60c0" class="">Maintaining SDKs is a whole different story. Even companies with huge API teams struggle to update their SDKs on time. APIs tend to evolve and version over time and with every new update, the SDKs go obsolete. Reflecting these changes across SDKs in multiple languages in a way that does not break things is tough, time-consuming work.</p>
<p id="8a6b" class=""><mark>Simple maths reveal that around 83% of the total SDK cost comes from keeping it up to date and bug-free after every API update.</mark></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-556 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_1cyAbmzqIEDsFn6W2GIf0A.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9cff" class="">Its safe to assume that in order to write a single SDK, a developer who is proficient enough to write idiomatic code is required full time. Assuming the developer takes a week to build and test that SDK on a pay rate of $46/hour (bls.gov), then the cost turns out to be $1,852 for SDK in one language.</p>
<p id="67a2" class="">Cost of maintaining an SDK although depends on many variables like how frequent the API is changed or what’s the size of the library. For the sake of simplicity let’s assume it takes two days a month on average for a developer to maintain an SDK. With same cost assumptions, the burn turns out to be $8,885 for maintaining a single SDK over a year. Summing up both building and maintenance cost gives us a figure of $11,000 per API per SDK per language.</p>
<p id="e055" class="">Multiply this by the number of languages or APIs, we’re looking at sizeable costs, for just manually writing and maintaining SDKs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-557 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Czg0DEbC41Fx0Az2AaEU4g.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="2b93" class="">Not to mention the delays in time-to-market caused by making changes in API(s), reflecting them in Client libraries, checking for breaking changes and finally releasing updated documentation.</p>
<p id="2bec" class="">The SDK dream with all the $$$ and effort involved turns into an SDK nightmare. With many even questioning their worth and value.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p><em>“Necessity is the mother of Invention”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p id="5197">Over years scientists and engineers have worked hard to replace redundant work with automation, that’s how the first wheels, machines and engines were made.</p>
<p id="c8ad">And as soon a need was recognized to automate the laborious process of creating SDKs, birth was given to code generators for APIs.</p>
<h2 id="afce">What are Code Generators?</h2>
<p id="69eb" class="">Code Generators are the engines which enable automatic generation of SDKs. They have now been around for some years but are still a new concept in the API space. The objective is to use your API Specification as a single source of truth to derive fully working functional SDKs out of them in minutes.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-558 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_FLECCuyGQLDzoeCoxHdYCA.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="faa4" class="">The APIMatic CodeGen Engine takes in an API Specification in any format (Swagger/OpenAPI, RAML, API Blueprint etc.), and spews out fully functional SDKs, complete with:</p>
<ul class="">
<li>Client Libraries</li>
<li>Dynamic Code Samples</li>
<li>Documentation</li>
<li>Getting Started Guides</li>
</ul>
<p id="b2d9">And all of that in a variety of programming languages!</p>
<p id="7fb8">Unlike every piece of revolutionary technology in history, CodeGen Engines have amassed a number of critics and sceptics, who argue how something so complex can be achieved in minutes like that. Good thing for us, it is science, not magic. And every concept of science has an explanation to it.</p>
<p id="f6bc">Here’s what we do to generate SDKs automatically for you:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-559 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_yD9ALr6xQvOo3aD0Rg6GXg-1-1024x630.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:list -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<ol class="">
<li>Take API Description in any popular format</li>
<li>Convert it to our Standard Description Language (SDL) or the APIMatic format</li>
<li>Run a series of validations</li>
<li>Loop different parts of the API description and generate code representations</li>
<li>Convert important entities from an API Description to SDK.</li>
<li>Generate an HTTP abstraction layer to wrap the HTTP client</li>
<li>Generate one or more helper class files to abstract out a lot of the common code from the SDK</li>
<li>Provide a client library interface to wrap the SDK and make it easier to use.</li>
<li>Generate language or platform-dependent files, such as gemspec, Gemfile and Rakefile are generated for Ruby SDKs</li>
<li>Generate Readme files, Getting Started Guides, Code Samples and Documentation</li>
<li>Package everything in zip files ready to be deployed on GitHub or designated repos</li>
</ol>
<p id="0517" class="">Now all of that may sound like a really complicated process, but we believe API Providers should not be worrying about this. APIMatic is here to do the hard work, we are here to produce fully functioning quality SDKs, and to achieve all of this from signup to your first SDK Generation,&nbsp;<strong>take up less than a minute</strong>. Use APIMatic’s CodeGen API to build the engine into your CI/CD pipeline and never worry about updating SDKs ever again!</p>
<p id="59af" class="">Another question that bugs many providers is what if they want their SDKs to follow certain conventions. Luckily they do not have to worry, APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine does not produce generic, one fit all SDKs. With our CodeGen settings, we allow providers to chose what works or does not work for them such as</p>
<ol class="">
<li>Automatic appending of JSON accept and content-type headers</li>
<li>Allowing skipping of SSL Certificate validation</li>
<li>Setting timeouts for endpoint calls</li>
<li>Perform linting</li>
</ol>
<p id="4c14" class="">Furthermore, we can make more customisations to the engine and mould it to the specific requirement of providers as a premium offering.</p>
<p id="94bd">APIMatic’s CodeGen Service is more than just a Code Generator, it’s an entire platform. Where you can</p>
<ol class="">
<li>Maintain, edit and manage different version of API specifications</li>
<li>Publish generated SDKs on Github or package repositories</li>
<li>Host SDKs on completely customisable Developer Portals, complimented with Reference Docs Live and Dynamic Code Samples</li>
</ol>
<p id="5a60" class="">Not sure how you can build in the API Code Engine to your pipeline? Reach out to us today to book a Demo!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:list -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/11/how-to-create-sdks-for-your-api-in-less-than-a-minute/">How to Create SDKs for your API in less than a Minute ⏰</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Redesigning APIs at APIMatic — A Case Study</title>
		<link>/blog/2018/10/redesigning-apis-at-apimatic-a-case-study/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[REST APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rest API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sdks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=584</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ever since the start of the year, the top priority for us at APIMatic was to improve the packaging of our products and features. We launched the Developer Experience Portal, added package publishing capabilities to our eco-system, added curl commands to our console, revamped our Developer Portal to optimize loading speeds and so on. With [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/10/redesigning-apis-at-apimatic-a-case-study/">Redesigning APIs at APIMatic — A Case Study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="584" class="elementor elementor-584">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-10a05dcd elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="10a05dcd" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-57309f88" data-id="57309f88" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-58c4ed1 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="58c4ed1" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-585 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_a6X94xx-nFIRIcmtgdoBMQ.gif" alt="Redesigning APIs at APIMatic — A Case Study " width="800" height="350"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="5a6f" class="">Ever since the start of the year, the top priority for us at APIMatic was to improve the packaging of our products and features. We launched the Developer Experience Portal, added package publishing capabilities to our eco-system, added curl commands to our console, revamped our Developer Portal to optimize loading speeds and so on.</p>
<p id="d891" class="">With our new products and offerings, we needed new APIs to allow our users to more points of access. This gave us a perfect opportunity to revamp our existing APIs as well, which were developed for internal use only and were never designed to have the perfect structure, naming or performance. However when duty called</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-586 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_72RiNGLJyCaMiS0hSTEMXA.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class="">we rose up to the occasion and revamped our entire infrastructure to make the perfect little REST APIs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-587 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_fWpRAux4xe7_4XN6lUk7NA.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="cc21">Goals</h2>
<p id="0c14" class="">Developer Experience is the most important metric to measure the quality of an API. For us at APIMatic it is the rule of law, it’s the word of god, it’s everything. We have always preached the idea of well-designed APIs that are super easy to use and make the life of developers easy. An API is not a random chunk of code, it’s an interface, and like any interface, you need to make sure that the experience you’re providing is as smooth and seamless as possible because that is what developers are looking for.</p>
<p id="284f" class="">With developer experience as the goal post, the direction we took for implementing our new APIs was very clear. Let’s briefly look at the fundamental concepts that were under consideration throughout the development cycle:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>Stable&nbsp;</strong>and even more importantly&nbsp;<strong>Scalable</strong>&nbsp;APIs.</li>
<li>Making our APIs&nbsp;<strong>truly RESTFUL&nbsp;</strong>by adhering to the&nbsp;<strong>constraints</strong>&nbsp;of&nbsp;<em>REST</em>&nbsp;as much as possible.</li>
<li>Ensure&nbsp;<strong>backward compatibility</strong>&nbsp;for our public APIs.</li>
<li>Focusing on&nbsp;<strong>simplicity</strong>,<strong>&nbsp;extensibility</strong>,<strong>&nbsp;reliability,&nbsp;</strong>and<strong>&nbsp;performance</strong>.</li>
<li>Sticking to popular&nbsp;<strong>standards&nbsp;</strong>to create&nbsp;<strong>uniformity</strong>&nbsp;in the code.</li>
<li>Prioritize&nbsp;<strong>naming</strong>&nbsp;and making it&nbsp;<strong>consistent</strong>&nbsp;across the application.</li>
<li>Improving the&nbsp;<strong>readability</strong>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<strong>structuring</strong>&nbsp;of the code to optimize it for incremental upgrades in the future.</li>
<li>Creating the APIs to be easily&nbsp;<strong>testable&nbsp;</strong>and then writing&nbsp;<strong>Unit Tests&nbsp;</strong>for them.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="d943">The Richardson Maturity Model</h2>
<p id="a20e" class="">The Richardson Maturity Model is a great way to grade your API according to the constraints of REST. The better your API adheres to these constraints, the higher its score is. The Richardson Maturity Model knows 4 levels (0–3), where level 3 designates a truly RESTful API.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large">
<figure id="attachment_588" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-588" style="width: 700px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-588" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/0_4wRhEvmnQLwjpF2q.png" alt="Courtesy: nordicapis.com" width="700" height="429"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-588" class="wp-caption-text">Courtesy: nordicapis.com</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="4383" class="">Our previous APIs were&nbsp;<strong>Level 0</strong>;&nbsp;<em>RESTful</em>&nbsp;only in name as they were only using&nbsp;<em>HTTP</em>&nbsp;to send requests and receive responses without utilizing the full potential of&nbsp;<em>HTTP</em>. The APIs were used only to invoke remote mechanisms based on remote procedure call. There was some&nbsp;<strong>leveling up&nbsp;</strong>required, and that’s what we did.</p>
<blockquote class="">
<p id="a233" class=""><em>You can read all about the best practices to design your API from scratch here:</em><a href="https://apimatic.io/blog/2018/03/building-rest-apis-the-right-way" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> Best Practices to Increase API Adoption</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="035d" class="">Resources</h2>
<p id="e357" class="">A resource is one of the most essential part of&nbsp;<em>REST</em>. Resource is an object or representation of something, which has some data associated with it and there can be a set of methods to operate on it. According to&nbsp;<em>REST&nbsp;</em>the URI should only contain resources(nouns) not actions or verbs.<em>&nbsp;The paths should contain the plural form of resources and the HTTP method should define the kind of action to be performed on the resource</em>. We identified our resources to be:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><strong>Transformation:</strong>&nbsp;A single resource describing all the relevant information of the&nbsp;<em>Transformation</em>&nbsp;of an API description from one format to another. The transformation is tied to the&nbsp;<em>User</em>.</li>
<li><strong>API Entity Code Generation:&nbsp;</strong>A single resource describing all relevant information of a code generation performed from an API description already stored with us. The&nbsp;<em>API Entity Code Generation</em>&nbsp;is tied to the&nbsp;<em>API Entity</em>&nbsp;for which the SDK is generated.</li>
<li><strong>User Code Generation:</strong>&nbsp;A single resource describing all relevant information of a code generation performed from an API description provided by the user as file or URL. The&nbsp;<em>User Code Generation&nbsp;</em>is tied to the&nbsp;<em>User</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p id="e0cf" class="">The 3 new APIs are based on these 3 resources, with each resource having its specific API and each API having many endpoints. These corresponding database models of these resources were also added to the old CodeGen and Transformer APIs as well, to ensure&nbsp;<em>backward compatibility</em>&nbsp;for our public APIs. Increased our score from&nbsp;<strong>Level 0&nbsp;</strong>to&nbsp;<strong>Level 1</strong>. Are we happy with this? Yes; can we go higher? 100%.</p>
<h2 id="02be">HTTP Methods and Status Codes</h2>
<p id="e881" class="">HTTP has defined few sets of methods which indicate the type of action to be performed on the resources. The URL is a sentence, where resources are nouns and HTTP methods are verbs. Aspiring to achieve true RESTful-ness for our APIs we used HTTP methods instead of using a single method for all requests, for instance,&nbsp;<em>GET&nbsp;</em>when requesting resource and&nbsp;<em>DELETE&nbsp;</em>when deleting resources and so on.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class=""><code class="language-json">// Request:
GET /transformation/1

// Response:
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
{
   exportFormat: &quot;APIMATIC&quot;
}</code></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="dac4" class="">Similarly, HTTP has defined a bunch of standardized codes which let the client know the feedback, whether the request failed, passed or the request was wrong. For the sake of correct&nbsp;<strong>Developer Experience,&nbsp;</strong>our API should always return the right HTTP Status Code. e.g. 200 OK for successful retrieval of resource and 404 Not Found if the requested resource doesn’t exist.</p>
<h2 id="7ec4" class="">Content-Type based routing</h2>
<p id="a935" class="">While writing the new APIs we came across a few cases where we needed a different action performed for the same resource and the same HTTP verb e.g. creating (<em>POST</em>) a&nbsp;<em>Transformation&nbsp;</em>with a File and creating (<em>POST</em>) a&nbsp;<em>Transformation&nbsp;</em>with a URL. In such a case where we wanted even finer-grain control over the routing mechanics, we ended up routing them to different actions based on the content-type header. We implemented a custom version of the&nbsp;<em>Route</em>&nbsp;attribute which adds a Content-Type parameter that gets evaluated when a request is being routed. And now we had a single path (e.g. POST: “api/transformations”) that accepts both binary and JSON data and routes them to a different action.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-589 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/0_Jmjfvx3qVgg-gwqr.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="1316" class="">Repository Design Pattern</h2>
<p id="4fbd" class="">The new APIs were implemented on the&nbsp;<em>Single Responsibility Rule&nbsp;</em>and the&nbsp;<em>Repository Design Pattern</em>. It leverages a layer that isolates the APIs from the details of database access code. In large systems such as ours adding this layer helps minimize duplicate query logic. The repository (or as it’s called in our codebase; a manager) acts as an in-memory object collection. Objects are added and removed from the repository and the code encapsulated by the repository carries out the appropriate operations behind the scenes. The API is completely unconcerned about the underlying mechanism of getting the data or even the kind of database being used; it could be a&nbsp;<em>MongoDB</em>&nbsp;or&nbsp;<em>SQL</em>&nbsp;database being accessed inside the repository using whatever&nbsp;<em>ORM&nbsp;</em>or<em>&nbsp;Querying mechanism</em>, the controller would just call the relevant method of the repository to get the data it requires.</p>
<h2 id="c7a1" class="">Documentation</h2>
<p id="c3be" class="">The new APIs were written to be self-documenting, we tried to make things as self-explanatory as possible. Here’s a work in progress version of a documentation generated using APIMatic tools:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.apimatic.io/apidocs/apimatic/v/1_0#/java/getting-started">Preview Docs</a></p>
<p id="0401" class="">The taxonomy and naming convention we advised can easily be picked by documentation rendering tools to name our endpoints in a way that even a layman can understand.</p>
<h2 id="b3df" class="">Unit Tests</h2>
<p id="e1e6" class="">Writing unit tests for code results in fewer bugs in production and fewer bugs in production means more time for making cool new features. It’s usually good practice to have automated unit tests while writing code. Doing so helps find bugs early in the development cycle and saves time in the long run. These tests can be run multiple times to verify the behavior of a particular unit of code for different sets of input.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-590 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/0_7_VFkkAKg2k-8R21.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8989">We used NUnit to write&nbsp;<em>unit tests&nbsp;</em>for the data access layer and plan on expanding test coverage to the rest of the codebase, it’s a good start but we’ve got a long way to go when it comes to automated unit testing.</p>
<h2 id="e891" class="">Hypermedia</h2>
<p id="2956" class="">Level 3, the highest level, uses HATEOAS to deal with discovering the possibilities of your API towards the clients. This is our end goal for the APIs to completely satisfy the REST constraints. We have already started working towards this.</p>
<p id="2250" class="">We would soon be launching our new APIs publicly, once they are completely tried and tested. Our product team is working day and night to package them nicely and make them available to our users in a really convenient way. We intend to make all of our services and products super flexible and enable everyone to access and retrieve what they want in form of optimised payloads.</p>
<p id="ce36" class="">Also a big round of applause for&nbsp; Ammar Naqvi, Software Engineer @&nbsp;&nbsp;APIMATIC&nbsp;, who played a huge role in reviving our APIs and with whose collaboration this blog was written. Follow him on Twitter @ <a href="https://twitter.com/ammarabbasnaqvi">ammarabbasnaqvi</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/10/redesigning-apis-at-apimatic-a-case-study/">Redesigning APIs at APIMatic — A Case Study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Exactly is Developer Experience?</title>
		<link>/blog/2018/09/what-exactly-is-developer-experience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 12:34:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Company]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Event]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Meetup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTD San Francisco]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=1103</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Write the Docs is a global community of people who care about documentation. They boast a Slack network of thousands of members and are physically present on 3 continents where they conduct regular meet-ups. Our team ran into some members of the San Francisco Chapter earlier in the summer, and an arrangement was made for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/09/what-exactly-is-developer-experience/">What Exactly is Developer Experience?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1103" class="elementor elementor-1103">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-43cc30fb elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="43cc30fb" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-6525236e" data-id="6525236e" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-759f3cca elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="759f3cca" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<figure class="graf graf--figure">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1196 size-full bg-img bg-img-1" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Thedeveloperexperienceforapis-01-1.png" alt="" width="800" height="350"></p>
<p class="graf graf--p"><a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://www.writethedocs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://www.writethedocs.org/">Write the Docs</a> is a global community of people who care about documentation. They boast a <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/slack/">Slack network</a> of thousands of members and are physically present on 3 continents where they conduct regular meet-ups.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">Our team ran into some members of the <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://www.meetup.com/Write-the-Docs-SF/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://www.meetup.com/Write-the-Docs-SF/">San Francisco Chapter</a> earlier in the summer, and an arrangement was made for Nauman, our Product Manager to speak at their latest meet-up. With this talk, we aimed to introduce<strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"> the latest practices in API Documentation and explain what Developer Experience is for APIs.</strong></p>

<blockquote class="graf graf--pullquote graf--startsWithDoubleQuote">“….APIs are not only for savvy developers or tech companies”</blockquote>
<p class="graf graf--p">The talk started off with how APIs are slowly taking over the world, and how it has become important for every business to have an API. The cyberspace is changing rapidly, and just like it was important for businesses to have a website a few years back, it’s important for them to have an API today to exist and stay relevant.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">APIs are not as easy to interact with and require prior documentation and know-how for third-party interactors to deal with, in the case of APIs, the third-party interactors being developers, which brings us to the concept of Developer Experience.</p>

<h2 class="graf graf--h4">What Exactly is Developer Experience?</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Developer Experience (DX) is the equivalent of User Experience (UX) when it comes to a developer.</strong></p>
<p class="graf graf--p">It is a concept often referenced in the API world and rightly so. APIs are complex structures and unless you properly explain what your API does, nobody is ever going to use it. In fact, the value of your API and the usage is something that directly depends on your Developer Experience.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">Developers are the lifeblood of an API economy and until it is made easy for them to access and play around with your API, it may never really see success.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">A great Developer Experience is when even novice developers come to your API and require minimum onboarding time, no handholding, and achieve maximum satisfaction. Here, the <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">3:30:3 Rule is applied </strong>which a developer coming in of any experience should take:</p>

<ul class="postList">
 	<li class="graf graf--li"><strong class="markup--strong markup--li-strong">3 seconds to understand what your API does</strong></li>
 	<li class="graf graf--li"><strong class="markup--strong markup--li-strong">30 seconds to understand the required functionality</strong></li>
 	<li class="graf graf--li"><strong class="markup--strong markup--li-strong">3 minutes to be up and running</strong></li>
</ul>
<p class="graf graf--p">This should be the end goal of your entire Developer Experience campaign. These are the metrics you should measure your efforts against at end of the day. Companies like Stripe and Twilio have come close to this and have found massive success with their APIs.</p>

<h2 class="graf graf--h4">What Constitutes a Great Developer Experience?</h2>
<p class="graf graf--p">Great Developer Experience can be achieved with the help of the following components:</p>

<ul class="">
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Getting Started Guides</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Client Libraries</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">API Console</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Code Samples</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">FAQs</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Change Logs</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Dashboard(Monitoring and Reporting)</li>
 	<li class="graf graf--blockquote">Authentication</li>
</ul>
<p class="graf graf--p">It is essential to take the correct steps and measures throughout your API Lifecycle to ensure you end up providing a great experience. You can read in detail about the best practices you can <a href="https://apimatic.io/blog/2018/03/building-rest-apis-the-right-way/">follow throughout your API lifecycle</a>.</p>

<div class="graf graf--mixtapeEmbed">
<p class="mod-reset">Your primary focus should be on getting your specification right and how that will drive your entire API Program. No matter what specification you are comfortable with, OpenAPI, RAML, or API Blueprint, you can convert back and forth as many times as you like with the API Transformer and can even integrate the Transformer API in your CI/CD cycle to convert specs on the go.</p>

</div>
<p class="graf graf--p">Coming to the consumption part, Twilio, Stripe, Algolia, and other API companies achieved their success by making their APIs super easy to consume. However, it is important to note that, for all of these companies, APIs are the bread and butter and they can afford to spend their entire resources towards a better Developer Experience. But traditional companies like banks, airlines, and telcos that are recently jumping into the API space or are opening up their API to wider audiences, may necessarily not have the expertise or the knowledge to pull of something similar.</p>
<p class="graf graf--p">But that does not have to be the case anymore and that’s where APIMatic comes in. With us, you can produce everything that makes it easy for developers to consume APIs. You can provide a Developer Experience only parallel to the best in the industry. And all of that with the least of effort (in minutes) and least of resources. All you need to do is manage and maintain a specification, and let us do the rest.</p>

<blockquote class="graf graf--blockquote graf--hasDropCapModel">Don&#8217;t miss reading APIMatic&#8217;s philosophy behind automating the developer experience:<a class="markup--anchor markup--mixtapeEmbed-anchor" title="https://blog.devapi.dream.press/introducing-portals-that-speak-your-devs-language-bac82a8c573f" href="https://apimatic.io/blog/2018/01//developer-experience-beyond-api-docs" data-href="https://blog.devapi.dream.press/introducing-portals-that-speak-your-devs-language-bac82a8c573f">Introducing Portals That Speak Your Devs Language</a></blockquote>
<p class="graf graf--p">We’d like to throw a special thanks to <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/moniquesemp" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/moniquesemp">Monique</a>, for doing such a superb job organizing the event and <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/richmattiello/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/richmattiello/">Richard</a> for recording all the videos.&nbsp;</p>
</figure>						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2018/09/what-exactly-is-developer-experience/">What Exactly is Developer Experience?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
