
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Communication APIs Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/communication-apis/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 14:47:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Communication APIs Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodeGen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Api documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[customer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&#160; The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1697 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/CustomrPoV3-02-1024x619.png" alt="SDKs and API documentation by APIMatic" width="744" height="450"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&nbsp; </span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum developer experience with the least onboarding problems.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automated SDK and API documentation generations are a sure way to boost API adoption while lifting the strain of repetitive tasks off developers. API provider companies from various industries like communication, fintech, and travel enjoy better team productivity and faster time to market as the time-consuming monotony of maintaining SDKs and API documentation is handled by APIMatic.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication APIs: Increased Developer Productivity for MessageMedia</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://messagemedia.com/us/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform that offers communication services between its customers’ workforce.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sending over a billion messages per year and servicing thousands of global customers required a streamlined developer experience to integrate their various messaging APIs, and manually updating SDKs on each update was not optimal.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the problems we had with our SDKs was if a new feature was added to the API, we would have to manually make the code changes to the SDKs itself. Given we have 6 SDKs for each of our APIs, it was a long and inefficient process to update.” — Ibrahim Tareq, Developer Evangelist</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine, MessageMedia was able to auto-generate SDKs in all of the required languages, and the SDKs could reflect changes in the API on the go, which had been a pain point for the team.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It has helped reduce the barrier of entry… you can hand out SDKs to your customers and make it easier and simpler for them to code their way to the first ‘hello world’.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/messagemedia-speaking-the-language-of-developers-with-apimatic-codegen-5a3a7ad17d8e"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with Autogenerated SDKs</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fintech APIs: Revenue Generator for Fortune 500 Fintech</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">This leading financial services giant provides access to the world’s largest independent payment network to almost any country in the world through API integrations.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hence, this company was quick to realize that in order to obtain partnerships and integrations with third parties, they needed to reach out to a larger developer community and ensure that their APIs were adopted faster. They began offering .NET and Java SDKs for their APIs, which were built in-house, but maintaining them took the time that could instead be spent on expanding their API landscape with the growing demand.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Writing SDKs for just two languages was a pretty time consuming and expensive </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">process, every time we had a release that affected those services, it would increase </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">our sprints and dev timelines” &#8211; Head of Innovation</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine streamlined their process in the form of automatically generated SDKs and API documentation for six languages instead of two, directly from their API definition files. This resulted in cost savings of hundreds of thousands of dollars compared to building SDKs and docs in-house while reducing their time to market the APIs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Fast go-to-market time for documentation, and then the ability to generate SDKs in </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">multiple languages; those were the things that attracted us to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/fintech/a-fortune-500-fintech-company/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How APIMatic Became a Revenue Generator for a Fortune 500 Fintech</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Operation Management APIs: From 1 Week to 18 Seconds with Dude Solutions</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.dudesolutions.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a leading software-as-a-service (SaaS) provider of operations management solutions for education, government, healthcare, and many industries.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">They have two front-facing REST APIs that drive their platform and are supported by a set of micro-services that specialize in different areas.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions realized early on that with SDKs, they would have sharable software that could be used across the entire platform. It would reduce the amount of code in each API stack and understand the security protocols. However, they started by creating the SDKs from scratch and soon enough found out that it was just as long a process as API development.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We learned that it takes almost as long to do the API implementation as it did the SDK development. In fact, it took one week to develop the SDK for a single language.” &#8211; Brian Hyder, Engineering Manager</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When they began designing their next micro-service, Dude Solutions started looking for alternate ways for SDK development and came across APIMatic. The autogeneration of SDKs in multiple languages helped drastically cut down SDK development and maintenance costs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Development time for SDKs for each language went from 1 week to 18 seconds thanks to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1695 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/dude-solutions.png" alt="" width="603" height="393"></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While they had initially planned to provide SDKs in 3 languages, the significant time and cost reduction enabled them to provide SDKs for 7 languages with APIMatic’s autogenerated SDKs.</span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/automate-all-the-things-how-dude-solutions-saved-20-000-in-development-costs-using-apimatic-f9c05118f041"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Dude Solutions Cut Down Time to Release from 1 Week to 18 Seconds</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel APIs: Client Onboarding Time Reduced by 20% for Didgigo</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.didgigo.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a digital media platform that assists travel agents in organizing and maintaining data, as well as creating detailed itinerary proposals that save time and boost sales opportunities for clients.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo offers APIs that allow travel experts to create travel documents for their clients automatically and publish both digital and print versions at the same time. However, for a firm that excels at offering automated tailor-made solutions to its clients, it became critical to find a solution that could shorten the API onboarding time for customers, without the engineering team having to context switch on each release.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our process was extremely manual and required a lot of back and forth” &#8211; Keanu Ashwell, Development Operations Engineer</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s autogenerated documentation in multiple languages, Didgigo is able to shift its focus on building robust APIs, without having to devote time and resources to maintain the documentation. The customer onboarding process has become more streamlined, with tickets raised during onboarding being <strong>reduced by 11-20%</strong>, and customer onboarding meetings going down by more than 7 meetings per quarter.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our experience with APIMatic and its provisions has been exceptional. We haven&#8217;t had </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">much time to maintain everything as we&#8217;re still strapped for resources due to COVID-19, </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">but we&#8217;ve still been able to rely on APIMatic to give our API users an understanding of </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">what functionality we expose via our APIs. The ability to test [the APIs] is also a feature I </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">love and something that drew me to the service when we migrated from our in-house Swagger solution.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/api-portal/didgigo/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Didgigo Reduces Client Onboarding Time with Autogenerated Documentation</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthcare/Senior Living APIs: Time to Release Down by 30% for Caremerge</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://caremerge.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">is an </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">all-in-one platform that empowers families, residents, and staff of senior citizens by </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">providing tools for modern elder care including family engagement, community engagement, chronic care management, and more.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge also uses various pre-existing services to make them more accessible for these senior citizens, for example with voice commands. However, managing all these services in a single platform requires multiple internal microservices and a public API.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Caremerge API powers communication between the services they offer and allows them to build integrations with various third-party vendors and services. Building those integrations requires the documentation for the API to be always updated, so developers spend less time figuring out how to integrate.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using APIMatic’s autogenerated API documentation with the API playground allows developers to test inputs and outputs within the docs, resulting in quicker integration of the API, and helps Caremerge cut down on time spent on maintenance.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">“APIMatic helps us save 20–30% of the time it took us to manage documentation for our API” &#8211; </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder, and CTO</span></em></span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api-734da95b2d9b"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge</span></a></p>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quicker synchronization of documentation and SDKs with APIs leads to shorter sprints and faster time to market. With a mission to make API consumption as simple as possible, APIMatic considers it a victory when our</span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> customers’ APIs are consumed</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more readily with our autogenerated SDKs and documentation.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sms Marketing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=436</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Every day, 23 billion SMS messages are sent worldwide, which is equivalent to 16 million messages per minute, exchanged between 7 billion mobile subscribers across the world — (CTIA) The SMS industry is huge, and the bulk SMS industry huger. Wide adoption and availability of the technology has made it the number one choice of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/">State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="436" class="elementor elementor-436">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-21c95151 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="21c95151" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-33c470a0" data-id="33c470a0" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-188ddceb elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="188ddceb" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
			<style>/*! elementor - v3.6.4 - 13-04-2022 */
.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-stacked .elementor-drop-cap{background-color:#818a91;color:#fff}.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-framed .elementor-drop-cap{color:#818a91;border:3px solid;background-color:transparent}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap{margin-top:8px}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap-letter{width:1em;height:1em}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap{float:left;text-align:center;line-height:1;font-size:50px}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap-letter{display:inline-block}</style>				<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-437 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_9S0vdIiVL9SvUXrR4vLH8w-1024x512.jpg" alt="State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020" width="1024" height="512"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<blockquote class="">
<p id="16fa" class="">Every day, 23 billion SMS messages are sent worldwide, which is equivalent to 16 million messages per minute, exchanged between 7 billion mobile subscribers across the world — (CTIA)</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="4cab" class="">The SMS industry is huge, and the bulk SMS industry huger. Wide adoption and availability of the technology has made it the number one choice of communication for businesses, who can now reach out to millions of people across the globe with the minimum of effort. Businesses today are making use of SMS messages to send alerts of all kinds, and for a very good reason.</p>
<blockquote class="">
<p id="d3ad" class="">SMS messages are more likely to be opened than Emails, a typical message is read within 3 minutes with a CTR of 19% versus 2% for email.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="b46e" class="">A lot of that is being done over (A2P), Application-to-Person, where an application is programmed to trigger messages at particular intervals or events. There are a number of tools available to run these campaigns, but none as customizable and powerful as SMS APIs which give direct control to businesses to build messaging facilities straight into their systems.</p>
<p id="9dc1" class="">As of now, they are more than&nbsp;<strong>750 Messaging APIs</strong>&nbsp;currently listed on Programmable Web, with more and more services being listed daily. Using SMS APIs, companies can send complex 2-Way SMS messages, marketing messages, verification messages, notifications, alerts and warnings of all kinds.</p>
<p id="0f97" class="">To see what makes some of these APIs so popular, we shortlisted a pool of them, analyzed what they had to offer, and what really makes them so popular in this age and time. The APIs that we analyzed include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li>Twilio</li>
<li>Nexmo</li>
<li>Plivo</li>
<li>Telstra</li>
<li>AT&amp;T</li>
<li>Bandwidth</li>
<li>ClickSend</li>
<li>MessageMedia</li>
</ul>
<p id="db07" class="">For the analysis, we started off by looking at the features these APIs have to offer, followed by the compliances they meet, and then their Developer Experience programs. By the end of the blog, you would know what does it take to stand out in the industry and compete with the giants we know today.</p>
<h2 id="9de9"><strong>Essential Features — SMS APIs 2019</strong></h2>
<p id="53af" class="">Analyzing these APIs in terms of the functionality they provide, we recognized that there are a set of features that are common to most of them. These features are the bare essentials if you want to make it in the SMS APIs space. They include:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-438 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_OVg9CFI3FVS4MJiJUYoohA.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8d87" class="">Many of the APIs included in this study go beyond that and have added more value, building on these features. For instance Twilio allows sending of MMS messages, allowing senders to attached pictures or other forms of media. Furthermore, they have a mechanism to recognize the optimum routes to send out messages, ensuring guaranteed delivery in record time. Nexmo features a persistent sending ID, using the same number to send messages to one person. Plivo features number pooling, to distribute campaign loads and ensure quicker delivery.</p>
<h2 id="3099"><strong>Compliance Requirements — SMS APIs 2019</strong></h2>
<p id="8c9e" class="">For the telecommunication industry, one of the biggest challenges faced is being compliant with local and international regulations. Often continents, countries, states and even specific carrier networks, have a set of rules they abide with, and unless an SMS API caters to these rules, messages may never be delivered as intended and campaigns may go in vain.</p>
<p id="6064" class="">For most top SMS APIs, all these regulations are met and precautions are implemented, some important regulations and guides include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><a href="https://www.fdic.gov/regulations/compliance/manual/8/viii-5.1.pdf">The TCPA (<em>Telephone Consumer Protection Act)</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://api.ctia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/190719-CTIA-Messaging-Principles-and-Best-Practices-FINAL.pdf">CTIA Messaging Principles and Best Practices</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.wixstatic.com/ugd/9456a5_72a6056a11f5401c95d29181e850625b.pdf">CTIA Short Code Monitoring Handbook</a></li>
</ul>
<p id="9a39">Some common practices to be globally compliant by most regulations include:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-439 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_X_kTbzcew9iAPJo5qvqq4A.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="57e4" class=""><strong>What Really Makes Great SMS APIs?</strong></h2>
<p id="6b08" class="">So by now, if you are trying to rate one SMS API over the other, you probably would run into too many of them offering the same set of features, with different implementations, all offering them one way or the other, leaving you guessing that which of them is really worth it?</p>
<p id="ecc8" class="">And for that, we take you to the question,&nbsp;<strong>what makes a great API?</strong></p>
<p id="5e94" class="">And the unanimous answer to that is great&nbsp;<strong>Developer Experience.</strong>&nbsp;All the best APIs are easy to consume and require shorter development time to integrate. At the end of the day, each API is supposed to facilitate interoperability, and the easier is it to integrate, the better the API.</p>
<p id="a149" class="">To see how these SMS APIs stood out, we analyzed their publicly available Docs and Developer Portals and came up with the matrix below, which summarizes our findings.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-440 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_q_AESiXsFaY4P0uKPSMWHg-1024x640.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="4f3d">Where each of these API providers fills in quite a number of checks on the Developer Experience Checklist, each of them stood out in some respective fields.</p>
<p id="481b" class="">Twilio, Nexmo and ClickSend do a wonderful job with their Landing Pages, which do a great job onboarding users with what facilities they offer, what features does the API come with and how can they help them solve problems with tons of uses cases, tutorials, and Sample Apps. Almost all API Providers have made use of visuals and diagrams to explain the inner workings of an API.</p>
<p id="ef3a" class="">Bandwidth offers a Sandbox environment where users could play around with the API, similarly, MessageMedia offers an API console where Code Samples can be tried around with. Telstra has a run in postman button, where you can try out sample calls, the click of a button takes you to the postman tool.</p>
<p id="ec68">Both Twilio and Nexmo offer a dedicated API Service Status page, with intuitive layout structures that help consumers get to their desired bit of information faster.</p>
<p id="d7b9" class="">SDKs and Code Samples are also something that all these popular APIs have to offer, popular languages being: Ruby, PHP, Python, JavaScript, C# and Node.</p>
<h2 id="1752" class=""><strong>Great Developer Experience: A Challenge</strong></h2>
<p id="d64f" class="">If you are out at this making an SMS API, it’s essential that you miss out on none of these offerings, or you will stand no chance against the competition. Often smaller teams come up with brilliant technology but lack the numbers to focus on anything else except the core offering. It is just as essential to focus on material revolving around the API, the marketing pages, documentation, client libraries and much more, all of which take a lot of time, effort and energy, but without none of which your API will see success or adoption.</p>
<p id="54e5" class="">While companies like Twilio, Nexmo, and AT&amp;T can afford to heavily invest in programs like that, for startups and smaller companies it becomes impossible to spare time or money. With the cost and time it takes to produce all of this material, it’s not scalable with evolution, often Docs and SDKs lag far behind when APIs are multiple versions ahead, and this is the reason.</p>
<p id="4f0d" class="">So the challenge here is how do you take your brilliant API out to developers when you don’t have the means to keep it developer-friendly for long?</p>
<p id="050f" class="">And the answer lies in automation, while a human developer may take several days to produce and maintain all of these components, Code-Gen Engines can take an API Spec as input to automatically generate all of these components and all of it within a few minutes. Want to make updates to your API? Don’t worry, build the engine into your CI/CD pipeline and generate new components with every new push, release or update.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-441 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/0_UFKse1UtCEOQwgJr.gif" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="691f" class="">All you now have to do is, add more and more features to your API, make it compliant to the point you can rollover your competition, while a Code-Gen Engine takes care of the material you need to put it out in front of Developers.</p>
<p id="7373" class="">Need to talk more about automating Developer Experience?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.apimatic.io/contact">Speak to us</a>&nbsp;today and we’ll help you get started.</p>
<p class="">Thanks to&nbsp;Adam DuVander.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/12/state-of-developer-experience-sms-apis-2020/">State of Developer Experience: SMS APIs 2020</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
