
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>FinTech APIs Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/fintech-apis/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>APIMatic is an API documentation tool that provides a complete set of DX components such as autogenerated SDKs, API portal, API docs, live code samples, and more.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 14:47:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-cropped-apimaticio-favicon-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>FinTech APIs Archives - APIMatic</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</title>
		<link>/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nida I Zamir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APIMATIC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodeGen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Communication APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Api documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[auto-generated SDKs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Case Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[customer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://apimatic.io/blog/?p=1693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&#160; The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p class=""><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1697 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/CustomrPoV3-02-1024x619.png" alt="SDKs and API documentation by APIMatic" width="744" height="450"></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The API community seems to have settled upon one ground rule: give the developers what they want, and then some more. Yay for the external developers (the API users), nay for the internal developers (the API developers).&nbsp; </span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The exponential growth in APIs and the consequent competition between the API providers warrant the need for maximum developer experience with the least onboarding problems.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automated SDK and API documentation generations are a sure way to boost API adoption while lifting the strain of repetitive tasks off developers. API provider companies from various industries like communication, fintech, and travel enjoy better team productivity and faster time to market as the time-consuming monotony of maintaining SDKs and API documentation is handled by APIMatic.</span></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication APIs: Increased Developer Productivity for MessageMedia</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://messagemedia.com/us/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is Australia’s leading global business messaging platform that offers communication services between its customers’ workforce.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sending over a billion messages per year and servicing thousands of global customers required a streamlined developer experience to integrate their various messaging APIs, and manually updating SDKs on each update was not optimal.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the problems we had with our SDKs was if a new feature was added to the API, we would have to manually make the code changes to the SDKs itself. Given we have 6 SDKs for each of our APIs, it was a long and inefficient process to update.” — Ibrahim Tareq, Developer Evangelist</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine, MessageMedia was able to auto-generate SDKs in all of the required languages, and the SDKs could reflect changes in the API on the go, which had been a pain point for the team.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It has helped reduce the barrier of entry… you can hand out SDKs to your customers and make it easier and simpler for them to code their way to the first ‘hello world’.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/messagemedia-speaking-the-language-of-developers-with-apimatic-codegen-5a3a7ad17d8e"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MessageMedia Increases Developer Productivity with Autogenerated SDKs</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fintech APIs: Revenue Generator for Fortune 500 Fintech</span></h2>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">This leading financial services giant provides access to the world’s largest independent payment network to almost any country in the world through API integrations.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hence, this company was quick to realize that in order to obtain partnerships and integrations with third parties, they needed to reach out to a larger developer community and ensure that their APIs were adopted faster. They began offering .NET and Java SDKs for their APIs, which were built in-house, but maintaining them took the time that could instead be spent on expanding their API landscape with the growing demand.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Writing SDKs for just two languages was a pretty time consuming and expensive </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">process, every time we had a release that affected those services, it would increase </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">our sprints and dev timelines” &#8211; Head of Innovation</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">APIMatic’s CodeGen Engine streamlined their process in the form of automatically generated SDKs and API documentation for six languages instead of two, directly from their API definition files. This resulted in cost savings of hundreds of thousands of dollars compared to building SDKs and docs in-house while reducing their time to market the APIs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Fast go-to-market time for documentation, and then the ability to generate SDKs in </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">multiple languages; those were the things that attracted us to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/fintech/a-fortune-500-fintech-company/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How APIMatic Became a Revenue Generator for a Fortune 500 Fintech</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Operation Management APIs: From 1 Week to 18 Seconds with Dude Solutions</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.dudesolutions.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a leading software-as-a-service (SaaS) provider of operations management solutions for education, government, healthcare, and many industries.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">They have two front-facing REST APIs that drive their platform and are supported by a set of micro-services that specialize in different areas.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dude Solutions realized early on that with SDKs, they would have sharable software that could be used across the entire platform. It would reduce the amount of code in each API stack and understand the security protocols. However, they started by creating the SDKs from scratch and soon enough found out that it was just as long a process as API development.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We learned that it takes almost as long to do the API implementation as it did the SDK development. In fact, it took one week to develop the SDK for a single language.” &#8211; Brian Hyder, Engineering Manager</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">When they began designing their next micro-service, Dude Solutions started looking for alternate ways for SDK development and came across APIMatic. The autogeneration of SDKs in multiple languages helped drastically cut down SDK development and maintenance costs.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Development time for SDKs for each language went from 1 week to 18 seconds thanks to APIMatic.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">&nbsp;</p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-1695 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/dude-solutions.png" alt="" width="603" height="393"></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">While they had initially planned to provide SDKs in 3 languages, the significant time and cost reduction enabled them to provide SDKs for 7 languages with APIMatic’s autogenerated SDKs.</span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/automate-all-the-things-how-dude-solutions-saved-20-000-in-development-costs-using-apimatic-f9c05118f041"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Dude Solutions Cut Down Time to Release from 1 Week to 18 Seconds</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel APIs: Client Onboarding Time Reduced by 20% for Didgigo</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://www.didgigo.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> is a digital media platform that assists travel agents in organizing and maintaining data, as well as creating detailed itinerary proposals that save time and boost sales opportunities for clients.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Didgigo offers APIs that allow travel experts to create travel documents for their clients automatically and publish both digital and print versions at the same time. However, for a firm that excels at offering automated tailor-made solutions to its clients, it became critical to find a solution that could shorten the API onboarding time for customers, without the engineering team having to context switch on each release.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our process was extremely manual and required a lot of back and forth” &#8211; Keanu Ashwell, Development Operations Engineer</span></i></span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">With APIMatic’s autogenerated documentation in multiple languages, Didgigo is able to shift its focus on building robust APIs, without having to devote time and resources to maintain the documentation. The customer onboarding process has become more streamlined, with tickets raised during onboarding being <strong>reduced by 11-20%</strong>, and customer onboarding meetings going down by more than 7 meetings per quarter.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our experience with APIMatic and its provisions has been exceptional. We haven&#8217;t had </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">much time to maintain everything as we&#8217;re still strapped for resources due to COVID-19, </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">but we&#8217;ve still been able to rely on APIMatic to give our API users an understanding of </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">what functionality we expose via our APIs. The ability to test [the APIs] is also a feature I </span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">love and something that drew me to the service when we migrated from our in-house Swagger solution.”</span></i></span></p>
<p class="">Case Study: <a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/api-portal/didgigo/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">How Didgigo Reduces Client Onboarding Time with Autogenerated Documentation</span></a></p>
<h2 class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Healthcare/Senior Living APIs: Time to Release Down by 30% for Caremerge</span></h2>
<p class=""><a href="https://caremerge.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">is an </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">all-in-one platform that empowers families, residents, and staff of senior citizens by </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">providing tools for modern elder care including family engagement, community engagement, chronic care management, and more.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caremerge also uses various pre-existing services to make them more accessible for these senior citizens, for example with voice commands. However, managing all these services in a single platform requires multiple internal microservices and a public API.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Caremerge API powers communication between the services they offer and allows them to build integrations with various third-party vendors and services. Building those integrations requires the documentation for the API to be always updated, so developers spend less time figuring out how to integrate.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using APIMatic’s autogenerated API documentation with the API playground allows developers to test inputs and outputs within the docs, resulting in quicker integration of the API, and helps Caremerge cut down on time spent on maintenance.</span></p>
<p class=""><span style="color: #999999;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">“APIMatic helps us save 20–30% of the time it took us to manage documentation for our API” &#8211; </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fahad Aziz, Co-Founder, and CTO</span></em></span></p>
<p class="">Read More: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/serving-the-senior-living-industry-with-caremerge-api-734da95b2d9b"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Serving The Senior Living Industry with Caremerge</span></a></p>
<div class="row bg-editor-hr-wrap">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<p class=""><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quicker synchronization of documentation and SDKs with APIs leads to shorter sprints and faster time to market. With a mission to make API consumption as simple as possible, APIMatic considers it a victory when our</span><a href="https://www.apimatic.io/success-stories/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> customers’ APIs are consumed</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more readily with our autogenerated SDKs and documentation.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2022/02/the-customers-pov-how-do-sdks-and-api-documentation-help-business/">How Are SDKs and API Documentation Helping API Industries?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Psd2]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=627</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>FinTech Startups have leveraged upon the utility of Web APIs to dominate the financial services industry, and traditional financial institutes are following suit, executing strategies like the&#160; Open Banking&#160; initiative, to expose their services. When so many options are available, putting out an API is never enough, it’s essential to make sure developers can actually [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/">Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="627" class="elementor elementor-627">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-68285476 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="68285476" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-31224221" data-id="31224221" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-44df238c elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="44df238c" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
			<style>/*! elementor - v3.6.4 - 13-04-2022 */
.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-stacked .elementor-drop-cap{background-color:#818a91;color:#fff}.elementor-widget-text-editor.elementor-drop-cap-view-framed .elementor-drop-cap{color:#818a91;border:3px solid;background-color:transparent}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap{margin-top:8px}.elementor-widget-text-editor:not(.elementor-drop-cap-view-default) .elementor-drop-cap-letter{width:1em;height:1em}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap{float:left;text-align:center;line-height:1;font-size:50px}.elementor-widget-text-editor .elementor-drop-cap-letter{display:inline-block}</style>				<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="alignnone wp-image-628" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_sBXfWZNYodHGMEjtg17YKQ-1024x512.jpg" alt="Popular Developer Experience Practices in FinTech and Banking APIs" width="1024" height="512"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="743e" class="">FinTech Startups have leveraged upon the utility of Web APIs to dominate the financial services industry, and traditional financial institutes are following suit, executing strategies like the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/o/open-banking.asp"> Open Banking&nbsp; </a>initiative, to expose their services.</p>
<p id="a8fb" class="">When so many options are available, putting out an API is never enough, it’s essential to make sure developers can actually make use of the API in an effective and efficient manner. And for this, we have analyzed some popular APIs from both the Open Banking and FinTech Space. We evaluated these APIs using our Developer Experience checklist as a reference, which has been endorsed by industry experts like Kin Lane, Adam Duvander and more</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="aligncenter wp-image-630" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Sd1gAl5zc8GjfcY3Mi4MCw-1.jpg" alt="" width="567" height="441"></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b918">The list of APIs derived from multiple resources, including RapidAPI, GoMedic, etc. include:</p>
<ul class="">
<li><em>Barclays APIs</em></li>
<li><em>Nordea Bank</em></li>
<li><em>Citi APIs</em></li>
<li><em>Deutsche Bank</em></li>
<li><em>Stripe</em></li>
<li><em>Square</em></li>
<li><em>Visa</em></li>
<li><em>CoinAPI</em></li>
</ul>
<p id="afad">For the study, we analyzed, their publicly available resources, including their developer portals, product pages, and all underlying documentation and components.</p>
<p id="49a0">We have summarized our research in the form of a table to give you a quick overview of both Banking and FinTech APIs in terms of what they are offering.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-631 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_buxsZK1nfOKAtciwSwysOg.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="6743">And then further discuss in depth and detail, how each of these vendors has gone about with individual components.</p>
<h2 id="1a0c" class="">1. Citibank</h2>
<p id="e44a" class=""><a href="https://sandbox.developerhub.citi.com/us/home">Citibank’s</a>&nbsp;API program comprises of 11 APIs in total, the documentation for all of which they have available on a single developer portal. Their developer portal which they call the “Developer Hub” comes with a beautiful Landing Page, which features their API Catalog, Getting Started Guides, Use Cases and Success Stories.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-632 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_Z1wTN5ipavKTJKGh8kSbBw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="46c1">This is followed by a brief preview of some sample API Calls and Responses, which they do rather intuitively.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-633 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_JxdaUGEX-QsGevwEbgSxpA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b6a0">Landing pages are where consumers usually make their choice and it’s important you help them make it by selling a value proposition, and Citibank builds on that beautifully.</p>
<p id="5ecd">Signing Up is pretty easy, straightforward, and requires just a username and passwords, upon activation, you are allowed to generate your own API keys. Most of the portal is accessible without logging in, which is essential for a portal of any nature in this age.</p>
<p id="cc95" class="">The API Catalog page displays all their APIs in a very organized manner, classified according to function and location, they are easy to search and browse. Each API has an in detailed Overview Page, which explains what an API does and how does it do it. Since Citi Banks serves different markets, their pages and documentation is specifically curated for each region.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-634 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_oNnGMYt60NKEZc09o5h4hw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="5871" class="">Citi Bank’s API Playground lets you play around with their APIs in a really intuitive manner. It takes in your Client ID and Secret to generate an access token, following which you chose an app to make a sample call, with parameters you want to experiment with.</p>
<p id="72ee">The Documentation pages start with a short summary of what the API does, followed by authorization instructions. The endpoints are grouped according to function and can be accessed via sidebar navigation.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-635 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_VAqtcC1IU74RrJ-vX7xmJw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="bcbc">The endpoints for each group are first listed, and then explained in detail. The descriptions are accompanied by Code Samples in 8 languages. CitiBank adds a really interesting touch to how these samples are displayed by offering a light and dark mode and making them copy-paste ready. For each API call, they also list and explain the possible responses and error messages in cases applicable. They also give out a swagger specification for each API.</p>
<p id="41a9" class="">The FAQs section covers all topics from registration to security in detail and tries to answer as many questions as possible. The Sales and Support pages provide an email interface to request help from their teams.</p>
<p id="8de5">Their portal overall looks really neat and clean is simple to use and looks like it does belong from the CitiBank line of products.</p>
<h2 id="89c6">2. Deutsche Bank</h2>
<p id="8015" class=""><a href="https://developer.db.com/">Deutsche Bank&nbsp; </a>offers around 9 APIs, grouped by function and all cataloged on their Developer Portal, which in their navy blue and grey colors, looks beautiful. On the landing page of the portal, they communicate important announcements, updates, and features straight at the top, which is followed by a listing of their API Products.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-636 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_U844WNNZStZlgZYom7PPoA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="05c5" class="">Deutsche then builds on trust by highlighting their advanced security protocols, since that’s a big concern for developers before working with any kind of financial gateway. Addressing potential interests as such, early on, can help you hook visitors even before they explore your code. Deutsche understands that and builds on it by exhibiting their beautiful API Explorer next.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-637 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_8tGFG4yeRr7DwuoCuDuF5Q.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8840">Following that they present a customer story to explain a common use case, and then display the ideal user journey with the help of visuals. Deutsche makes use of visuals to explain workflows and inner workings of their APIs at various places.</p>
<p id="d679" class="">Their portal also features news and events channels, where they highlight latest releases, new features, publish their events and talk about new ideas. This sort of engagement plays a crucial role in connecting with the community, which they successfully do.</p>
<p id="ce02">Each API has a pretty rich Overview page, which talks about the features of an API, explains what it does, pricing plans, and then links to the API Explorer so developers can get to experiment with it straight away.</p>
<p id="af18">Getting started guides are really thorough and explain how to register an account and apply for authorization keys. Reference Docs are beautiful, with endpoints for each API grouped together and each endpoint with every parameter is explained in detail.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-638 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_eW6RhLBKzYUHyWWTu_fJ-A.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="2553">The interactive API explorer allows to make sample calls straight away and displays potential responses according to the type of call made.</p>
<p id="7730">Deutsche goes an extra mile with support and allows users to request features, contact them for general inquiries, seek troubleshooting support, or report bugs all from the same page. The FAQs page pretty much explain everything and serve as an excellent self-servicing support option.</p>
<p id="aaec">We love the slick UI, and the use of visuals that Deutsche makes, everything is pretty easy to understand, although they lack a few basic components, that could have elevated their developer experience even further.</p>
<h2 id="7821">3.&nbsp; Nordea Open Banking</h2>
<p id="3238" class=""><a href="https://developer.nordeaopenbanking.com/app/">Nordea Bank</a>&nbsp;offers one of the best onboarding techniques we have seen in any portal across any industry, they take users across the entire journey from registering, setting up an app, to generating API keys and everything, with beautiful visuals and step by step content.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-639 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_fvgKszBdWB74IMHiel2mfA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0e2d" class="">With that, they also offer training videos for multiple scenarios, Swagger and Postman collections for all APIs and sample code, which can be accessed on their GitHub.</p>
<p id="1477">The Landing Page is beautiful and builds upon the value the bank delivers via their APIs, we loved how they have testimonials as social proof and then evangelize the open banking industry as a whole with articles and blogs straight on the Landing Page.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-640 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_04n0Xe9uX_aBFB65UHvxgQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="1d3d">Nordea also deals with multiple APIs, each with an Overview Page, that helps customers understand what they can achieve with it, Nordea uses visuals to explain how their APIs work. To build up trust further, they have their API roadmaps up, so evaluating developers can foresee what the future would look like, helping them make a solid well-informed decision.</p>
<p id="381f" class="">Documentation for APIs starts with Change Logs and Version release notes. We believe that is a really important practice, early on educating users, what preliminary actions they have to take before going on with implementation are really important. We love how they set out the context, and answer any sort of considerations such as security concerns, terminology, rate limiting and all other queries a user may have before they actually get to documentation.</p>
<p id="7c35">The Reference docs are beautiful, come with a detailed description of parameters, sample call request, and responses and an API Console where those calls can be tried out and tested.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-641 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_UUS5QtbansjtDK7MWt-nTw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="9fa3" class="">The endpoints are listed on the sidebar, from where they are easily navigable. Nordea gives out OpenAPI spec for each API and recommend to generate client libraries on Swagger CodeGen but do not have that listed as an offering anywhere on their portal, and have a few languages agnostic code samples listed on their GitHub.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-642 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_mVoY-OQjtIvfZCVWBb5yRQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="5f7c">The support section once again does a great job, covers up pretty much everything with FAQs and provides an option to seek help by raising tickets or discussing issues with the community.</p>
<h2 id="eff2" class="">4. Barclays’s API</h2>
<p id="ed81" class=""><a href="https://developer.barclays.com/">Barclay’s API&nbsp; </a>program is one of the largest in the industry, with over 12 well-maintained APIs and more in experimental phases, they have made sure they deliver a great developer experience.</p>
<p id="c59d" class="">Their developer portal is the face of their API program and they have managed the entire project beautifully.</p>
<p id="57ac" class="">On the Landing Page, they send out a very bold message about their mission, and with that list their APIs, customer stories, use cases and talk about open banking overall. Building upon the value of their offering is something that all API providers have done in this space and we cannot stress how important that is considering the competition in this fast-paced industry.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-643 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_rVKQVWYGDJVClxHLGuyOBw.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="65e8" class="">The next most important thing on a portal is an API Overview Page and Barclay’s does a wonderful job, making use of video content to explain the offering. They highlight all key features and benefits and explain what customers would need to get started.</p>
<p id="ad0f">Registering an account is standard practice and takes no longer than a minute, getting started guides are in fair detail and depth as well, covering everything from key features, version history, to prerequisites.</p>
<p id="35f8">The Reference Docs do a fair job in explaining what an endpoint does and comes with code samples in some cases. Barclay’s also gives out an API Specification in RAML format for their APIs, so that you can make use of complementary tooling and take maximum advantage out of it.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-644 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_hAKD7gXoFC516OVW1bLg4Q.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="470f" class="">The FAQs section which they call their knowledge Base does a decent job explaining the ins and outs of the program on top of which they have to get in touch option, so consumers can approach them at any given time.</p>
<h2 id="4fc7">5.&nbsp; Square</h2>
<p id="c05e"><a href="https://squareup.com/us/en/developers">Square</a>&nbsp;is one of the leading payment processing companies in the US, and they made that possible, with easy to integrate services and great developer experience. With an API first model, they have enabled both hardware and software to seamlessly integrate and provide a butter smooth experience.</p>
<p id="9192" class="">To make their APIs easy to consume, they tick almost all major things on the developer checklist. Their developer portal looks great, is easy to navigate, and makes use of visuals for explanations where necessary.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-645 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_jp1Bs05rOfDwpyyX7p96jA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="e657" class="">The Landing Page highlights all major features, benefits, pricing plans, customer stories, sample apps and support channels that a visitor may require to begin with.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-646 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZRb7WbHCLFasEkBavOAI9w.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="2a40">The Documentation Page begins with a step by step guide on how to get started on their platform, registering an account, generating authorization keys and handling errors, etc. Square strongly believes that developers get help implementing their APIs in languages they are comfortable with and hence give out multiple SDKs in multiple platforms, which they proudly present on their portal before everything. This is followed by a few sample applications where developers can take inspiration from. They then list out their APIs, each API has an Overview Page, where they talk about how to use it, work with it, prerequisites and pricing.</p>
<p id="829c">The Reference Docs which they call, Technical References, are put out in a three — column architecture, the in-app postman button allows testing out Sample Requests and views their responses.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-647 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_jLci1f78TTheTq3QgqXbbA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="ca97">The docs are really well done and coupled together with SDKs, make it very easy to integrate their services into any system, no matter what the platform. A reason that many modern companies chose to go with services as such, saving implementation time and cost at their end.</p>
<p id="d7e9">Square has a developer blog, newsletter, a dedicated slack channel and an email widget built into their portal, so any developer can reach out to them anytime.</p>
<h2 id="4ffd" class="">6.&nbsp; Stripe</h2>
<p id="1332"><a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a>&nbsp;offers one of the best if not the absolute best developer experience, not only in the FinTech space but in the entire API industry. They offer everything that makes API consumption easy and hence comes as no surprise that they are one of the most popular payment processing platforms today.</p>
<p id="5bd6" class="">Stripe deal in several APIs, and on their landing page catalog them in a way which makes it really easy for developers to figure out what they need. Developers can check out these APIs straight away on their try it out section which comes straight after. This is followed by development guides and other tips which may help developers jump-start their platforms.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-648 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_qNBkJK3isl3rHINeDli3gQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="af6e" class="">Where Stripe wins is that they on-board non-developer decision makers as well, and have a comprehensive guide explaining their offering in a non-technical way and not only that, they have pre-built plug-ins and extensions which can be configured to trigger their APIs, allowing non-developer users take advantage of what they have to offer.</p>
<p id="bc42">Each API has an Overview Page which thoroughly explains what consumers can achieve from that API. Stripe goes an extra mile and helps users implement APIs in a number of ways, including pre-built UI components for both Web and Mobile, along with SDKs in multiple platforms. The guides section is full of code samples and instructions for each kind of implementation, including the necessary CSS or styling files that go with it.</p>
<p id="69be">The Getting Started Guides are platform specific, so users have no trouble setting up their environments or IDEs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-649 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_xUDhmY2weHITfL_Ti1-XIQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="30d5">They make use of visuals where they can to explain workflows and journeys, which they present in a very engaging manner.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-650 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZMPqddEakPYNg8l2urEsDA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="97ed">The Reference Docs give a really clean look and very easy to go through, there’ s no clutter or confusion, each endpoint in explained in detail, and come with Code samples in multiple languages including Ruby, Python, PHP, Java, Node, .NET and GO.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-651 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_meK6rJlTjqgS2VbtsfHHSA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="f2c0">They have forums and discussion boards where developers can engage with the community anytime to solve their queries, on top of which representatives from Stripe are always on the look around to guide anyone in need. Alternatively, their team can also be reached out via email, chat or phone. With their Developer digest, they effectively communicate any changes and updates to their users, which is an opt-in service, with the widget available on the landing page.</p>
<p id="0f93" class="">We love how they have made their platform accessible to global communities and render all of their documentation it in around 7 languages, earning them bonus accessibility points.</p>
<p id="9e64">Stripe completes everything that is on our Developer Experience checklist and it should come as no surprise that it is the number 1 choice for so many businesses when it comes to payment processing.</p>
<h2 id="e101">7. Visa</h2>
<p id="baf5"><a href="https://developer.visa.com/">Visa</a>&nbsp;is one of the largest payment networks across the world, that facilitates millions of electronic transactions per minute. The service is made available to vendors and businesses through a number of APIs and plug-ins.</p>
<p id="7286">Visa’s Developer Center is one of the most beautiful Developer Experience platforms we have seen, it encompasses all their values, branding and visuals to deliver a delightful experience. On the Landing Page, straight on the top, they have a scroll where they advertise their devrel events, ask for feedback and present their tutorials.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-652 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_-afTH4rlFSJLIFTLeoQBsQ.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="fa88" class="">After that, they list their API catalog, which can be further browsed in detail, along with that they mention multiple use cases over various verticals and industries. We love how they present their Customer Stories, which they do in the form of videos, which are engaging and beautiful captivate the attention of landing visitors.</p>
<p id="08c1">On the catalog page, the APIs are grouped together according to function and can be browsed using filters on the left. Each API has an in detail Overview Page, which explains what the API is for, who can use it, how are they supposed to priced and their regional availability.</p>
<p id="3183">They make use of visuals were required to explain key features, workflows and supporting APIs.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-653 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_3vqm1iafbyh-I10K_AjCjA.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="8c7e">The Getting Started Guides are really through and explains step by step how to make use of APIs, the reference docs are presented in a three column architecture, with sample calls and responses, that can be tried out on their interactive API Explorer.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-654 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_qtfBVr8xMyG9LcKRT1a-Gg.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="cea7" class="">Where we found Visa to be leading, is how they communicate with users, all types of messaging are really rich, vibrant and deliver their point across in a beautiful manner.</p>
<p id="2b21">They have separate pages for Release Notes, Glossary, Support where they have FAQs, a whole About Us page where they explain why to use any of Visa APIs at all and a Contact Us page which directs you to an email widget.</p>
<p id="8fac">On top of that, they have a Developer blog, where they keep posting the latest news, updates and tips about their services, and a community page where users can come discuss and solve each other’s problems.</p>
<p id="4b10" class="">Developer Experience is more than just Docs and Visa treating their APIs like products truly proves that, no wonder they are where they stand today.</p>
<h2 id="1678"><strong>8. CoinAPI</strong></h2>
<p id="2b30" class="">CoinAPI is a unique cryptocurrency API that combines data from all virtual currency exchanges and makes it available through a single platform. The API provides incredible utility to cryptocurrency traders and has become a huge hit in the space. What has made the API so successful is the ease when it comes to consuming it. Through their documentation practices, they have made it really easy to work with the many endpoints and terabytes of data they have to offer.</p>
<p id="987e">When you land on their site, you are taken straight away to the product pages which are beautifully done.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-655 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_n-cQwQ7AAzORIaWaZAy7ew.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="19c4">The pages cover everything, from the exceptional value the API provides, to the social proof, uses cases and how client libraries are available in multiple languages.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-656 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_gXfChIGczKqlDoaWQUSi2g.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="893d" class="">The documentation site is done in the same branding and looks striking in their navy blue. The landing page for the documentation site gives a thorough explanation of their API programs, which is divided into three distinct protocols, REST, WebSocket and FIX. This ensures they keep developers across all boards happy since REST is a popular API format overall and other two popular in the finance space.</p>
<p id="278d">After that, they talk about the SDKs which the offer in 15 languages. For them the SDKs are an integral part of their offerings, hence are well tested and well maintained and they encourage the use of it, while also accepting suggestions to their main repository from the community.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-657 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_52_Xw6Ldw9JIRTNiPhBB1w.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="b77f">This is followed by security protocols, and the standards and conventions the APIs follow.</p>
<p id="bda5">CoinAPI does a wonderful job educating users, on how and where to get started with their APIs, before they nosedive into development and we give them full points for that. All three APIs have a short overview which explains how to work with that particular format, along with necessary details such as authorization, request limits, etc.</p>
<p id="a921">The Reference Docs are presented in a really neat manner, have nicely done descriptions, and come with code samples in 9 languages. We love the way they do their warnings, disclaimers, and tips, making them extremely legible.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-658 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_EUHWgbjJSOmdgnoGLKdevA-1024x343.png" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="0e8b">They have a dedicated page for support, where they have separate tabs for FAQs, Security &amp; Privacy, Announcements, Billing and Subscriptions, answering every potential query a user might run across. CoinAPI gets full marks for communication as well, the support page is easy to navigate, has a search function and serves as an effective communication channel between them and consuming developers.</p>
<p id="a8dd">Coming from an industry that is still emerging, it’s impressive how they check most of the things from the Developer Experience checklist. And their wide adoption should come as no surprise.</p>
<p id="c17a">Summarizing the research we found out, although most of these APIs offer a number of components from the Developer Experience checklist, it’s FinTech APIs that has taken the lead by offering SDKs and investing more in thier documentation practises. A developer coming in for a payment solution is more likely going to choose an API, which has an implementation available in a language they are comfortable with and is more convenient to use, hence no wonder Stripe and Square are global leaders today.</p>
<p id="889f" class="">If you are in the Finance industry, you too can offer an amazing developer experience for your API, and without putting in the hard work, time or dedicating resources. We can help you get started with your developer experience program from the Landing Pages, to Docs, Code Samples, SDKs, and everything.&nbsp;</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis/">Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</title>
		<link>/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[APIMatic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 11:02:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API Portal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Developer Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FinTech APIs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SDK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[API]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software Development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://devapi.dream.press/?p=660</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Banking and Finance industry is one of the most heavily regulated sectors of the world. The regulations, although important to protect the integrity of the system and customer interest, come at the cost of hindered advancement and such had been the case for the industry. This was until the rise of FinTech companies, who [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/">State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="660" class="elementor elementor-660">
									<section class="elementor-section elementor-top-section elementor-element elementor-element-34f857ff elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default" data-id="34f857ff" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
					<div class="elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column elementor-element elementor-element-4aea8260" data-id="4aea8260" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-widget-wrap elementor-element-populated">
								<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-4a141574 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="4a141574" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
							<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-661 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_AwRHHaXNeo1O2pu7hQz8ag-1024x512.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="d6ac" class="">The Banking and Finance industry is one of the most heavily regulated sectors of the world. The regulations, although important to protect the integrity of the system and customer interest, come at the cost of hindered advancement and such had been the case for the industry.</p>
<p id="db59" class="">This was until the rise of FinTech companies, who leveraged APIs as gateways to expose traditional financial services so that third-party developers could build custom solutions on top of them. There’s a lot you can achieve with FinTech APIs, without having to go through the labor of manually implementing any functionality.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>A simple query on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.programmableweb.com/search/financial"> ProgrammableWeb</a>shows there are&nbsp;<em>1956</em>&nbsp;APIs listed under the tag of Financial APIs, with around&nbsp;<em>290</em>&nbsp;listed this very year.</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="e432" class="">FinTech APIs are putting immense pressure on Traditional Banking and Financial Organisations, who are actively trying to catch up. Customers today expect advanced, frictionless experiences and banks with traditional business models are failing to provide them.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-662 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_o6g31nFwrWSkx9twG7rzOw.jpg" alt=""></p>
<figcaption>A stat from EY’s FinTech Adoption Index shows that globally, 64% of “Digitally active consumers” are using FinTech applications in favor of traditional banking ones.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="d65f" class="">When <a href="https://assets.ey.com/content/dam/ey-sites/ey-com/en_gl/topics/banking-and-capital-markets/ey-global-fintech-adoption-index.pdf">Ernst and Young&nbsp; </a>conducted their first study on FinTech adoption in 2015, they found adoption rates for FinTech as low as 10% amongst the consumers they surveyed. The number rose to 33% in 2017 and now stands at 64%. More and more individuals especially millennials, are shying away from traditional banking and instead are inclined more towards digital solutions put out by these FinTech companies.</p>
<p id="4c55" class="">It’s clearly time for banks to explore newer business models and to expose data and functionality in a similar fashion, acting as the infrastructure or platform on which financial services of the future are built. Else tech giants or startups in the space will ultimately wipe them over.</p>
<h2 id="d558" class="">Open Banking and Europe’s PSD2</h2>
<p id="9911" class="">In 2015 the European Parliament adopted new legislation, Payment Services Directive 2 better known as <a href="https://www.ecb.europa.eu/paym/intro/mip-online/2018/html/1803_revisedpsd.en.html">PSD2</a>, to streamline the digitalisation of banks and financial services. The directive obligates banks across Europe to make banking data and services available to third-party developers, so they can build value-added services on top of them.</p>
<p id="dca9">The concept of Open Banking, on the other hand, has been around for much longer and it suggests that banks provide access to user data via Open APIs, so that they can partner with external entities to improve customer experience.</p>
<p id="0b6b" class="">The Open Banking Initiative is powering PSD2 today, for which deadlines are running out and banks are putting out APIs on a daily basis. The directive has provided Banks with an excellent opportunity to make their mark, tight deadlines have forced banks to work faster on API preparation, resulting in 529 Banking APIs publicly listed as of today.</p>
<p id="4a24">Banks, because of the initiative, and the legislation are on their way to make a comeback, but is just putting out an API enough?</p>
<h2 id="33c8" class="">Developer Experience Makes APIs Useable</h2>
<p id="5ca8" class="">Developers today have a wide array of choices. A number of Banking and Finance APIs today provide the same utility and services, some implementing them in a different manner, some adopting different technology stacks, but what truly sets these APIs apart is the ease when it comes to consumption.</p>
<p id="07ff" class="">Developers want to get started as soon as possible, spend as little time getting acquainted with the API, and focus more on building creative solutions on top of them. In order for an API to be widely adopted, it must have a great developer experience.</p>
<p id="0ba7" class="">Since Developer Experience is a huge deciding factor when it comes to adopting an API, we sat down and shortlisted 8 popular Banking and Finance APIs and analysed what they have to offer in terms of Developer Experience, and what makes them popular choices amongst developers.</p>
<p id="6fa9" class="">Using the famous Developer Experience checklist as criteria and point of reference, we noticed some common trends and practices, which are objectively summarised in the table below:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Read in detail what forms the Developer Experience Checklist for APIs: <a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/what-exactly-is-developer-experience-1646b813df14">What exactly is Developer Experience?</a></p>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<p class="mod-reset"><img class="wp-image-663" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_buxsZK1nfOKAtciwSwysOg-1.jpg" alt=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<p id="19ca" class="">Quickly skimming through the table you would notice that most of these APIs offer a number of components from the Developer Experience checklist, and hence comes as no surprise why they are doing so well. One area we saw FinTech APIs lead, was with offering API implementations in multiple languages, in the form of SDKs, so developers can instantly start making use of these APIs in languages they are comfortable with.</p>
<p id="91fc" class="">We further ran a detailed analysis to find out how these APIs have gone about with their Developer Experience and what sets them apart from each other and remaining of the competition, which you can go through here:&nbsp;<a href="https://blog.apimatic.io/popular-developer-experience-practices-fintech-and-banking-apis-a5474fe535e4"> Popular Developer Experience Practices: FinTech and Banking APIs.</a></p>
<h3 id="8e19"><strong>PSD2 is an Opportunity for Digital Transformation</strong></h3>
<p id="2287" class="">FinTech APIs have built popularity, cashing on the exemplary experiences they provide, both to developers and customers, and Banking APIs that have followed suit have done well. But this is not the case for every bank out there. PSD2, although very explicitly requires banks to open up data and banking functionalities, it does not specify how banks are supposed to meet these requirements, with many just checking them off with bare minimum implementations.</p>
<p id="8b13" class="">Banks that are looking to just adhere to regulatory requirements and not do more, may miss out on big opportunities to expand and grow new business models, and may not be able to put themselves on the map with FinTech APIs.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>According to a survey, only 59% of Europe’s 442 banks met PSD2’s 14th March deadline, to have a publicly available testing facility or a sandbox environment .</p>
</blockquote>
<p id="a963">Of course, it is easier said than done and many banks are still struggling to prepare their APIs, with most of them slacking behind. In order to fulfill legal requirements, the API experience gets second fiddle. While understandable, it leads to a missed opportunity nonetheless</p>
<p id="adf4" class="">With the final 29th September deadline looming ahead, a number of Banking APIs are going to hit the markets, and only the ones that come with a developer experience will catch all the buzz, leaving the rest trailing on traction.</p>
<h2 id="32b5" class="">Automation is the Key to Scaling Developer Experience</h2>
<p id="0227" class="">So where does this leave API teams today who are still working on their API and have no time or resources to work on the consumption part of it?</p>
<p id="8a9a" class="">And the answer lies in&nbsp;<strong>Automation</strong>.</p>
<p id="833d" class="">With all hands busy on deck working on the core functionality of APIs, there is no reason that resources have to be dedicated to just work on producing the artifacts that make APIs easier to consume. Instead, let the machines do the working for you!</p>
<p id="3749">A lot can be done with an API Specification today. The document, when passed through CodeGen engines, can drive entire Developer Experience(DX) for APIs with automatic generation of DX components. And not just Documentation or Portals, but also complex components like SDKs, Code Samples, API Explorers and can even CI/CD pipelines so none of this has to be updated manually.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:quote /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:heading /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:image -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large">
<figure id="attachment_664" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-664" style="width: 800px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-664" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/1_ZE_9hIZFJCH8to2mVeNeig.gif" alt="Generate DX Components with just an API Specification" width="800" height="450"><figcaption id="caption-attachment-664" class="wp-caption-text">Generate DX Components with just an API Specification</figcaption></figure>
</figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<div class="boldgrid-section">
<div class="container">
<div class="row">
<div class="col-md-12 col-xs-12 col-sm-12">
<h2 id="0f4d" class="">Get Started ASAP</h2>
<p id="5df6" class="">Where are you with Developer Experience for your APIs? Pushing for that 29th September Deadline and have no idea where to get started? Don’t worry about it.</p>
<p id="a7bb">Luckily for you, here at APIMatic, this is our specialty. We hold the necessary skills and expertise to help you set up an automated Developer Experience solution, and with our in-house technology, can get you running within weeks!</p>
<p id="f9ff" class="">You can always&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/contact">reach out to our team</a>&nbsp;to discuss Developer Experience and we’ll help you find an easy way out that fits your need. There’s no reason you have to stay behind and not compete with the top Banking and FinTech APIs of today.&nbsp;<a href="https://apimatic.io/account/register"> Get started&nbsp; </a>as soon as you can!</p>
<p class="">Thanks to&nbsp;Adam DuVander.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->

<!-- wp:paragraph /-->						</div>
				</div>
					</div>
		</div>
							</div>
		</section>
							</div>
		<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/2019/07/state-of-developer-experience-banking-and-fintech-2019/">State of Developer Experience: Banking and FinTech 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">APIMatic</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
